<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Iqbal's Weblog</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/ja/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/ja/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://iqbalabdullah.net/ja/</id><updated>2024-05-23T20:27:00+09:00</updated><entry><title>Python Software Foundation (PSF) で Pythonista をノミネートしよう</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/ja/posts/2024/05/nominating-pythonistas-at-the-psf/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-05-20T09:20:00+09:00</published><updated>2024-05-23T20:27:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabdullah.net,2024-05-20:/ja/posts/2024/05/nominating-pythonistas-at-the-psf/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;PSF で仲間の Pythonista をノミネートするための README&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;PSF であなたの好きな頑張っている人やグループをノミネートして、彼らの仕事を認めることができるって知っていましたか？しかもこれがすべて無料でできるんです！（無料と言っても無料のお茶みたいな感じで）&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;彼らを認めて感謝しよう: 仲間の Pythonista をノミネートする&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2014 年以前、Python Software Foundation (PSF) には正式なノミネーションプロセスや基準がありませんでした。PSF がオープンメンバーシップ組織に移行したとき（基本的に誰でも PSF のメンバーになれるという意味です）、コミュニティのメンバーに特別な認識を与えるための正式なノミネーションプロセスが作られました。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2024 年の PyCon US では、私の経験を共有し、このトピックに関する質問に答えるためにオープンスペースを行いました。会議の閉会時に、PSF のエグゼクティブディレクターである &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/denicholson/"&gt;Deb Nicholson&lt;/a&gt; さんがステージに上がり、今年はノミネーションが不足しているため、コミュニティサービス賞 (CSA) を授与できなかったことを指摘しました。毎年たくさんの素晴らしいことが行われているのに、誰も CSA に値しないとは考えにくいので、私たちのコミュニティがこのようなノミネーションができることを十分に認識していないのだと思います。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;何をノミネートできるの？&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CSA だけじゃありません。仲間の Pythonista を以下のようなものにノミネートできます：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PSF フェロー&lt;/strong&gt;: PSF フェローメンバーシップは、Python コミュニティに重要な貢献をした個人に与えられる特別なメンバーシップです。これには、Python の開発への貢献、インフラのサポート、イベントの企画、その他の影響力のある活動が含まれます。PSF フェローのノミネーションは &lt;a href="https://wiki.python.org/psf/FellowWG/Charter"&gt;PSF フェロー ワークグループ&lt;/a&gt; によって処理され、決定されます。詳細は &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/fellows/"&gt;PSF フェローメンバーシップページ&lt;/a&gt; をご覧ください。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PSF コミュニティサービス賞&lt;/strong&gt;: これが CSA です。Python コミュニティのために特別なボランティアサービスを行った個人やグループを認めます。イベントの企画、教育リソースへの貢献、コミュニティイニシアティブのサポートなど、さまざまな方法でコミュニティを改善するために多大な時間と労力を費やした人々を称賛します。CSA の授与は PSF ボードによって決定されます。詳細は &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/community/awards/psf-awards/"&gt;PSF コミュニティサービス賞ページ&lt;/a&gt; にあります。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Outstanding PyLady Award&lt;/strong&gt;: この賞は、Python コミュニティ内で多様性を促進し、女性や性別少数派を支援する PyLadies コミュニティに重要な貢献をした個人に与えられます。メンタリング、イベントの企画、包括的な環境の育成において卓越した活動を行った人々を称えます。Outstanding PyLady Award の授与は PyLadies グローバルカウンシルによって決定されます。この賞についての詳細は &lt;a href="https://kit.pyladies.com/en/latest/global/award.html"&gt;こちら&lt;/a&gt; をご覧ください。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PSF 功労賞&lt;/strong&gt;: これは財団の最高賞です。PSF 功労賞は、Python コミュニティへの継続的な模範的貢献に対する認識の申し出です。この賞は、コードの貢献、コミュニティ活動への努力、その他の手段を通じて Python の世界を形作る重要な影響を与える行動に対して授与されます。コミュニティサービス賞と同様に、コミュニティへのこのようなサービスが認識と報酬につながることを示すことが意図されており、貢献者に直接的なインセンティブを提供することが目的ではありません。この賞について詳しくは&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/community/awards/psf-distinguished-awards/"&gt;こちら&lt;/a&gt;をご覧ください。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;これらの賞と認識は、世界中の Pythonista の貴重な貢献を強調し、祝う素晴らしい方法です。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PSF ボードディレクターシップ&lt;/strong&gt;: これは賞ではなく責任ですが、ディレクターシップへのノミネートも意味があります。PSF ボードオブディレクターは、財団の活動を監督し、その使命が効果的に実行されるようにします。ボードディレクターは PSF メンバーシップによって選出され、戦略的な意思決定とガバナンスにおいて重要な役割を果たします。詳細は &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/"&gt;PSF ボード選挙ページ&lt;/a&gt; をご覧ください。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;なぜノミネートするべきなの？&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Python Software Foundation (PSF) 内で誰かをノミネートすることは、ただの形式ではありません。これは、Python コミュニティのメンバーがエコシステムに投資した努力と献身を祝福し、認める強力な方法です。個人やグループを認めることは：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ポジティブなコミュニティ精神を促進&lt;/strong&gt;: 貢献を認めることで、感謝とモチベーションの文化を育て、より多くの人々がコミュニティに参加し、貢献することを奨励します。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;多様な貢献を強調&lt;/strong&gt;: 異なる個人の仕事を認めることで、コード、コミュニティの組織化、教育、アドボカシーなど、人々が貢献できるさまざまな方法を示します。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;継続的な関与を奨励&lt;/strong&gt;: コミュニティメンバーに賞を与えることで、彼らの仕事が評価され、注目されていることを知り、努力を続ける動機になります。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;強いネットワークを構築&lt;/strong&gt;: 成果を祝うことで、コミュニティ内のつながりを強化し、メンバー間の協力とサポートを促進します。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;私たちはギフトエコノミーの中で生きています。ギフトが私たちの世界を動かしています。オープンソースはギフトです。オープンソースを支えるために人々が行う無償の労働もギフトです。年齢、性別、経済状況、教育レベルに関係なく、人々を私たちのコミュニティに歓迎することもギフトです。コミュニティの仲間に感謝し、認めることも彼らへの恩返しとなるギフトです。Naomi Ceder は彼女の &lt;a href="https://www.naomiceder.tech/posts/pycon_keynote_2022/"&gt;A Time of Gifts キーノート&lt;/a&gt; でこれを最もよく表現しています。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;しかし、認識プロセスが包括的であり、多様な Python グローバルコミュニティを代表するものであることが重要です。特定のグループは、技術とコミュニティリーダーシップの役割で過小評価されてきました。例えば、私の地域（東アジア、南アジア、東南アジア）のコミュニティは、約 500 人の PSF フェローと約 100 人の CSA 受賞者のうち、18 の PSF フェローシップと 2 人の CSA 受賞者（1 グループを代表する）しかいませんでした。これは全体の約 4% と 2% にすぎません。世界中に約 &lt;a href="https://thefortunate.blog/diversification-is-the-future-for-the-psf.html"&gt;820 万人の Python 開発者またはユーザーがいる&lt;/a&gt; と考えると、私の地域での最大の成長があるとき、それは明らかに過小評価されています。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;どのようにノミネートするの？&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PSF で誰かを認識するためにノミネートするプロセスは簡単です：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;カテゴリーを特定する&lt;/strong&gt;: ノミネートしたい個人やグループに最も適した賞や認識を決定します。これには、PSF フェロー、コミュニティサービス賞、ボードディレクターシップ、または Outstanding PyLady Award が含まれます。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ノミネーションを準備する&lt;/strong&gt;: ノミネートする人の情報を集めます。これには、Python コミュニティへの貢献、具体的な業績、その他関連する詳細が含まれます。ノミネーションは、なぜその人が認識に値するのかを強調するべきです。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ノミネーションを提出する&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PSF フェロー&lt;/strong&gt; のノミネーションはメールで提出できます。詳細は PSF フェローメンバーシップページでご覧ください &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/fellows/"&gt;こちら&lt;/a&gt;。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;コミュニティサービス賞&lt;/strong&gt; の詳細と提出手順は、&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/community/awards/psf-awards/"&gt;PSF コミュニティサービス賞ページ&lt;/a&gt; にあります。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PSF ボードディレクターシップ&lt;/strong&gt; のノミネーションは通常、年次選挙プロセスの一部です。詳細は &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/"&gt;PSF ボード選挙ページ&lt;/a&gt; をご覧ください。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Outstanding PyLady Award&lt;/strong&gt; の詳細は &lt;a href="https://kit.pyladies.com/en/latest/global/award.html"&gt;こちら&lt;/a&gt; で確認できます。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PSF Distinguished Service Award&lt;/strong&gt; の詳細は&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/community/awards/psf-distinguished-awards/"&gt;こちら&lt;/a&gt; から確認できます。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;より良い代表性の必要性&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PSF は、&lt;a href="https://wiki.python.org/psf/DiversityandInclusionWG"&gt;D&amp;amp;I ワークグループ&lt;/a&gt; の設立や、2023 年にアフリカおよびアジアのコミュニティへの助成金の増加など、多様性と包括性の促進に向けた大きな進展を遂げましたが、個人やグループの仕事を認める上で、世界中の異なるコミュニティからのより良い代表性が必要です。多くの地域が PSF のリーダーシップと認識プログラムにおいて過小評価されています。この代表性の欠如は、新しい貢献者の参入障壁を生み出し、コミュニティ内のアイデアと視点の多様性を制限する可能性があります。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;これに対処するために、以下のことを行う必要があります：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;意識の向上&lt;/strong&gt;: 過小評価されているグループの間で、ノミネーションプロセスと認識の機会についての認識を高める。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;サポートの提供&lt;/strong&gt;: 多様な背景を持つ個人がノミネーションプロセスをナビゲートし、コミュニティと関わるのを助けるリソースとサポートを提供する。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;多様なノミネーションを奨励する&lt;/strong&gt;: 過小評価されている地域や背景を持つ個人のノミネーションを積極的に探し、奨励する。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;メンターシッププログラム&lt;/strong&gt;: 多様なコミュニティからの新しい貢献者を支援し、彼らが Python エコシステム内での旅を案内するメンターシッププログラムを確立する。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;これらのステップを踏むことで、PSF が Python コミュニティのグローバルで多様な性質を真に反映し、すべての貢献が評価され認識される包括的な環境を育むことができます。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;何ができるの？&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;たくさんあります！&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;まず、まだ PSF のメンバーでない場合は、&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/membership/"&gt;こちら&lt;/a&gt; からサインアップしましょう。コミュニティのために行った仕事が &lt;a href="https://psfmember.org/civicrm/contribute/transact/?reset=1&amp;amp;id=32"&gt;Managing, Contributing, または Supporting メンバー&lt;/a&gt; に該当する場合は、そのように認識されることを確認してください。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;次に、誰かをノミネートできます！コミュニティに長くいるなら、この記事を読んでいる間に思い浮かぶ人がいるはずです。誰もいない？本当に？例えば、新しい都市やコミュニティに来たときに、何人かの人に新人が関与するのに最適な人は誰かを尋ねてみます。そして、もし 75% の人が同じ名前を挙げるなら、その人はおそらく PSF フェローにふさわしい人物でしょう。その人を知り、彼らが行った仕事について話し始めることができます。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;コミュニティサービス賞（CSA）は理解しやすい基準がありますが、受け入れられるためのハードルは依然として高いです。一例として、私が行った PyCon JP 協会のノミネーションがあります（詳細は &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/records/board/resolutions/"&gt;こちら&lt;/a&gt; と &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/community/awards/psf-awards/#december-2021"&gt;こちら&lt;/a&gt; をご覧ください）。これはパンデミックの影響で財政的に大打撃を受けた PSF のために資金を集めるためのチャリティトークイベントを開催したことに対するものです。もう一つの最近の例は、&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/records/board/minutes/2024-03-13/#new-business"&gt;Leonard Richardson, Lais Cavalho と Raquel Dou が CSA を受け取ったことを認める&lt;/a&gt;もので、彼らが構築し維持してきたソフトウェアやコミュニティが全体としてのコミュニティに利益をもたらしたためです。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;功労賞 (DSA) は、はるかに高いハードルがあります。2012年にはじめて授与されて以来、これまでに7人しか受賞していません。時には CSA のノミネーションが DSA 授与につながることもありますが、それは PSF 理事会の判断に委ねられています。DSA が授与される理由については&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/community/awards/psf-distinguished-awards/"&gt;こちら&lt;/a&gt;をお読みいただき、他の受賞者と肩を並べるにふさわしいと思う方がいれば、ぜひノミネーションを行ってください。ノミネーションは&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/community/awards/psf-distinguished-awards/"&gt;こちら&lt;/a&gt;に記載されているように、PSF 理事会に電子メールでノミネートすることができます。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;もちろん、自己推薦することもできますが、私は個人的にはこれを非常に難しく、非常に退屈だと感じるので、それをすることには興味がありません。他の人について書く方が楽しいです！&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;最後に、これらのノミネーションを通じて、Pythonista の仲間を認識し、評価し、高める機会の認識を高める手助けをすることができます。PyCon や Python ミートアップにいるとき、自己紹介にこれまでに行ったノミネーションの数を含めるようにしています。例えば：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;こんにちは、私は Iqbal です。ここで時々手伝っています。これまでに xxx 人を PSF フェローに、xxx 人を CSA にノミネートしました。それについてもっと知りたいですか？&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;そして、時々話している人が私がノミネートした人を知っていて、素晴らしい会話が生まれます。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;誰かを認識するべきだと思っているけれど、まだ方法がわからない場合は、&lt;a href="https://mtd.pythonasia.org/@iqbalabd"&gt;Mastodon&lt;/a&gt;、&lt;a href="https://x.com/iqbalabd"&gt;X&lt;/a&gt; または &lt;a href="linkedin.com/in/iqbalabd/"&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt; を通じて私にメッセージを送っていただければ、できる限りお手伝いします。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;FAQ&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PSF ノミネーションについてのオープンスペースでの質問は以下の通りです：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;自己推薦できますか？&lt;/strong&gt; - はい&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;コミュニティサービス賞（CSA）と PSF フェローの違いは何ですか？&lt;/strong&gt; - CSA が何のためのものかについての公式説明は &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/community/awards/psf-awards/"&gt;こちら&lt;/a&gt; を、PSF フェローについては &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/fellows/"&gt;こちら&lt;/a&gt; をご覧ください。簡単に言えば、CSA は特定の奉仕行為を祝うものであり、PSF フェローメンバーシップは Python エコシステムとコミュニティへの包括的で顕著な貢献を認識するものです。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PSF フェローに誰かをノミネートするための要件は何ですか？&lt;/strong&gt; - 明確な要件はありませんが、通常のオーガナイザーや貢献者を超えた貢献が必要です。良い例は、PSF フェローノミネーションのために公開されているノミネーション文自体であり、&lt;a href="https://wiki.python.org/moin/PythonSoftwareFoundation/FellowNominations"&gt;こちら&lt;/a&gt; に掲載されています。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;これらのノミネーションはどのように決定されますか？&lt;/strong&gt; - 誰でも誰かをノミネートできますが、ノミネーションは PSF 内の異なるグループによって審議され、受け入れられるか拒否されます。PSF フェローノミネーションは &lt;a href="https://wiki.python.org/psf/FellowWG/Charter"&gt;PSF フェローワークグループ&lt;/a&gt; によって決定され、CSA は &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/board/"&gt;PSF ボード&lt;/a&gt; によって、そして Outstanding PyLady Award は &lt;a href="https://pyladies.com/blog/Announcing-the-Inaugural-PyLadies-Global-Council/inaugural-pyladies-council/"&gt;PyLadies Global Council&lt;/a&gt; によって決定されます。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;この投稿をレビューしてくれた &lt;a href="https://x.com/cheukting_ho"&gt;Cheuk&lt;/a&gt; に感謝します&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2024"></category><category term="pycon"></category><category term="psf"></category><category term="コミュニティ"></category></entry><entry><title>Nominating Pythonistas For Stuff At The Python Software Foundation (PSF)</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/en/posts/2024/05/nominating-pythonistas-at-the-psf/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-05-20T09:20:00+09:00</published><updated>2024-05-23T20:27:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabdullah.net,2024-05-20:/en/posts/2024/05/nominating-pythonistas-at-the-psf/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A README to nominating your fellow Pythonistas for stuff at the PSF&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Do you know that you can nominate your favorite hardworking person or group for stuff and recognize them for their work at the PSF, and do all this for &lt;em&gt;free&lt;/em&gt;? (i.e., free as in free tea)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Acknowledge And Thank Them: Nominating Your Fellow Pythonistas&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before 2014, the Python Software Foundation (PSF) didn't have a formal nomination process or criteria. When they moved to an open membership organization (basically meaning anyone can join as a member of the PSF), they created formal processes for nomination and granting special recognition to members of its community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did an Open Space during PyCon US 2024 in Pittsburgh to exactly share my experiences and answer questions on this topic. During the closing of the conference, &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/denicholson/"&gt;Deb Nicholson&lt;/a&gt; – who is the Executive Director of the PSF – got on stage and pointed out that we've had no Community Service Award (CSA) to present this year due to a lack of nominations. With all the great things everyone is working on in any particular year, it's really difficult to think that no one deserves the CSA; so the only possible thing is that our community just aren't aware enough that they can do such nominations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;What Can You Nominate For?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's more than just the CSA. You can nominate your fellow Pythonistas for these:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PSF Fellow&lt;/strong&gt;: The PSF Fellow membership is a special membership awarded to individuals who have made significant contributions to the Python community through their work, including contributions to the development of Python, supporting the infrastructure, organizing events, and other impactful activities. PSF Fellow nominations are handled and decided upon by the &lt;a href="https://wiki.python.org/psf/FellowWG/Charter"&gt;PSF Fellow Workgroup&lt;/a&gt;. More details can be found on the &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/fellows/"&gt;PSF Fellow Membership page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PSF Community Service Award&lt;/strong&gt;: This is the CSA. It recognizes individuals or groups that have performed exceptional volunteer service for the Python community. It highlights those who have dedicated significant time and effort to improve the community through various means, such as organizing events, contributing to educational resources, or supporting community initiatives. The decision to award the CSA to an individual or a group is decided by the PSF Board. Details are available on the &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/community/awards/psf-awards/"&gt;PSF Community Service Award page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Outstanding PyLady Award&lt;/strong&gt;: This award is given to individuals who have made significant contributions to the PyLadies community, which is dedicated to promoting diversity and supporting women and gender minorities in the Python community. It celebrates those who have gone above and beyond in mentoring, organizing events, and fostering an inclusive environment. The decisions on awarding the Outstanding PyLady Award are done by the PyLadies Global Council. You can learn more about this award &lt;a href="https://kit.pyladies.com/en/latest/global/award.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PSF Distinguished Service Award&lt;/strong&gt;: This is the Foundation's highest award. The Distinguished Service Award is an offer of recognition for sustained exemplary contributions to the Python community. This award is given for actions which carry significant impact that shapes the Python world, whether through contributions of code, efforts in community action, or otherwise. As with the Community Service Award, the intention is to demonstrate that such service to the community does lead to recognition and reward, rather than to provide a direct incentive to contributors. You can learn more about this award &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/community/awards/psf-distinguished-awards/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These awards and recognitions are excellent ways to highlight and celebrate the invaluable contributions of Pythonistas around the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PSF Board Directorship&lt;/strong&gt;: Although a responsibility, not an award, nominating someone for Directorship is still meaningful. The PSF Board of Directors oversees the Foundation's activities and ensures its mission is carried out effectively. Board Directors are elected by the PSF membership and play a crucial role in strategic decision-making and governance. Read more on the &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/"&gt;PSF Board Elections page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Why Should You Nominate?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nominating someone for recognition within the Python Software Foundation (PSF) is not just a formality – it's a powerful way to celebrate and acknowledge the hard work and dedication that Python community members invest in the ecosystem. Recognizing individuals and groups:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Promotes Positive Community Spirit&lt;/strong&gt;: By acknowledging contributions, we foster a culture of appreciation and motivation, which encourages more people to get involved and contribute to the community.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Highlights Diverse Contributions&lt;/strong&gt;: Recognizing the work of different individuals showcases the variety of ways people can contribute, whether through code, community organizing, education, or advocacy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Encourages Continued Involvement&lt;/strong&gt;: Awarding community members can incentivize them to continue their efforts, knowing that their work is valued and noticed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Builds a Stronger Network&lt;/strong&gt;: Celebrating achievements helps build stronger connections within the community, facilitating collaboration and support among members.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're living in the gift economy. Gifts turn the wheels in our world. Open source is a gift. The unpaid labor that people do to support the community around open source is a gift. Welcoming people into our community regardless of age, gender, economic status or education level is a gift. Saying thank you and acknowledging our peers in the community is also a gift that pays them back. Naomi Ceder says this best in her &lt;a href="https://www.naomiceder.tech/posts/pycon_keynote_2022/"&gt;A Time of Gifts keynote&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it's crucial to ensure that the recognition process is inclusive and represents the diverse Python global community. Certain groups have been underrepresented in technology and community leadership roles. For example, the communities from my region (the East Asia, South Asia and Southeast Asia) only had 18 PSF Fellow memberships and 2 CSA recipients (one representing a group), out of around a total of 500 PSF Fellows and around 100 individuals for the CSA. That's just around 4% and 2% of the total recipients. When we consider there are around &lt;a href="https://thefortunate.blog/diversification-is-the-future-for-the-psf.html"&gt;8.2 million Python developers or users worldwide&lt;/a&gt; and the biggest growth is within my region, &lt;em&gt;that is&lt;/em&gt; underrepresentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;How Do You Nominate?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The process for nominating someone for recognition at the PSF is straightforward:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Identify the Category&lt;/strong&gt;: Determine which award or recognition is most appropriate for the individual or group you want to nominate. This could be a PSF Fellow, Community Service Award, Board Directorship, or Outstanding PyLady Award.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prepare the Nomination&lt;/strong&gt;: Collect information about the nominee, including their contributions to the Python community, specific achievements, and any other relevant details. The nomination should highlight why the nominee deserves the recognition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Submit the Nomination&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For &lt;strong&gt;PSF Fellow&lt;/strong&gt; nominations, you can submit via email. Read more on the PSF Fellow membership page &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/fellows/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For the &lt;strong&gt;Community Service Award&lt;/strong&gt;, details and submission instructions can be found on the &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/community/awards/psf-awards/"&gt;PSF Community Service Award page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nominations for &lt;strong&gt;PSF Board Directorship&lt;/strong&gt; are typically part of the annual election process. More information can be found on the &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/"&gt;PSF Board Elections page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Outstanding PyLady Award&lt;/strong&gt; details can be found &lt;a href="https://kit.pyladies.com/en/latest/global/award.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;PSF Distinguished Service Award&lt;/strong&gt; details can be found &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/community/awards/psf-distinguished-awards/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Need for Better Representation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the PSF has made significant strides in promoting diversity and inclusion, such as the creation of the &lt;a href="https://wiki.python.org/psf/DiversityandInclusionWG"&gt;D&amp;amp;I Workgroup&lt;/a&gt; and granting more grants to the African and Asian communities in 2023, there is still a need for better representation from different communities around the world in terms of acknowledging the work of individuals and groups. Many regions are underrepresented in PSF leadership and recognition programs. This lack of representation can create barriers to entry for new contributors and limit the diversity of ideas and perspectives within the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To address this, we need to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Promote Awareness&lt;/strong&gt;: Increase awareness about the nomination processes and opportunities for recognition among underrepresented groups.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Provide Support&lt;/strong&gt;: Offer resources and support to help individuals from diverse backgrounds navigate the nomination process and engage with the community.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Encourage Diverse Nominations&lt;/strong&gt;: Actively seek out and encourage nominations of individuals from underrepresented regions and backgrounds.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mentorship Programs&lt;/strong&gt;: Establish mentorship programs to guide and support new contributors from diverse communities in their journey within the Python ecosystem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By taking these steps, we can ensure that the PSF truly reflects the global and diverse nature of the Python community, fostering an inclusive environment in which all contributions are valued and recognized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;What Can I Do?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plenty!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, if you're not a PSF member yet, sign up &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/membership/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. If you've done work for the community that makes you eligible to be a &lt;a href="https://psfmember.org/civicrm/contribute/transact/?reset=1&amp;amp;id=32"&gt;Managing, Contributing or Supporting member&lt;/a&gt;, make sure you're recognized as such too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, you can nominate someone! If you've been in your community long enough, I'm sure by the time you're reading this, you'll have the person(s) in mind right now. No one? Are you sure? Well, one example I can give is when I get to a new city or community, I ask a few people who would be the best person to talk to for a newcomer to get involved, and if let's say 75% of them give me the same name, then that person would probably be PSF Fellow material. You can then start by getting to know that person and talking about the work they have done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Community Service Awards (CSA) have an easier criteria to understand, but still a high hurdle to be accepted. An example is the nomination that I made for the PyCon JP Association (read more &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/records/board/resolutions/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/community/awards/psf-awards/#december-2021"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, for the charity talks event that they did to raise money for the PSF on the wake of the pandemic, which had disastrous effects on the PSF financially. Another more recent example is the recognition by the board for &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/records/board/minutes/2024-03-13/#new-business"&gt;Leonard Richardson, Lais Cavalho and Raquel Dou to receive the CSA&lt;/a&gt; for the software or community that they have built and maintained, which benefited the community at large.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Distinguished Service Award (DSA) has a much higher hurdle to clear. Since given out in 2012, only 7 people have
received it. Sometimes a CSA nomination can lead to a DSA being awarded, but that is up to the PSF Board to decide. You
can read on the reasons for the DSA to be awarded &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/community/awards/psf-distinguished-awards/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and if you have someone that you think deserves to stand as
tall as these other recepients, that please make a nomination. Nominations can be sent confidentially by email to the
PSF Board as written &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/community/awards/psf-distinguished-awards/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can of course self-nominate, but I personally find this a very difficult thing to do and very boring, so I'm not interested in doing that. It's more fun to write about other people!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, you can help increase awareness of such opportunities to recognize, acknowledge, and elevate your fellow Pythonistas through these nominations: When I'm at PyCon or a Python meetup, I've started to include the amount of nominations I've made in my self-introduction, something like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hey, my name is Iqbal. I sometimes help around here, and have nominated xxx people to the PSF Fellow and xxx for the CSA. Would you like to know more about that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and sometimes I'll be pleasantly surprised that the person I'm talking to will know the person I nominated, and that becomes a great conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have someone in mind that should be recognized but you still don't know how to do it, you can just quickly drop
me a message through my &lt;a href="https://mtd.pythonasia.org/@iqbalabd"&gt;Mastodon&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://x.com/iqbalabd"&gt;X&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="linkedin.com/in/iqbalabd/"&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt; and I'll be happy to help whatever I can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;FAQ&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During my Open Space about PSF Nominations, these are some of the questions we had:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Can you self-nominate?&lt;/strong&gt; - Yes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What's the difference between the Community Service Award (CSA) and PSF Fellow?&lt;/strong&gt; - You can read the official description of what the CSA is for &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/community/awards/psf-awards/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and the PSF Fellow &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/fellows/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. In a nutshell, the CSA celebrates particular acts of service, while the PSF Fellow membership recognizes an individual's comprehensive and distinguished contribution to the Python ecosystems and community.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What's the requirement to nominate someone for the PSF Fellow?&lt;/strong&gt; - There are no hard requirements, but contributions that clearly go beyond your casual organizer or contributor. A good place to get examples are the nomination statements themselves, which are published &lt;a href="https://wiki.python.org/moin/PythonSoftwareFoundation/FellowNominations"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for the PSF Fellow nominations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How do these nominations get decided upon?&lt;/strong&gt; - Anyone can nominate someone, but the nominations are deliberated, accepted or rejected by different groups within the PSF. The PSF Fellow nominations are decided by the &lt;a href="https://wiki.python.org/psf/FellowWG/Charter"&gt;PSF Fellow Workgroup&lt;/a&gt;, the CSA by the &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/board/"&gt;PSF Board&lt;/a&gt; while the Outstanding PyLady Award by the &lt;a href="https://pyladies.com/blog/Announcing-the-Inaugural-PyLadies-Global-Council/inaugural-pyladies-council/"&gt;PyLadies Global Council&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thank you to &lt;a href="https://x.com/cheukting_ho"&gt;Cheuk&lt;/a&gt; for reviewing this post&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2024"></category><category term="pycon"></category><category term="psf"></category><category term="community"></category></entry><entry><title>ウェブログの更新 (ついに!)</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/ja/posts/2024/05/weblog-latest-update-2024/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-05-01T13:22:00+09:00</published><updated>2024-05-01T13:22:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabdullah.net,2024-05-01:/ja/posts/2024/05/weblog-latest-update-2024/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;2024年のウェブログの更新と5年日記&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;ウェブログの更新&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ついにこのウェブログの更新に取り組みました。私は多くを書きますが、ほとんどは仕事関連で、&lt;a href="https://kafkai.com/ja/blog/"&gt;Kafkaiブログ&lt;/a&gt;、&lt;a href="https://otp.dev/ja/blog/"&gt;GetOTPブログ&lt;/a&gt;、&lt;a href="https://lalokalabs.co/ja/blog/"&gt;LaLoka Labs's ブログ&lt;/a&gt;などの各個別ブログにアップしています。
そのすべてを終えた後は、より個人的なことを書く時間がもうなくなった。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;5年日記から始まった&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="俺の5年連用日記" src="https://iqbalabdullah.net/ja/images/5-year-diary.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;アフィザは私の47歳の誕生日プレゼントとして「5年日記」をくれました。彼女は日記に書くことを楽しんでおり、現在の1冊目の日記をほぼ完成させています。
友人に勧められたそうで、今では私にもおすすめしてくれました。毎日の終わりに2、3分費やして、その日に起こったランダムなことを書き始めたところ、仕事のことを考えずに、もっと長い考えを書きたくなりました。
それがこの個人ウェブログを更新するきっかけになりました。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;修正点&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;更新するなら、途中で修正点もチェックしておくべきですよね。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;カテゴリ&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;これまで多くを書いてきて気づいたのは、投稿をある特定の方法でカテゴライズする必要があったことが、実は私の書く自由を制限していたということです。私は上から下に考える人間なんだから、
仕事で書く場合はカテゴリがあると役立ちますね。目標とするアウトカムがあり、構造を与えてくれます。でも個人的な書き物の場合は、かえって邪魔になるのです。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;そこで、投稿はすべて書いた年でファイルし、緩やかな分類法として&lt;a href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/tags.html"&gt;タグ&lt;/a&gt;を使うことにしました。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Pelicanでの非翻訳カテゴリ&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;もう一つ、投稿を別の言語に翻訳することもあって、このウェブログにはPelicanを使っています。Pelicanは&lt;a href="https://qiita.com/agektrombala/items/bc0da1f2bdf9e1f35aeb"&gt;i8n_subsites plugin&lt;/a&gt;を使って、
さまざまな言語で確実に公開してくれますが、カテゴリ(ディレクトリを作成するときに決まるもの)を翻訳する方法は見つかりませんでした。だから、年ごとにするだけなら翻訳の必要がありません。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;新ドメイン&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;そして最後に、このウェブログには新しいドメインが付きました。私の良く読むブログの人たち、例えば&lt;a href="https://ziade.org/"&gt;Tarek Ziade&lt;/a&gt;や&lt;a href="https://simonwillison.net/"&gt;Simon Willison&lt;/a&gt;のように、
インターネット上の自分を反映するドメインを持つのが私にはより合理的だと思います。&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2024"></category><category term="日常の出来事"></category><category term="執筆"></category><category term="ブログ"></category></entry><entry><title>Weblog Update (Finally!)</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/en/posts/2024/05/weblog-latest-update-2024/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-05-01T13:22:00+09:00</published><updated>2024-05-01T13:22:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabdullah.net,2024-05-01:/en/posts/2024/05/weblog-latest-update-2024/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Updating this weblog for 2024 and my 5-year diary&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Weblog Update&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I finally sat down and got to updating this weblog. I write a lot, but most of my writing is work-related and will go to
their respective blogs such as &lt;a href="https://kafkai.com/en/blog/"&gt;Kafkai blog&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://otp.dev/en/blog/"&gt;GetOTP blog&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://lalokalabs.co/en/blog/"&gt;LaLoka Labs's blog&lt;/a&gt;
and after all of that there wasn't enough time for me to write things which are more personal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Started by a 5-Year Diary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="My 5-year diary" src="https://iqbalabdullah.net/ja/images/5-year-diary.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Afiza gave me a "5-year diary" present for my 47th birthday. She enjoyed writing things on it and nearly finished her current diary.
She was recommended to it by a friend, and now she has also recommended it to me. I've started spending two or three minutes at the end of my
day every day to write random things that happened that day in it, and realized the urge to write longer thoughts without thinking about work too much.
That brought me around to updating this personal weblog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Some Fixes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, no point in updating something without fixing things along the way, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Categories&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I realized after all the time I've spent writing that my posts needed to be categorized in a particular way was actually restricting my writing.
I have always been a person who thinks from top to bottom. Categories help if I'm writing for work because we usually have an outcome we want to
achieve and it gives me structure, but when it comes to personal writing, this gets in the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I've decided to just file all my posts under the year they were written and use &lt;a href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/tags.html"&gt;tags&lt;/a&gt; instead as a loose form
of categorization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Non-Translatable Categories in Pelican&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another thing is that sometimes I translate my posts to different languages and I'm using Pelican for this weblog. Pelican does a great job at publishing the
different languages through the &lt;a href="https://qiita.com/agektrombala/items/bc0da1f2bdf9e1f35aeb"&gt;i8n_subsites plugin&lt;/a&gt;, but I haven't found a way to have the categories
(which are decided when you create directories) in Pelican translated. So, just having them as years doesn't require translation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;New Domain&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And finally, this weblog has a new domain. Just like the weblogs of people I read frequently, such as &lt;a href="https://ziade.org/"&gt;Tarek Ziade&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href="https://simonwillison.net/"&gt;Simon Willison&lt;/a&gt;, it just makes more sense to me to have a domain that reflects myself on the internet.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2024"></category><category term="daily stuff"></category><category term="writing"></category><category term="blogging"></category></entry><entry><title>多様化がPythonソフトウェア財団（PSF）の将来像</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/ja/posts/2020/06/diversification-is-the-future-for-the-psf/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-06-20T16:05:00+09:00</published><updated>2020-06-20T16:05:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabdullah.net,2020-06-20:/ja/posts/2020/06/diversification-is-the-future-for-the-psf/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Pythonソフトウェア財団（PSF）の2020年理事会選挙に立候補し落選して思うこと。&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;前提&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2019年以降、私は東アジア、南アジア、東南アジア（まとめてAPACと呼ばれる）にあるPythonコミュニティがより一貫した方向に進めるよう尽力してきた。
毎年北米で開催されるPyCon(今年はピッツバーグで開催)の期間中に、より広範な北米および国際コミュニティに
紹介するコミュニティブースも予定されていたが、COVID-19のため残念ながら中止になった。
PyCon US&lt;sup id="fnref:fn01"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:fn01"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; とはPythonソフトウェア財団（PSF）が主催する年に1度のプログラミング言語Pythonに関するカンファレンスで、
同時に唯一の大規模な資金調達イベントでもある。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Pythonソフトウェア財団（PSF）とは&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;まず、次のことを私は認めざるを得ない。2002年にPythonを使い始めたとき、PSFの存在については知らなかった。
2010年にPyConに初めて参加し、PSFというものの存在を理解し始めた。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PSFは、Python言語、そのエコシステム、それを使用し依存しているコミュニティを維持し保護するために非常に重要な、
しかし極めて一般的にあまり知られてないな役割を担っている。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PSFの取り組みについては&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/#:~:text=The%20mission%20of%20the%20Python,international%20community%20of%20Python%20programmers."&gt;こちら&lt;/a&gt;を参照してください。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;PSF理事会のポストに立候補&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2020年6月、任期が満了するPSFのディレクター(理事のこと)の4つの席が空席になる。
長年、&lt;a href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/ja/drafts/changing-the-world-one-pycon-at-a-time-en.html"&gt;地球の裏側でコミュニティを構築するために働きながら&lt;/a&gt;
私は米国中心の組織であるPSFが実行していると思っていることと、世界の他の場所で拡大しているコミュニティが実行していると思っていること
の間にギャップがあると感じていたので、少なくとも東・南・東南アジアの声を代弁するため、ディレクターに立候補することを決心した。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;正直に言うと、その時点でのモチベーションはそれほど明確ではなかった。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;資金調達の努力が重要だと知っており、次のようなことを支援したかった。
私は過去数年にわたり、オープンソースに対し金銭的な愛を広めるよう&lt;a href="https://blog.xoxzo.com/en/2018/05/02/annual-opensource-grant-for-2018/"&gt;ここで&lt;/a&gt;、&lt;a href="https://www.slideshare.net/xoxzo/lightning-talk-pycon-thailand-2019"&gt;PyCon THでのLTで&lt;/a&gt;および&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7U2D5tcMZb4&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be&amp;amp;t=2107"&gt;PyCon JPでのLTで&lt;/a&gt;)提唱してきたし、これからも続けたいと思っている。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;しかし、PSFを通じてより大きなPythonコミュニティが一緒になれば&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/2020-python-software-foundation-board/nominees/iqbal-abdullah/"&gt;価値観を共有する私の思いはさらに強まり、関わっているコミュニティへの発言権ももっと大きくなった&lt;/a&gt;と思う。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ちなみに、PSFディレクターが担う責任と日常的な活動を知りたくてこれを読んでいるなら、次のリンクが役立つかもしれない。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://wiki.python.org/moin/PythonSoftwareFoundation/DutiesAndResponsibilitiesOfDirectors"&gt;PSFディレクターの任務と責任&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZLKj6FaQA4M"&gt;Pythonソフトウェア財団ディレクターとしての生活&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;選挙の結果&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;選挙結果が発表され、私は空席4に対する候補者26人中11位だった。見事に落選 😅&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;投票権持つ1,151人のうち、実際に投票したのは462人だけだった。
選出された上位4名は、以下のとおり。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/2020-python-software-foundation-board/nominees/nina-zakharenko/"&gt;Nina Zakharenko&lt;/a&gt;
得票数 263&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/2020-python-software-foundation-board/nominees/dustin-ingram/"&gt;Dustin Ingram&lt;/a&gt;
得票数 249&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/2020-python-software-foundation-board/nominees/jeff-triplett/"&gt;Jeff Triplett&lt;/a&gt;
得票数240&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/2020-python-software-foundation-board/nominees/thomas-wouters/"&gt;Tomas Wouters&lt;/a&gt;
得票数 237&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;結果を分析し自分自身の「選挙活動」を振り返った後、私がPythonとそのコミュニティの将来像だと強く確信し取り組みたいと考えていた、
本当の課題が鮮明に見えてきた。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;その課題とは&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;私はSlackでの質疑応答セッションに参加する機会があったが、そこでは立候補者または選挙に関心を持つほかの誰でも現在の理事会メンバーに
質問することができた。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1つ私が尋ねたのは、「PSF、あるいは過去数年間PSFが達成を望んでいた事柄に関して今取り組んでいる懸念事項」のことだった。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/glasnt"&gt;Katie McLaughlin&lt;/a&gt;さんは、特に最大のPSF資金調達イベント、PyCon 2020が開催されなかったことを考えると、
短期的には資金調達の努力を多様化するために多くの施策が行われている、と回答した。長期的には、多くの取り組みは目標に焦点を当て、
この何年にもわたる努力が継続し完了するための勢いを確保するべきだ。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;任期満了するもう一人のPSFディレクター&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/jackiekazil"&gt;Jacqueline Kazil&lt;/a&gt;さんからも、
洞察力に富んだ別の見解をもらった。
彼女は、PyConが中止された際PSFが直面する財務上の問題とリスクを支援するために、
&lt;a href="https://medium.com/@jackiekazil/elect-more-international-representation-finance-focused-individuals-to-psf-3eedcf0a91a7"&gt;理事会はより国際的な代表の選出と、ファイナンス関連の知識を持つ人物を必要としている&lt;/a&gt;と考えている。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;こうした主張を聞き、私たちに必要なのは&lt;strong&gt;多様化&lt;/strong&gt;であることピンときた。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;多様化&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;私たちの代表を選出する点でも資金面のサポートという点でも、現時点でPSFの問題として私が把握した包括的なテーマは、多様化であること。
私思うのは、この両方は相互に関連している。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;代表の選出&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;今回PyLadiesのメキシコ拠点オーガナイザー、&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/valerybriz"&gt;Valeria Calderon&lt;/a&gt;さんが数票差で落選したのは残念だった。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;その他米国以外の立候補者、中南米のPython Ambassadorである&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/reydelhumo"&gt;Manuel Kaufmann&lt;/a&gt;さんや、
Python Namibiaの創立者&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/muheuenga"&gt;Ngazetungue Muheue&lt;/a&gt;さんなども落選した。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ちなみにManuelさんは&lt;a href="https://pycon.jp/2018/"&gt;PyCon JP 2018のキーノートスピーカの一人だった&lt;/a&gt;。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;これら全員が、世界のさまざまな地域に存在するコミュニティのニーズに関して新鮮な意見や見解を持ち込む可能性があった。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;中核となる技術的コンピテンシーを維持するため求められる技術力と信頼性のハードルが高い&lt;a href="https://realpython.com/lessons/python-steering-council/"&gt;Python意思決定議会&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/dev/peps/pep-8101/"&gt;選挙&lt;/a&gt;とは異なり、
PSF理事会は空席があれば誰でも立候補できる。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PSF理事会はこの言語とそれに依存する人々の将来を向上させるためにリソースをうまく活用する責任があり、
技術的なコア・コンピテンシーは必要となるかもしれない素質の一部に過ぎない。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;これは、非常に重要なメッセージを発信している。
&lt;em&gt;あなたがどこにいる誰であっても、私たちの将来を形作り願望を実現する手助けは歓迎される。&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;今年の当選者は全員コミュニティで活発に活動しており、カンファレンスのスピーカーであり、
&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/dev/peps/pep-0001/#:~:text=PEP%20stands%20for%20Python%20Enhancement,a%20rationale%20for%20the%20feature."&gt;PEP&lt;/a&gt;の著者または技術プロジェクトのライターでもある。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PSFのワーキンググループ（WG）メンバーも数人おり、1人は現行のPython意思決定議会メンバーである。
当選者の半分はディレクター業務の経験があり、1人は理事会メンバーへの復帰であり、全員が米国を拠点としている。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;今回あるいは過去の選挙で当選したディレクターがふさわしいかどうかが問題なのではない。
立候補し、必要な得票数に達していれば、当然ディレクターになるべき。
私は選出された理事会メンバーが、私たち全員の利益を最優先に考え最善を尽くすことを確信している。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;問題は、&lt;strong&gt;投票した462人というのは、世界中のPythonコミュニティが抱く将来への願望と現在の状況を公正に反映しているのか？&lt;/strong&gt;
ということ。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PSFはエリートとみなされる危険があり、すでに特定のネットワーク関われている人々のグループに対してのみ開かれている。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;投票権持つ者のベースの拡大&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;現在、世界には&lt;a href="https://www.zdnet.com/article/programming-languages-python-developers-now-outnumber-java-ones/#:~:text=According%20to%20SlashData%2C%20there%20are,and%207.1%20million%20Java%20developers."&gt;820万人のPython開発者&lt;/a&gt;がいる。
開発者人口の増加という点で、アジア太平洋地域は最高の成長率を示しており、インドは今後5年以内に米国に取って代わる。
中南米地域は、2番目に高い開発者人口の成長率を示している。&lt;sup id="fnref:fn02"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:fn02"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;代表者の多様性を高めるという目標を達成するには、全体的な有権者ベースを増やす必要がある。毎年検討を繰り返し、
進捗状況をコミュニティに報告すれば、これは目に見える追跡可能な目標である。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;日本、台湾、韓国、マレーシア、インドネシア、タイ、フィリピンなどにいるたくさんの人材が、エコシステムをサポートする
会合やカンファレンスに積極的に参加したり開催したりするため時間とエネルギーを費やしており、
&lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSfwWBGkzvkWDZrxW3up_M_B7qgt1IWZlx9KJ0ucLA5WJP1vfA/viewform"&gt;補助メンバーとして適任である&lt;/a&gt;
ことを私は知っているが、彼らは投票権持ってないし、このベースに反映されていない。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;どうしてでしょうか？&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;自分自身の経験を振り返ってみて、おそらく最大級のハードルは&lt;strong&gt;Pythonコミュニティ自体に内在するPSFに対する無関心&lt;/strong&gt;だろう。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;無関心への取り組み&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;あともう一つのざんげ。
2010年にPSFについて知ったにもかかわらず、PSFが自分自身とコミュニティにどう関係するのか、真剣に考えていなかった。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;私の視点からは、米国のPyConに参加している大半が友達同士の白人たちで構成された、遠く離れた米国の組織だった。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;その視点は自分たちのPyConのためにPSFの助成金を申請し始めたときに進化した。
その時点においてPSFは助成金も出してくれる同じ組織であることを再確認された。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;資金供給するプロジェクトを通して私たちのインフラをサポートしたり、コミュニティ内の参加性を促進する取り組みを率先したりといった、
PSFが行っている重要な業務についてまだよく分かっていなかった。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;有権者ベースの拡大は、投資を受けたコミュニティ・メンバーがPSFの行っている重要な業務すべてを知ることにそのままつながるのである。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PSFは&lt;a href="http://pyfound.blogspot.com/2015/02/enroll-as-psf-voting-member.html"&gt;会員制をオープンする&lt;/a&gt;にあたり、実に大きな前進だった。
投票権を持つメンバーとなるために会費を支払うという最も分かりやすい方法に加え、
刷新した会員制度ではコードを書いたり会合やカンファレンスを主催したりする活動的なメンバーにもまた投票権が与えられる。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;扉は所定の位置に設置されているのだから、次にやるべきはその扉から入ってくるよう人々を促すことである。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PSFは、現在テクノロジー企業が採用の際に行っているようなことを提唱するアプローチを取る必要がある。
顧客の生活に及ぼす効果や影響を強調することによってである。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;こうしたことを提唱するにあたり、プロジェクト管理者に丸投げするべきでなく、
プロジェクトの発案から承認に至るプロセスに関わった全員が行うべきだ。
この点において、PSF理事会はその役割を提唱し売り込む上で重要な役割を担っている。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;例えば、次のことをより詳しく説明する必要がある。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PyLadies"&gt;PyLadies&lt;/a&gt;や&lt;a href="https://us.pycon.org/2020/speaking/charlas/"&gt;PyCon Charlas&lt;/a&gt;など
への参加性を促進するため資金調達においてコミュニティで率先すること&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pythonの名前など、PSFおよび世界中にあるコミュニティの知的財産を保護すること&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://beeware.org/"&gt;Beeware project&lt;/a&gt;や&lt;a href="https://pypi.org/sponsor/"&gt;PyPI&lt;/a&gt;など
PSFが資金提供する技術的な取り組みが私たちのコミュニティに影響し、さらに重要なことに未来にどう影響するか&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;米国から誰かを招いてこうしたことを話し合い、世界の他の場所にあるコミュニティについて知ることは重要であり、
少なくともPSFはそのコミュニティの存在を認識していることを示せる。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;とはいえそのようなコミュニティの近くにとどまり、コミュニティをよりよく理解し、&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/ewa_jodlowska"&gt;Ewa&lt;/a&gt;
あるいは&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/naomiceder"&gt;Naomi&lt;/a&gt;が去った後もずっとPSFについて語り続けられる人物がいれば、
そのほうがずっと良いだろう。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;財政に関して&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2019年のPSF収益USD450万のうち、その63%以上がPyConから得たものだった。
PyCon開催費用の総額はUSD190万なので、つまりPSFがPyConに1ドルを投じること対して1.50ドルが戻ってくるという計算になる。
&lt;sup id="fnref:fn03"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:fn03"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id="fnref:fn05"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:fn05"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;これを、寄付、会員費、助成金から成る収益の残り32%と比較してみよう。その種の収益を得るのに、どれほどの費用がかかるだろうか。&lt;sup id="fnref:fn04"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:fn04"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
すでに確立されたプロセスを通した継続的な収益の場合、1ドルあたりの費用は収益を得るたびに減少する。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;投資した1ドルあたりの利益率はPyConのそれより高いと思う。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;総収益額が変わらずともPyCon以外からの収益を増やすという目標により、PSFは将来&lt;a href="https://pyfound.blogspot.com/2020/03/psfs-projected-2020-financial-outcome.html."&gt;COVID-19が与えたような衝撃&lt;/a&gt;に対してより柔軟に対応できるようになるだろう。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PyCon以外からの収益を増やすには、コミュニティのより広範なベースからの理解と共感を必要なのだ。
認識して手を差し伸べないといけないのはお金や投入した時間と労力ですでに高い関心を示してくれてるコミュニティーの皆、他でもない。
こうして、私たちにとって大切な人々とより強い関係を築くことになる。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://pycon.blogspot.com/2020/03/pycon-us-2020-in-pittsburgh.html"&gt;PyCon 2020中止の発表&lt;/a&gt;に記載されているように、
雇用主にスポンサーシップに参加してもらうことも関心が高いコミュニティができる支援策にもなれる。関心が高い、関わりたい気持ちを
持つメンバーがいれば、彼らの身近なコミュニティに対し私たちの目標を提唱する助けになる。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;米国以外のコミュニティ、特にアジアや南米の拡大しているコミュニティに手を差し伸べるため費やした助成金の大部分と
時間という観点での大きな投資は、PSFが現在ではなく&lt;strong&gt;未来のため&lt;/strong&gt;投資していることを示している。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;大きな投資は大きな関心を意味し、それが好意と信用を生み、より強固な関係への道を開く。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PSFはすでにこの面において正しい方向に向かっているが、助成金の配分量など、さらなる改善の余地があると思っている。&lt;sup id="fnref2:fn05"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:fn05"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id="fnref:fn06"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:fn06"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;より良い関係を築くために、次はPSFへ直接資金援助してくれる支援メンバーのグループ拡大に尽力すべきだ。
このグループを私たちが本当に重視すべきグループで、うまく拡大できれば、財政的なサポートだけでなく、
彼らがもたらすアドボカシーからの支援も得られる。いろんなレベルでプラスになることだろう。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;商業的なサポートと寄付という観点から、米国拠点ではない企業からの収益を多様化するよう尽力もできる。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;具体的に理事会として特定の地域に与えられた助成金の割合を、その地域から得られる企業のスポンサーシップや個人の会費を同額になるよう、
という目標を設定することも考えられる。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;また、それを実行するにあたり、状況を有利に生かすためその地域に根付いたより広範な支援者ベースを必要とする。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;各地域および国には、直接または間接的に事業でPythonを使う、成功した地元の企業が多数存在する。
その国のコミュニティ・メンバーだけがそれを知っており、互いの架け橋となってくれる。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;結論&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;すべては多様化に行き着くことになる。受容の幅を広げ、理解し、最終的に広範なベースの人々から支援されるため、
コミュニティを支援する世界的な組織としてPSFを適合させていく。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;この投稿を終えるにあたり、それがPSFにおける唯一の将来像であると確信している。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;この投稿をレビューしてくれた&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/terapyon"&gt;terapyon&lt;/a&gt;に感謝します&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:fn01"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going forward the PSF is rebranding PyCon to PyCon US since they happen everywhere according to Ewa&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:fn01" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:fn02"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.daxx.com/blog/development-trends/number-software-developers-world"&gt;How Many Software Developers Are There in the World?&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:fn02" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:fn03"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Total revenue in 2019 was $4,481,192 and $2,852,109 was from PyCon according to Ewa&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:fn03" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:fn04"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contributions and Grants were $1,165,278. We can also factor in PSF sponsorship fees, which are another $248,343. If we factor that in, that is ~32% according to Ewa&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:fn04" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:fn05"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/annual-report/2019/"&gt;PSF Annual Report 2018&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:fn05" title="Jump back to footnote 5 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref2:fn05" title="Jump back to footnote 5 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:fn06"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/annual-report/2020/"&gt;PSF Annual Report 2019&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:fn06" title="Jump back to footnote 6 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="2020"></category><category term="psf"></category><category term="政治"></category><category term="コミュニティ"></category><category term="2020"></category></entry><entry><title>Diversification is the future for the Python Software Foundation (PSF)</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/en/posts/2020/06/diversification-is-the-future-for-the-psf/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-06-20T16:05:00+09:00</published><updated>2020-06-20T16:05:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabdullah.net,2020-06-20:/en/posts/2020/06/diversification-is-the-future-for-the-psf/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;My thoughts after my failed attempt at running for the 2020 board of the Python Software Foundation (PSF).&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;The Premise&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since 2019, I have been working on trying to
get our Python community in East/South/South East Asia (collectively called APAC) to move towards a
more coherent direction together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were also plans for a poster session to introduce us to the wider North American and international community
during the annual PyCon 2020 in Pittsburgh, but due to COVID-19, that unfortunately didn't happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PyCon US&lt;sup id="fnref:fn01"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:fn01"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; is an annual Python programming language conference, which is organized by
the Python Software Foundation (PSF) and at the same time is also its single biggest
fundraising event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The Python Software Foundation (PSF)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I have to admit: When I started using Python in 2002, I didn't know about
the existence of the PSF. I only begin to understand that there is such a thing
as the PSF in 2010 when I attended my first PyCon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The PSF has a very important but very much obscure role to maintain and
safeguard the Python language, its ecosystems and the community that use and
depends on it. Read more about what the PSF does &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/#:~:text=The%20mission%20of%20the%20Python,international%20community%20of%20Python%20programmers."&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Running for a seat on the PSF board&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In June 2020, the Python Software Foundation (PSF) had four seats going vacant with
directors fulfilling their term. After many years &lt;a href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/ja/drafts/changing-the-world-one-pycon-at-a-time-en.html"&gt;working with and building the community on this side of the planet&lt;/a&gt;
I had a feeling that there is a gap between what the PSF, as a US-centric organization thinks it's doing, with what the rest
of the growing community on our part of the world think that they are doing, so I
decided to run for a seat, to at least represent a voice from E/S/SE Asia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have to admit that at that time, my motivations to run were still not very clear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do know that efforts to raise money will be important and I wanted to help: I
have been advocating for us to spread financial love to open source (&lt;a href="https://blog.xoxzo.com/en/2018/05/02/annual-opensource-grant-for-2018/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://www.slideshare.net/xoxzo/lightning-talk-pycon-thailand-2019"&gt;my lightning talk in PyCon TH&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7U2D5tcMZb4&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be&amp;amp;t=2107"&gt;my lightning talk in PyCon JP&lt;/a&gt;)
for the past few years and is something which I would like to continue doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I guess &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/2020-python-software-foundation-board/nominees/iqbal-abdullah/"&gt;my feelings were much stronger to share values and give a greater voice
to the communities which I am involved in&lt;/a&gt; with the greater Python community
through the PSF.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're reading this because you're interested to know what are the responsibilities of a
director of the PSF and what that person does on a day-to-day basis, these resources might be helpful:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://wiki.python.org/moin/PythonSoftwareFoundation/DutiesAndResponsibilitiesOfDirectors"&gt;Duties &amp;amp; Responsibilities of PSF Directors&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZLKj6FaQA4M"&gt;Life as a Python Software Foundation Director&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The results&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the election results was announced, I was in 11th place out of 26
nominees for the four board seats. 1,151 people were eligible to vote, while those that actually voted were 462 persons.
The elected top four nominees was:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/2020-python-software-foundation-board/nominees/nina-zakharenko/"&gt;Nina Zakharenko&lt;/a&gt;
with 263 votes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/2020-python-software-foundation-board/nominees/dustin-ingram/"&gt;Dustin Ingram&lt;/a&gt;
with 249 votes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/2020-python-software-foundation-board/nominees/jeff-triplett/"&gt;Jeff Triplett&lt;/a&gt;
with 240 votes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/2020-python-software-foundation-board/nominees/thomas-wouters/"&gt;Thomas Wouters&lt;/a&gt;
with 237 votes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After analyzing the results and reflecting on my own "campaign", it started to dawn on me
the real issue which I wanted to address which I also strongly believe is the future
for Python and its community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Issue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had the opportunity to participate in a Q&amp;amp;A session question on Slack, which was to
allow nominees or anyone else interested in the elections to ask questions to the
current board members. One of the questions I asked was about "active concerns for the PSF or something that the PSF
had wanted to achieve in the past two years or so".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/glasnt"&gt;Katie McLaughlin&lt;/a&gt; responded that in the short term a lot of work is happening around diversifying
the fundraising efforts especially given PyCon 2020 the biggest PSF fundraising event, didn't happen. In the longer term,
a lot of the efforts should be around focusing on goals, and ensuring that these multi-year efforts have the momentum to
continue and get completed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another insightful view was from &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/jackiekazil"&gt;Jacqueline Kazil&lt;/a&gt;, an outgoing PSF director.
She believes that &lt;a href="https://medium.com/@jackiekazil/elect-more-international-representation-finance-focused-individuals-to-psf-3eedcf0a91a7"&gt;the board needs more international representation and also people from finance backgrounds&lt;/a&gt;
to help with the financial issues and risks the PSF will face when a PyCon is cancelled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The points that they made really rang bells in my head. What we need is &lt;strong&gt;diversification&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Diversification&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The overarching theme of what I perceive as an issue for the PSF right now is
diversification, both in the context of representation of who we are, and also in the
context of financial support. In my view, these are inter-connected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;In representation&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was unfortunate this time that &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/valerybriz"&gt;Valeria Calderon&lt;/a&gt;,
a PyLadies organizer based in Mexico City missed a board seat by a few votes.
Other non-US based nominees such as &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/reydelhumo"&gt;Manuel Kaufmann&lt;/a&gt; who is Latin America Python Ambassador
and &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/muheuenga"&gt;Ngazetungue Muheue&lt;/a&gt; founder of Python
Namibia also didn't make the cut. All of them had the potential of bringing
fresh voices and views about the needs of communities that we have in different
parts of the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike the &lt;a href="https://realpython.com/lessons/python-steering-council/"&gt;Python Steering Council&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/dev/peps/pep-8101/"&gt;elections&lt;/a&gt; which has a technical and trust hurdle that is required for it to maintain
its core technical competency, the PSF board is open for &lt;em&gt;anyone&lt;/em&gt; to run when there are vacant seats.
The PSF board has a wider responsibility to use its resources for the betterment of the future of the
language and the people that rely on it, and technical core competencies are just one part of what you might need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This sends out a very important message: &lt;em&gt;We welcome you to help shape the future and aspirations
of us, whoever and wherever you are.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of the people elected this year are active in communities and speakers at conferences,
are authors of &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/dev/peps/pep-0001/#:~:text=PEP%20stands%20for%20Python%20Enhancement,a%20rationale%20for%20the%20feature."&gt;PEPs&lt;/a&gt; or writers of technical projects.
Some are also Working Group (WG) members in the PSF and one person is a current Python Steering Council member. Half of the elected
directors have directorship experience, one is a returning board member and all are US based persons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question is not that the directors which was elected in this and past
elections shouldn't be there: If they run and received the required votes, they of course should be there.
I am sure anyone elected to the board will have the best interests of all of us at heart and will do their best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question is: &lt;strong&gt;Does the 462 voters fairly reflect the current state and future aspirations of our worldwide Python community?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The PSF is in danger of being looked upon as being elitist, and is only open to a selected group of people who already
have access to a particular network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Increasing voter base&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As of now, there are &lt;a href="https://www.zdnet.com/article/programming-languages-python-developers-now-outnumber-java-ones/#:~:text=According%20to%20SlashData%2C%20there%20are,and%207.1%20million%20Java%20developers."&gt;8.2 million Python developers in the world&lt;/a&gt;.
In terms of developer population growth, the Asia Pacific region is showing the highest growth, with India taking over the US within the
next five years. The Latin America region is showing the second largest growth for the developer population. &lt;sup id="fnref:fn02"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:fn02"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To achieve the target of increasing diversity in representation, we need to increase the overall voter base. This is a tangible
and trackable goal, which we can bring back to the table every year and report on its progress back to the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know many people in JP, TW, KR, MY, ID, TH and ID who contribute their time and energy to actively participate and manage
meetups and conferences that support the ecosystem and would
&lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSfwWBGkzvkWDZrxW3up_M_B7qgt1IWZlx9KJ0ucLA5WJP1vfA/viewform"&gt;qualify as contributing members&lt;/a&gt;
but they are not reflected on our voter base.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why is that?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reflecting on my own experience, perhaps one of the biggest hurdle is &lt;strong&gt;indifference to the PSF within the Python community itself&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Tackling indifference&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another admission from myself: Even after knowing about the PSF in 2010, I
didn't seriously understand the relationship that the PSF could have with myself
and my community. From my point of view, it was an organization in faraway USA,
comprising mostly of white people who are mostly friends of each other and they attend PyCon in the US.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That point of view evolved when we started to apply for grants from the PSF for our own PyCons.
At that point the PSF is now an organization in faraway USA, comprising mostly of white people who mostly friends of each other and they
attend PyCon in the US that also gives out grants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was still not aware of the important work that the PSF was doing, like supporting our infrastructure through projects that it
funds, or what initiatives it has to increase inclusivity within our community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Increasing the voter base will directly result in community members which are
invested in knowing about all of the good and important work done by the PSF.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The PSF has done a great job at &lt;a href="http://pyfound.blogspot.com/2015/02/enroll-as-psf-voting-member.html"&gt;opening up memberships&lt;/a&gt;.
Other than the most obvious way of being a paying member to be a voting member, the revamped membership structure also
allows members who are active in other ways such as writing code or managing meetups and conferences to also become a
voting member.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The door has been set in place, so we next need to get people through that door.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The PSF should approach advocating about what it does like what tech companies do now days when they are hiring:
By stressing the impact of and influence its work on how their customers live their lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Advocating about these should not only be left to the project maintainer,
but everyone involved in the process from planning to approving the projects. In
this regard, the board of the PSF plays an important role to advocate and
market its role.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, we need to explain better how does&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Funding community initiatives to increase inclusivity like &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PyLadies"&gt;PyLadies&lt;/a&gt; and
  &lt;a href="https://us.pycon.org/2020/speaking/charlas/"&gt;PyCon Charlas&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Protecting the intellectual property of the PSF and it's communities worldwide, such as the name Python&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The technical initiatives funded by the PSF like the &lt;a href="https://beeware.org/"&gt;Beeware project&lt;/a&gt; or
&lt;a href="https://pypi.org/sponsor/"&gt;PyPI&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;affect our community, and most importantly how it will affect us in the future?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having someone come over from the US to talk about this and getting to know communities in
different parts of the world are great and shows that the PSF at least acknowledges the existence of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it is far much better when there is also someone that stays around these communities
and understand them better to carry on talking about the PSF long after &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/ewa_jodlowska"&gt;Ewa&lt;/a&gt;
or &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/naomiceder"&gt;Naomi&lt;/a&gt; has flown back home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;In finance&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Out of USD4.5MM of revenue for the PSF in 2019, around 63% of it came from PyCon.
USD1.9MM was the costs of having PyCon, which means that for every dollar spent
on PyCon, the PSF gets back 1.50 dollars. &lt;sup id="fnref:fn03"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:fn03"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id="fnref:fn05"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:fn05"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compare that to the 32% of revenue from sponsorship fees, contributions, membership dues, and grants.
What costs were involved to generate these revenue? &lt;sup id="fnref:fn04"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:fn04"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If these are recurring revenue through already established processes, costs per dollar only diminishes
for every dollar we get. I believe the return per dollar invested into them are higher than what
PyCon brings in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps a target of increasing the portion from the non-PyCon revenue even if
the total amount of revenue are the same will make the PSF more resilient in the future against
&lt;a href="https://pyfound.blogspot.com/2020/03/psfs-projected-2020-financial-outcome.html"&gt;shocks like what COVID-19 brought to us&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Increasing the portion of non-PyCon revenue will require more understanding and
empathy from the wider base of our community. Who better can we tap other
than those who have already shown their commitment, either by the money they
have paid or the time and effort they have put in. This means building a
stronger relationship to the people that matter to us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As written when &lt;a href="https://pycon.blogspot.com/2020/03/pycon-us-2020-in-pittsburgh.html"&gt;PyCon 2020 cancellation was announced&lt;/a&gt;, 
some of the ways the community can help are getting employers involved in
sponsorships. Having invested members will help us advocate our mission to the
their immediate communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bigger investments in terms of bigger portion of grants given and time taken to
reach out to non-US communities, especially to the growing communities in
Asia and Latin America signals that the PSF is now shifting to investing &lt;strong&gt;for the
future&lt;/strong&gt; instead of the present. Bigger investment shows commitment, which
breeds goodwill, trust and paves the way for a stronger relationship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The PSF is already heading in the right direction in this aspect, although I
believe there are more ways we can improve, like the quantum of grant portions.&lt;sup id="fnref2:fn05"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:fn05"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id="fnref:fn06"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:fn06"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With better relationship, we should next try to expand the supporting members
group, who directly contribute money to the PSF. I believe this is the one group
which we should really focus more on, as the returns from investing time and effort
to increase this base come at multiple levels: Not only on the financial support
that they give, but from the advocacy help that they will also bring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the context of commercial support and donations, we can try to diversify income
to non-US based companies. Perhaps we can use the percentage of grants given to
a certain region as a target for the amount of matching corporate sponsorships and
individual membership fees that we can expect to get from that region. Again,
in order for us to do that, we need a wider base of supporters on the ground
from that region to make it work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many successful local companies in each region and country that directly or indirectly
use Python in their businesses. Only our community members in those countries can tell us who
they are and connect us to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;In summary&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It all comes down to diversifying: To gain acceptance, understanding and finally
support from a much wider base of people, fitting the PSF as a worldwide organization supporting
its community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now at the end of writing this post, I believe that it is the &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; future for the PSF.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thank you to &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/terapyon"&gt;terapyon&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/scari_net"&gt;scari_net&lt;/a&gt; for proofreading
and reviewing this post. Thank you to &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/ewa_jodlowska"&gt;Ewa&lt;/a&gt; for proofreading and revewing the financial numbers&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:fn01"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going forward the PSF is rebranding PyCon to PyCon US since they happen everywhere according to Ewa&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:fn01" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:fn02"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.daxx.com/blog/development-trends/number-software-developers-world"&gt;How Many Software Developers Are There in the World?&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:fn02" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:fn03"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Total revenue in 2019 was $4,481,192 and $2,852,109 was from PyCon according to Ewa&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:fn03" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:fn04"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contributions and Grants were $1,165,278. We can also factor in PSF sponsorship fees, which are another $248,343. If we factor that in, that is ~32% according to Ewa&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:fn04" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:fn05"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/annual-report/2019/"&gt;PSF Annual Report 2018&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:fn05" title="Jump back to footnote 5 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref2:fn05" title="Jump back to footnote 5 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:fn06"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/annual-report/2020/"&gt;PSF Annual Report 2019&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:fn06" title="Jump back to footnote 6 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="2020"></category><category term="psf"></category><category term="politics"></category><category term="community"></category><category term="2020"></category></entry><entry><title>エアアジアが在留カードの確認する件</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/ja/posts/2017/03/why-does-airasia-check-zairyu-card/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-03-11T12:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2017-03-11T12:00:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabdullah.net,2017-03-11:/ja/posts/2017/03/why-does-airasia-check-zairyu-card/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;先日エアアジアを乗ってマレーシアへ行く時にチェックイン時に在留カードの提示求められた。&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;エアアジアを搭乗する際に、在留カードの提示強引に求められたことがあったので、エアアジアに問い合わせをして
クレームを入れたときの背景やその回答をメモの代わりにここに書いておく。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;先日10周年の会社記念の社員旅行のため、エアアジアでオンラインで航空券を予約して、
出発日に羽田空港のカウンタでチェックインすると、パスポートと搭乗券の他、在留カードの提示も求められました。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;今までANAや他の航空会社を乗ったとき、パスポート以外に在留カードの提示求められたことがなかったし、
すべての外国の搭乗者は在留カード持っているわけがないからなぜ我々だけか、
あと在留カードの提示は公務を執行する官憲の者以外は基本的に求められることはないと思いますのでちょっと変だなーと思って
「必要ですか」と訊きました。
カウンタの職員の女性は「はい、必要です。中にまた入管に確認されるのでスムーズに搭乗できるように」
と言われました。私は、「そうしたら、ここで提示を拒否します。入管みたいな官憲の方に任せればいいじゃない。」
そうすると「上司に確認します」とカウンタの女性を言って、上司らしきの方と相談したあとに戻ってきたら
「義務です。提示しなかければ搭乗手続き進めません」と言い切って、仕方がなく提示をしました。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;その後やっぱり腑に落ちませんでした。予約時でも必要の書類として「在留カード」も掲載なかったし、意味もなく
「外国人だから在留資格や在留カードをチェックしよう」という行為自体は人種差別の行為ととらえることも無理もないので
エアアジアの&lt;a href="https://eform.airasia.com/"&gt;Eフォーム&lt;/a&gt;から問い合わせをしました。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;マレーシア国籍で日本中長期滞在の者ですが、マレーシア行きのフライトのチェックイン時にパスポートを提示したにも関わらず在留カードの提示が求められました。航空券を購入したときでも、サイト上でも「在留カードの提示が必要」ということどこでも掲載がなかったので、びっくりしました。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;他の航空会社を利用した際にパスポート以外は在留カード等を求められたことがなかったので違和感を感じ、提示することを断ったのですが、御社のスタッフは「義務ですから」と言い、提示しなければフライト搭乗拒否すると言っています。そもそも、在留カードの提示を求めることできるのは、官憲の方だけで、航空会社のスタッフは強制的に求められることはないと思います。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;日本国籍の方ももちろん、短期滞在の外国の方（在留カード持ってないもの）がパスポートだけで十分サービス提供が行ってることにも関わらず、強制的に在留カード持ってるものだけ別扱いをすることはどうかと思います。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;そこで、以下の質問を答えてください。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1) 在留カード持参の者だけが在留カードを提示求められるのはなぜですか。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2) その理由は何かの法令または行政の指導基づいたことでしょうか。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3) 他航空会社を実施してないので御社だけが実施することになってるということなので自主的に行っていると思いますが、パスポートで十分のはずなのに提示を拒否した乗客に対してサービスを拒否することを問題と思います。これに対してどう思いますか？
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;そうすると、2週間後以下の回答がきました。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;本件、お待たせしており大変申し訳ございません。
弊社にて調査した結果を以下のとおり回答させていただきます。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;=================================================&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1) 在留カード持参の者だけが在留カードを提示求められるのはなぜですか。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2) その理由は何かの法令または行政の指導基づいたことでしょうか。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;=================================================&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;弊社では在留カードをお持ちの外国籍のお客様でかつ日本発着のフライトのご予約をお持ちのお客様については、パスポートに加え、日本への再入国の要件をお客様が満たしているか確認するため、お持ちの在留カードを必ず確認させて頂いております。
なお、この対応は入国管理局の規定に基づいたものである旨申し添えます。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;羽田空港の弊社地上業務担当部署によると、IQBAL様のご予約は羽田クアラルンプール間の往復のご予約でしたので、カウンターのスタッフが在留カードの提示をお願いさせて頂いたということです。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;==================================================&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3) 他航空会社を実施してないので御社だけが実施することになってるということなので自主的に行っていると思いますが、パスポートで十分のはずなのに提示を拒否した乗客に対してサービスを拒否することを問題と思います。これに対してどう思いますか？&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;==================================================&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;弊社では、入国管理局の規定に従い、日本発着のフライトのご予約をお持ちであり、かつ在留カードをお持ちの外国籍のお客様については在留カードを渡航書類の一部として取り扱っております。
そのため、在留カードをご提示頂けない場合、お客様が利用された羽田クアラルンプール間のフライトに適用される弊社の運送約款(7.1(i))に従い運送拒否をさせていただく場合もございます。
なお、弊社にて調査しましたところ、他の航空会社においても日本発着のフライトのご予約をお持ちであり、かつ在留カードをお持ちの外国籍のお客様に対しては在留カードの確認を行っております。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;しかしながら今回弊社地上係員の言動、また説明を十分に行わなかったことによりIQBAL様におかれましては大変ご不快な思いをさせてしまいましたことを心よりお詫び申し上げます。
今後更なるサービス向上に努めると共に、お客様に快適なご旅程をお送り頂けるよう社員一同一層気を引き締めて参ります。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ということだそうです。
個人的にはこれで納得できると思います。外国（アメリカやビサが必要の国に）へ行く時にチェックイン時にその国へ入国できる
資格を持っているかどうかをチェックされることが同じと考えています（ただそのときはパスポートだけをチェックされるけど）。
もちろん、片道のチケットだけをかっておいて日本に戻るかどうか本人が決まってないときに航空会社またわざわざ在留カード
をみることになったら意味合いが違っているけど。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;それにしてもエアアジア側として、事前説明が不十分だと思いますので、予約時や、チェックイン時に「往復のチケットをご購入の中長期滞在
の外国のお客様の再入国要件を確認するため在留カードを確認させていただいています」と一言を置いて貰えれば、誤解を招いた不愉快の
思いをさせることがないかなと思います。それを指摘すると、更にエアアジアから以下の回答を頂いています。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;この度は貴重なご意見を頂きましてありがとうございます。
IQBAL様より頂いたご意見は担当部署に申し伝え、今後のサービス向上に繋げさせて頂きます。
在留カードなど渡航書類を確認する際にはなぜ確認する必要があるのか、往復便をお持ちなので確認させて頂く必要がある、などといった明確な理由をもってお客様にご案内をするよう改善に努めます。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;今後このようなことがないよう、社員一同気をつけて参りますので是非またエアアジアの翼をお選び頂きます様お願いを申し上げます。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;エアアジア　カスタマーケア&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;日本にまだ一般的にこの辺のことの意識は低いところがあると思いますので、皆さんと一緒に誰にでも（女性・マイノリティ・外国人含む）住みやすい日本にして良くしていきましょう。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;日本に戻る場所にしている限り私達の未来は一緒ですから。&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2017"></category><category term="エアアジア"></category><category term="在留カード"></category><category term="外国人"></category></entry><entry><title>あいさつをやめましょう。</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/ja/posts/2016/11/no-greeting-condo/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-11-09T08:30:00+09:00</published><updated>2016-11-09T08:30:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabdullah.net,2016-11-09:/ja/posts/2016/11/no-greeting-condo/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;日本の近所付き合いの最先端だそうです。&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Twitterで以下の投稿を見かけたが、&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Letter to the editor on no greeting condo" src="https://iqbalabdullah.net/ja/images/no-aisatsu-twitter.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;読んでビックリした。教育上だからと言って周りの社会まで巻き込んで近所の付き合い方（というか防犯対策上も問題になりそうだが）を根本的に変えちゃう
というのはどうかと思うけど。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;「マンション内のあいさつは禁止」&lt;/strong&gt; という張り紙でもだすのでしょうか。やっぱりこっちも理解苦しんでいるわ。&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2016"></category><category term="近所付き合い"></category><category term="マンション生活"></category><category term="喜劇"></category></entry><entry><title>Let's stop saying hello</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/en/posts/2016/11/no-greeting-condo/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-11-09T08:30:00+09:00</published><updated>2016-11-09T08:30:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabdullah.net,2016-11-09:/en/posts/2016/11/no-greeting-condo/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The cutting edge on living together in a condo&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So I saw this on Twitter:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Letter to the editor on no greeting condo" src="https://iqbalabdullah.net/ja/images/no-aisatsu-twitter.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A person wrote to the local newspaper telling the story of his condominium making a new rule to not allow greeting each other. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the story goes, one of the parents was telling the management committee that they were teaching their children to not greet anyone that they know, and since it's difficult for children to know whether a person is an occupant of the condo complex or not, the parents were asking the committee to make a rule to not allow greetings in the condo complex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, one of the older occupants was also saying that since their greetings always go unanswered and don't make them feel any better, why not we just stop with all the greetings altogether? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so the occupants have reached an agreement not to greet each other, and now they need to publish the new rule so that the rest of the condo complex occupants know and follow it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2016"></category><category term="everyday life"></category><category term="japan"></category><category term="comedy"></category></entry></feed>