<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Iqbal's Weblog</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://iqbalabdullah.net/</id><updated>2024-08-09T23:15:00+09:00</updated><entry><title>The PSF Board Election Results For 2024: What I Think</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/posts/2024/07/the-psf-election-results-2024-what-i-think/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-07-17T07:30:00+09:00</published><updated>2024-08-09T23:15:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabdullah.net,2024-07-17:/posts/2024/07/the-psf-election-results-2024-what-i-think/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The 2024 PSF Board elections are closed and counted. This is what I think&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Congratulations To The Winners&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, congratulations to all the winners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am happy that a member of our APAC community &lt;a href="https://x.com/darjeelingt"&gt;Kwon-Han&lt;/a&gt;
managed to get the largest vote count.  &lt;a href="https://x.com/cmaureir"&gt;Cristián&lt;/a&gt; will be a new incoming board member, and I think he is long overdue to be on the
board as a member of Latam. Congratulations too to &lt;a href="https://x.com/ixek"&gt;Tania&lt;/a&gt; for winning another term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is bittersweet for me to see &lt;a href="https://x.com/pydebb"&gt;Débora&lt;/a&gt; finish her term. She is a strong ally in the &lt;a href="https://wiki.python.org/psf/DiversityandInclusionWG"&gt;Diversity &amp;amp; Inclusion Workgroup&lt;/a&gt; I'm involved in. I believe she has done a great job on the PSF Board, with her efforts to bridge the community at large and the PSF and the internalization of PSF material, which impacts the millions of Python users worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bylaw Changes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alongside the Board seat elections, we also had an election on &lt;a href="https://discuss.python.org/t/for-your-consideration-proposed-bylaws-changes-to-improve-our-membership-experience/55696"&gt;three proposed bylaw changes&lt;/a&gt;, which have also all been passed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Some Stats&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For 2024, there were 3 board seats up for election and &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/2024-python-software-foundation-board/nominees/"&gt;19 candidates&lt;/a&gt; (6.3 ratio of candidates to seats)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/2023-python-software-foundation-board/nominees/"&gt;In 2023, we had 15 nominees&lt;/a&gt; for 4 board seats (3.75 ratio) &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/2022-python-software-foundation-board/nominees/"&gt;In 2022, we had 26 nominees&lt;/a&gt; for 4 board seats (6.5 ratio)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/2021-python-software-foundation-board/nominees/?ref=refind"&gt;In 2021, we had 19 nominees&lt;/a&gt; for 3 board seats (6.3 ratio)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/2020-python-software-foundation-board/nominees/"&gt;In 2020, we had 26 nominees&lt;/a&gt; for 4 seats (6.5 ratio)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looks like for the past few years a 6.3 to 6.5 ratio had been the norm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What We Need To Improve&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many things of course. But from these election results, I noticed a few.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Despite our efforts to increase the voter base, the amount of votes cast and voting members were less than the previous year. 
  &lt;em&gt;NOTE: that the way we count eligible members changed from 2023 so we can't compare anything previous to that.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Year&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Votes Cast&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Eligible Members&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Turnout Rate&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://opavote.com/results/5004101476679680"&gt;2024&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;611 (-1% YoY)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;794 (-10% YoY)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;77%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://pyfound.blogspot.com/2023/06/announcing-2023-psf-board-election.html"&gt;2023&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;621 (&lt;strong&gt;+7.4&lt;/strong&gt;% YoY)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;877 (N/A)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;71%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://pyfound.blogspot.com/2022/07/board-election-results-for-2022.html"&gt;2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;578 (-3.5% YoY)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1459&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N/A&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://discuss.python.org/t/2021-python-software-foundation-board-of-directors-election-results/9418"&gt;2021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;599 (&lt;strong&gt;+30%&lt;/strong&gt; YoY)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1538&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N/A&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://pyfound.blogspot.com/2020/06/2020-python-software-foundation-board.html"&gt;2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;462&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1151&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N/A&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because there is no data to breakdown voters according to region, we do not know how much impact our efforts in the APAC region for the past year have made an increase in the voter base, although we have a record number of nominations for candidates from the APAC region such as Ivy and Kwon-Han this year, which shows a greater interest in the elections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the &lt;a href="https://pyfound.blogspot.com/2024/06/for-your-consideration-proposed-bylaws.html"&gt;new bylaw changes&lt;/a&gt; being passed for this election, we can expect the 611 voting members in 2024 will also vote in 2025 because they do not have to reaffirm their desire to vote. Reaffirming your vote has been an ongoing issue because the steps to do so were not intuitive and have been a barrier to increasing participation in the PSF Board elections. Hopefully, with this bylaw change, we can see some stability and also an increase in voter base.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We don't have anyone from the African continent to represent us. The two candidates (Abigail and Monica) we had from Africa didn't manage to get enough votes to be elected to the Board, and we don't have anyone on the Board right now active in the African continent.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The way some of our community members handled their &lt;a href="https://discuss.python.org/t/for-your-consideration-proposed-bylaws-changes-to-improve-our-membership-experience/55696"&gt;disagreements with the proposed bylaw change #3&lt;/a&gt; was
disappointing. Disagreements are fine and are a fact of life (in fact it is healthy and sometimes fun because we can learn something new) but the way some members of our community disagreed with each other while making snide
remarks, questioning trust while implying how &lt;em&gt;long&lt;/em&gt; they have been around doing this and that doesn't make the conversation appealing to new people and pushes them away.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Progress I'm Happy About&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also many things. But these would be the main ones:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kwon-Han getting the most votes. As a member of the APAC region I'm involved in, I'm happy to see him getting the support that he is getting. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cristián getting elected to the board. He is an active leader of the Python community and he is &lt;em&gt;everywhere&lt;/em&gt;. Just read his nomination statement &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/2024-python-software-foundation-board/nominees/cristian-maureira-fredes/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. His experience in helping the community and connection to people will be an asset to the PSF.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/2024-python-software-foundation-board/nominees/ivy-fung/"&gt;Ivy Fung&lt;/a&gt;, a first-time nominee for the PSF Board elections getting 37% approval from voters.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Record number of nominations for &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/2024-python-software-foundation-board/nominees/kwonhan-bae/"&gt;Kwon-Han&lt;/a&gt; (13) and Ivy (9), our nominees from APAC.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At least one nominee has her nomination statement in a language other than English.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We have a &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/2024-python-software-foundation-board/nominees/ali-tavallaie/"&gt;nominee from Tehran, Ali&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Increased interest in the PSF and participating in the Board elections within my own APAC community.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We have high turnout rates since 2023. &lt;a href="https://www.oecd-ilibrary.org/social-issues-migration-health/society-at-a-glance-2019_3483a69a-en"&gt;In our world, a 70% turnout rate is considered the median for major elections&lt;/a&gt;. (Thanks to &lt;a href="https://mastodon.social/@hugovk/112800501986331260"&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt; for reminding me of this data)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;After 5 Years&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reading back &lt;a href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/posts/2020/06/diversification-is-the-future-for-the-psf/"&gt;my post&lt;/a&gt; after I first ran for a board seat reminded me of the things which I wanted to change. These were &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Diversification&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;in representation on the Board&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;in the financials of the PSF&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;in our voter base&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Indifference to the PSF&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since 2020, I believe we have seen &lt;a href="https://observablehq.com/@terezaif/psf-board-timeline"&gt;progress in the diversification of representation by region&lt;/a&gt; within the PSF Board, although at
times it seems like we're taking two steps forward and a step back. We now have someone from the APAC region on the
board, which we have not had before, but no one to represent the African continent, which we once had. It is still North
America and Europe centric, but with a different shade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of financials, the PSF is still overdependent on PyCon US. In 2019, the PSF's revenue was 61% coming from
hosting PyCon US while 28% were from grants and membership fees. Based on the &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/annual-report/2023/"&gt;2023 PSF's Annual Report&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;we're now at
48% dependent on PyCon US while grants and membership fees take 30% . This is a decrease from 2020.&lt;/strong&gt; We're making progress on this front, although the PSF is seeing a deficit for 2023. &lt;sup id="fnref:fn01"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:fn01"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
I'm not too worried about the deficit though, because we know the PSF has just made big hires for people to work
in-house on PyPI and also on the security front.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our voter base doesn't seem to have changed much if we just look at the total amount of votes counted. Having data to
breakdown the amount of votes coming in from regions would be great, but I'm not sure how we can technically do this
without tying the votes to membership data. I am genuinely surprised to not see a significant increase after all the
promotion work we have done. If &lt;a href="https://observablehq.com/@terezaif/who-voted-in-the-psf-board-elections"&gt;Tereza's data&lt;/a&gt; is any sort of indicator, we need to get people to
nominate more of their peers to Fellows. I have been actively doing that on a personal level and try to &lt;a href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/posts/2024/05/nominating-pythonistas-at-the-psf/"&gt;include how many people I have nominated in conversations I had&lt;/a&gt; to increase awareness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aside from the voter base, I think the biggest progress we have made is on the indifference towards the PSF itself, at least from the more active members of our community.
I have seen, experienced and helped out on many initiative within our APAC community to promote the PSF in the forms of membership drive, lightning
talks and keynotes. Many of these are done through community initiaitves without explicit requests from the PSF. We now
see multiple people from the APAC region running for a Board seat, and even one of us are on the Board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am happy to play a small role in making our world a smaller place for our community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Further Reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/posts/2020/06/diversification-is-the-future-for-the-psf/"&gt;Diversification Is The Future Of The PSF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/posts/2022/07/the-future-is-still-not-here-for-the-psf-2022/"&gt;The Future Is Still Not Here For The PSF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/posts/2023/07/a-step-closer-to-the-future-for-the-psf-2023/"&gt;A Step Closer To The Future For The PSF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://micro.webology.dev/2024/07/16/my-thoughts-on.html"&gt;My thoughts on the PSF Election results - Jeff Triplett's Micro.blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://maureira.xyz/posts/getting-elected-for-the-psf-board-of-directors.html"&gt;Getting elected for the PSF Board of Directors - Cristián Maureira-Fredes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:fn01"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Updated with latest data from the PSF. Thank you to Phyllis, Deb and Jeff for pointing this out&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:fn01" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="2024"></category><category term="psf"></category><category term="politics"></category><category term="community work"></category><category term="elections"></category><category term="python community"></category></entry><entry><title>Getting Started With Python in Malaysia</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/posts/2024/06/getting-started-with-python-in-malaysia/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-06-17T21:30:00+09:00</published><updated>2024-06-17T21:30:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabdullah.net,2024-06-17:/posts/2024/06/getting-started-with-python-in-malaysia/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Tips and resources to start learning Python without spending (much) money if you're in Malaysia&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Python Is The Rage Now&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read &lt;a href="https://x.com/reviewbyyasmin/status/1802258242342736212"&gt;on the internet&lt;/a&gt; about people wanting to join Python and data science-related courses offered by government-led agencies. These courses are mostly free (funded by taxpayers) but have limited space, and some are restricted to those under 30 years old.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upskilling isn't just for the young, and learning Python shouldn't require significant financial investment. You can start immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Python is a versatile language used in various domains, from powering the internet and &lt;a href="https://huggingface.co/learn/nlp-course/en/chapter0/1"&gt;developing AI applications&lt;/a&gt; to being utilized in &lt;a href="https://datatas.com/does-nasa-use-python/"&gt;outer space&lt;/a&gt;. Its popularity and success stem from being &lt;a href="https://github.com/python/cpython"&gt;open-source&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/downloads/"&gt;free to download and use&lt;/a&gt;, which lowers barriers to its use and improvement by the public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Learning Python For Free&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I first picked up Python in 2002 (v1.5.2) without spending a sen, and so can you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are numerous online resources available for free to start learning Python. Sifting through them all might be overwhelming, so I'll suggest a few built on another reason for Python's popularity: its community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Learn By Doing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had tasks I wanted to automate, like pulling data from a website or sending SMS from my computer. You likely have your projects in mind. Spend a few minutes considering them, and start exploring how you can accomplish these tasks with Python. Hands-on experience is the fastest way to learn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some free materials that will be useful:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn To Program. For Free: Al Sweigart's &lt;a href="https://inventwithpython.com"&gt;Invent With Python&lt;/a&gt;
    I met Al at PyCon PH in 2018. He writes books for beginners and generously makes these materials available for free. His book &lt;a href="https://automatetheboringstuff.com"&gt;Automate The Boring Stuff With Python&lt;/a&gt; is particularly useful for generating ideas on what you can build with Python.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Join a &lt;a href="https://t.me/belajarpythonbot"&gt;local Telegram group "BelajarPythonBot"&lt;/a&gt; maintained by &lt;a href="https://x.com/k4ml"&gt;Kamal Mustafa&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://x.com/AmirulAbu"&gt;Amirul&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trey Hunner's &lt;a href="https://www.pythonmorsels.com/newsletter/"&gt;Python Morsels newsletter&lt;/a&gt;
    I met Trey at PyCon US. He writes newsletters and &lt;a href="https://x.com/treyhunner"&gt;tips on X&lt;/a&gt; about Python. His material might be intermediate level, but skimming through it can help familiarize you with technical terminology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Learn By Listening&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learning a new spoken language effectively often involves listening to it spoken. Initially, you might not understand the words, but getting a feel for the language's rhythm and expression can enhance your understanding when you start practicing. The same applies to programming languages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mike Kennedy's &lt;a href="https://talkpython.fm"&gt;Talk Python To Me&lt;/a&gt;
    I met Mike at PyCon PH in 2024. His podcast features interviews with people working with or using Python in various capacities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Learn Python Together&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next step is motivating yourself to continue learning and upskilling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After familiarizing yourself with the syntax and technical language, meeting people can provide motivation and reduce the likelihood of giving up after a few months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Python community is incredibly welcoming. Find a group near you and get involved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Meetups: Community members sometimes organize meetups to learn together. While there aren't many Python user groups in Malaysia, there are some related ones.&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://tfugmy.peatix.com"&gt;Artificial Intelligence And Machine Learning Malaysia User Group&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Women-driven data analytics, data science, data engineering, and ML community &lt;a href="https://x.com/WanitaData"&gt;Wanita Data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PyCons: Python conferences, known as PyCons, occur at both country levels, like &lt;a href="https://pycon.my/"&gt;PyCon MY (Malaysia)&lt;/a&gt;, and regionally, such as &lt;a href="https://europython.eu"&gt;EuroPython&lt;/a&gt; for Europe and &lt;a href="https://pycon.asia"&gt;PyCon APAC&lt;/a&gt; for Asia-Pacific.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Specific interest groups, like the women-led &lt;a href="https://pyladies.com/locations/"&gt;PyLadies&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://www.meetup.com/PyDataKL/"&gt;PyData&lt;/a&gt;, provide safe spaces for minorities within our community to learn.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meetups are often free, but PyCons usually have an entry fee. However, PyCons strive to keep ticket prices affordable or they wouldn't be considered PyCons. Most also offer travel grants and free tickets through sponsorships.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Happy Coding&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learning Python in Malaysia is accessible and affordable thanks to numerous free resources and a supportive community. By leveraging materials like Al Sweigart's books and Trey Hunner's newsletters, you can begin learning without financial strain. Engaging with the community through meetups, user groups, and PyCons not only enhances your learning experience but also provides motivation and support from like-minded individuals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Python's versatility and widespread use across industries make it a valuable skill. Consistency is crucial when learning Python or anything new. Spending an hour a day for a month is more effective than cramming 10 hours into three days. Celebrate your progress and enjoy the journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happy coding, and may your Python journey be as rewarding as it is exciting!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P.S: &lt;em&gt;Thanks to &lt;a href="https://x.com/sweemeng"&gt;Swee Meng&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://x.com/k4ml"&gt;Kamal&lt;/a&gt; for proofreading this post.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2024"></category><category term="python"></category><category term="newbie"></category><category term="learning"></category><category term="my"></category></entry><entry><title>Mula Belajar Python di Malaysia</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/ms/posts/2024/06/getting-started-with-python-in-malaysia/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-06-17T21:30:00+09:00</published><updated>2024-06-17T21:30:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabdullah.net,2024-06-17:/ms/posts/2024/06/getting-started-with-python-in-malaysia/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Tips dan sumber untuk mula belajar Python tanpa mengeluarkan (banyak) wang untuk anda di Malaysia&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Python Kini Popular&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saya membaca &lt;a href="https://x.com/reviewbyyasmin/status/1802258242342736212"&gt;di internet&lt;/a&gt; tentang mereka yang ingin menyertai kursus berkaitan Python dan sains data yang ditawarkan oleh agensi kerajaan. Kursus-kursus ini kebanyakannya percuma (dibiayai oleh pembayar cukai) tetapi mempunyai ruang terhad, dan sesetengahnya hanya terbuka untuk mereka di bawah umur 30 tahun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Menambah kemahiran bukan hanya untuk golongan muda, dan mempelajari juga Python tidak semestinya memerlukan pelaburan kewangan yang besar. Sesiapa sahaja boleh mula sekarang.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Python adalah bahasa pegaturcara serbaguna yang digunakan dalam pelbagai bidang, daripada memperkuasakan internet dan &lt;a href="https://huggingface.co/learn/nlp-course/en/chapter0/1"&gt;membangunkan aplikasi AI&lt;/a&gt; hingga digunakan di &lt;a href="https://datatas.com/does-nasa-use-python/"&gt;angkasa lepas&lt;/a&gt;. Populariti dan kejayaannya disebabkan kerana Python adalah &lt;a href="https://github.com/python/cpython"&gt;sumber terbuka&lt;/a&gt; dan &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/downloads/"&gt;percuma untuk dimuat turun dan digunakan&lt;/a&gt;. Ini mempermudahkan Python digunakan dan ditambahbaikkan oleh orang ramai.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Belajar Python Secara Percuma&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saya mula belajar Python pada tahun 2002 (v1.5.2) tanpa mengeluarkan sesen pun, dan anda juga boleh berbuat demikian.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Terdapat banyak sumber dalam talian yang tersedia secara percuma untuk mula belajar Python. Mungkin agak memeningkan kepala untuk membacanya semua sekali, jadi saya akan mencadangkan beberapa yang dibina atas sebab lain bagi populariti Python: komunitinya.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Belajar Python Secara Mencuba&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saya mempunyai tugas yang ingin saya automasikan, seperti mengambil data dari laman web atau menghantar SMS dari komputer saya. Anda juga mungkin mempunyai projek yang ingin dilakukan. Luangkan beberapa minit untuk mempertimbangkannya, dan mula meneroka bagaimana anda boleh menyelesaikan tugas-tugas ini dengan Python. Mencuba adalah cara terpantas untuk belajar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Berikut adalah beberapa bahan percuma yang mungkin berguna:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn To Program. For Free: Al Sweigart's &lt;a href="https://inventwithpython.com"&gt;Invent With Python&lt;/a&gt;
    Saya berjumpa dengan Al buat pertama kalinya di PyCon PH Manila tahun 2018. Buku beliau &lt;a href="https://automatetheboringstuff.com"&gt;Automate The Boring Stuff With Python&lt;/a&gt; juga berguna untuk mendapatkan idea perkara yang boleh kita bina dengan Python.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sertai komuniti &lt;a href="https://t.me/belajarpythonbot"&gt;"BelajarPythonBot" di Telegram&lt;/a&gt; yang dikendalikan oleh &lt;a href="https://x.com/k4ml"&gt;Kamal Mustafa&lt;/a&gt; dan &lt;a href="https://x.com/AmirulAbu"&gt;Amirul&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trey Hunner's &lt;a href="https://www.pythonmorsels.com/newsletter/"&gt;Python Morsels newsletter&lt;/a&gt;
    Saya berjumpa Trey buat pertama kalinya di PyCon US. Dia menulis &lt;em&gt;newsletter&lt;/em&gt; dan juga &lt;a href="https://x.com/treyhunner"&gt;tips di X&lt;/a&gt; mengenai Python. Tulisan Trey mungkin tidak sesuai untuk yang beru mahu berjinak dengan Python, tetapi kalau kita biasakan membaca tulisan Trey kita dapat membiasakan diri dengan bahasa teknikal yang sering digunakan dalam peraturcaraan Python.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Belajar Python Dengan Mendengar&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Membiasakan diri dengan mendengar percakapan adalah satu cara efektif untuk kita belajar bahasa baru. Sama juga dengan
bahasa pengaturcaraan seperti Python. Kemungkinan kita tidak akan dapat memahami semua ertikata dalam perbualan tersebut
tetapi membiasakan diri dengan ritma dan cara bahasa pengaturcaraan itu diceritakan akan menolong kita lebih cepat untuk
memahami konsep-konsep yang kita belajar semasa mencuba bahasa tersebut.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://talkpython.fm"&gt;Talk Python To Me&lt;/a&gt; oleh Mike Kennedy.
    Pertama kali saya bertermu Mike adalah di PyCon PH di Manila tahun 2024. &lt;code&gt;Podcast&lt;/code&gt; beliau mempertengahkan mereka yang berkerja dengan Python dan memperkenalkan cara-cara yang menarik bagaimana Python digunakan.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Belajar Python Bersama-Sama&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Langkah setersunya ialah untuk anda memotivasikan diri untuk terus belajar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Selepas membiasakan diri dengan cara penulisan dan terma-terma teknikal Python, berjumpa dengan orang lain boleh
memberikan anda motivasi dan mengurangkan kebarangkalian anda putus-asa selepas beberapa bulan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kommuniti Python mengalualukan penglibatan orang yang baru belajar seperti anda. Cari kumpulan terdekat dan libatkan
diri.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;Meetups&lt;/code&gt;: Ahli-ahli komuniti kadang-kadang berjumpa dan belajar bersama. Walaupun di Malaysia tidak banyak kumpulan pengguna Python, masih ada komuniti yang berkaitan.&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://tfugmy.peatix.com"&gt;Artificial Intelligence And Machine Learning Malaysia User Group&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Komuniti analisis data, sains data, kejuruteraan data, dan ML yang dipacu oleh wanita &lt;a href="https://x.com/WanitaData"&gt;Wanita Data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;PyCons&lt;/code&gt;: Persidangan Python, dikenali sebagai PyCons, diadakan di peringkat negara seperti &lt;a href="https://pycon.my/"&gt;PyCon MY (Malaysia)&lt;/a&gt;, dan secara serantau seperti &lt;a href="https://europython.eu"&gt;EuroPython&lt;/a&gt; untuk Eropah dan &lt;a href="https://pycon.asia"&gt;PyCon APAC&lt;/a&gt; untuk Asia-Pasifik.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kumpulan khusus, seperti &lt;a href="https://pyladies.com/locations/"&gt;PyLadies&lt;/a&gt; yang dipimpin dan khas untuk wanita yang berkecimpung dalam pengaturcaraan Python atau &lt;a href="https://www.meetup.com/PyDataKL/"&gt;PyData&lt;/a&gt; yang memberikan ruang selamat untuk kumpulan minoriti di dalam komuniti kita untuk belajar bersama.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meetups biasanya percuma, tetapi &lt;code&gt;PyCons&lt;/code&gt; biasanya mengenakan yuran penyertaan. Walau bagaimanapun, &lt;code&gt;PyCons&lt;/code&gt; berusaha untuk mengekalkan harga tiket yang berpatutan atau mereka tidak boleh dipanggil &lt;code&gt;PyCon&lt;/code&gt;. Kebanyakan juga menawarkan geran perjalanan dan tiket percuma melalui tajaan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Selamat Berkoding&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Memperlajari Python di Malaysia adalah mudah disebabkan oleh banyak sumber percuma dan komuniti yang menyokong. Dengan memanfaatkan bahan seperti buku-buku Al Sweigart dan buletin Trey Hunner, anda boleh mula belajar tanpa membelanjakan wang.
Melibatkan diri dengan komuniti melalui meetup dan PyCon bukan sahaja mempertingkatkan pengalaman pembelajaran anda tetapi juga memberikan motivasi dan sokongan diri.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Penggunaan Python yang meluas di perlbagai industri menjadikan kemahiran menggunakannya sangat berharga. Pembelajaran konsisten adalah kunci ketika mempelajari Python atau apa-apa pun yang baru. Menghabiskan sejam sehari selama sebulan adalah lebih efektif daripada 10 jam dalam tiga hari. Raikan kemajuan dan nikmati perjalanan pembelajaran anda.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Selamat berkoding, dan semoga perjalanan Python anda berjaya!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P.S: &lt;em&gt;Terima kasih kepada &lt;a href="https://x.com/sweemeng"&gt;Swee Meng&lt;/a&gt; dan &lt;a href="https://x.com/k4ml"&gt;Kamal&lt;/a&gt; kerana menolong membaca
pruf unuk post ini.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2024"></category><category term="python"></category><category term="newbie"></category><category term="pembelajaran"></category><category term="my"></category></entry><entry><title>Nominating Pythonistas For Stuff At The Python Software Foundation (PSF)</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/posts/2024/05/nominating-pythonistas-at-the-psf/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-05-20T09:20:00+09:00</published><updated>2024-05-23T20:27:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabdullah.net,2024-05-20:/posts/2024/05/nominating-pythonistas-at-the-psf/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A README to nominating your fellow Pythonistas for stuff at the PSF&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Do you know that you can nominate your favorite hardworking person or group for stuff and recognize them for their work at the PSF, and do all this for &lt;em&gt;free&lt;/em&gt;? (i.e., free as in free tea)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Acknowledge And Thank Them: Nominating Your Fellow Pythonistas&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before 2014, the Python Software Foundation (PSF) didn't have a formal nomination process or criteria. When they moved to an open membership organization (basically meaning anyone can join as a member of the PSF), they created formal processes for nomination and granting special recognition to members of its community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did an Open Space during PyCon US 2024 in Pittsburgh to exactly share my experiences and answer questions on this topic. During the closing of the conference, &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/denicholson/"&gt;Deb Nicholson&lt;/a&gt; – who is the Executive Director of the PSF – got on stage and pointed out that we've had no Community Service Award (CSA) to present this year due to a lack of nominations. With all the great things everyone is working on in any particular year, it's really difficult to think that no one deserves the CSA; so the only possible thing is that our community just aren't aware enough that they can do such nominations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;What Can You Nominate For?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's more than just the CSA. You can nominate your fellow Pythonistas for these:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PSF Fellow&lt;/strong&gt;: The PSF Fellow membership is a special membership awarded to individuals who have made significant contributions to the Python community through their work, including contributions to the development of Python, supporting the infrastructure, organizing events, and other impactful activities. PSF Fellow nominations are handled and decided upon by the &lt;a href="https://wiki.python.org/psf/FellowWG/Charter"&gt;PSF Fellow Workgroup&lt;/a&gt;. More details can be found on the &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/fellows/"&gt;PSF Fellow Membership page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PSF Community Service Award&lt;/strong&gt;: This is the CSA. It recognizes individuals or groups that have performed exceptional volunteer service for the Python community. It highlights those who have dedicated significant time and effort to improve the community through various means, such as organizing events, contributing to educational resources, or supporting community initiatives. The decision to award the CSA to an individual or a group is decided by the PSF Board. Details are available on the &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/community/awards/psf-awards/"&gt;PSF Community Service Award page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Outstanding PyLady Award&lt;/strong&gt;: This award is given to individuals who have made significant contributions to the PyLadies community, which is dedicated to promoting diversity and supporting women and gender minorities in the Python community. It celebrates those who have gone above and beyond in mentoring, organizing events, and fostering an inclusive environment. The decisions on awarding the Outstanding PyLady Award are done by the PyLadies Global Council. You can learn more about this award &lt;a href="https://kit.pyladies.com/en/latest/global/award.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PSF Distinguished Service Award&lt;/strong&gt;: This is the Foundation's highest award. The Distinguished Service Award is an offer of recognition for sustained exemplary contributions to the Python community. This award is given for actions which carry significant impact that shapes the Python world, whether through contributions of code, efforts in community action, or otherwise. As with the Community Service Award, the intention is to demonstrate that such service to the community does lead to recognition and reward, rather than to provide a direct incentive to contributors. You can learn more about this award &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/community/awards/psf-distinguished-awards/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These awards and recognitions are excellent ways to highlight and celebrate the invaluable contributions of Pythonistas around the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PSF Board Directorship&lt;/strong&gt;: Although a responsibility, not an award, nominating someone for Directorship is still meaningful. The PSF Board of Directors oversees the Foundation's activities and ensures its mission is carried out effectively. Board Directors are elected by the PSF membership and play a crucial role in strategic decision-making and governance. Read more on the &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/"&gt;PSF Board Elections page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Why Should You Nominate?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nominating someone for recognition within the Python Software Foundation (PSF) is not just a formality – it's a powerful way to celebrate and acknowledge the hard work and dedication that Python community members invest in the ecosystem. Recognizing individuals and groups:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Promotes Positive Community Spirit&lt;/strong&gt;: By acknowledging contributions, we foster a culture of appreciation and motivation, which encourages more people to get involved and contribute to the community.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Highlights Diverse Contributions&lt;/strong&gt;: Recognizing the work of different individuals showcases the variety of ways people can contribute, whether through code, community organizing, education, or advocacy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Encourages Continued Involvement&lt;/strong&gt;: Awarding community members can incentivize them to continue their efforts, knowing that their work is valued and noticed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Builds a Stronger Network&lt;/strong&gt;: Celebrating achievements helps build stronger connections within the community, facilitating collaboration and support among members.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're living in the gift economy. Gifts turn the wheels in our world. Open source is a gift. The unpaid labor that people do to support the community around open source is a gift. Welcoming people into our community regardless of age, gender, economic status or education level is a gift. Saying thank you and acknowledging our peers in the community is also a gift that pays them back. Naomi Ceder says this best in her &lt;a href="https://www.naomiceder.tech/posts/pycon_keynote_2022/"&gt;A Time of Gifts keynote&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it's crucial to ensure that the recognition process is inclusive and represents the diverse Python global community. Certain groups have been underrepresented in technology and community leadership roles. For example, the communities from my region (the East Asia, South Asia and Southeast Asia) only had 18 PSF Fellow memberships and 2 CSA recipients (one representing a group), out of around a total of 500 PSF Fellows and around 100 individuals for the CSA. That's just around 4% and 2% of the total recipients. When we consider there are around &lt;a href="https://thefortunate.blog/diversification-is-the-future-for-the-psf.html"&gt;8.2 million Python developers or users worldwide&lt;/a&gt; and the biggest growth is within my region, &lt;em&gt;that is&lt;/em&gt; underrepresentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;How Do You Nominate?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The process for nominating someone for recognition at the PSF is straightforward:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Identify the Category&lt;/strong&gt;: Determine which award or recognition is most appropriate for the individual or group you want to nominate. This could be a PSF Fellow, Community Service Award, Board Directorship, or Outstanding PyLady Award.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prepare the Nomination&lt;/strong&gt;: Collect information about the nominee, including their contributions to the Python community, specific achievements, and any other relevant details. The nomination should highlight why the nominee deserves the recognition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Submit the Nomination&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For &lt;strong&gt;PSF Fellow&lt;/strong&gt; nominations, you can submit via email. Read more on the PSF Fellow membership page &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/fellows/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For the &lt;strong&gt;Community Service Award&lt;/strong&gt;, details and submission instructions can be found on the &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/community/awards/psf-awards/"&gt;PSF Community Service Award page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nominations for &lt;strong&gt;PSF Board Directorship&lt;/strong&gt; are typically part of the annual election process. More information can be found on the &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/"&gt;PSF Board Elections page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Outstanding PyLady Award&lt;/strong&gt; details can be found &lt;a href="https://kit.pyladies.com/en/latest/global/award.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;PSF Distinguished Service Award&lt;/strong&gt; details can be found &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/community/awards/psf-distinguished-awards/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Need for Better Representation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the PSF has made significant strides in promoting diversity and inclusion, such as the creation of the &lt;a href="https://wiki.python.org/psf/DiversityandInclusionWG"&gt;D&amp;amp;I Workgroup&lt;/a&gt; and granting more grants to the African and Asian communities in 2023, there is still a need for better representation from different communities around the world in terms of acknowledging the work of individuals and groups. Many regions are underrepresented in PSF leadership and recognition programs. This lack of representation can create barriers to entry for new contributors and limit the diversity of ideas and perspectives within the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To address this, we need to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Promote Awareness&lt;/strong&gt;: Increase awareness about the nomination processes and opportunities for recognition among underrepresented groups.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Provide Support&lt;/strong&gt;: Offer resources and support to help individuals from diverse backgrounds navigate the nomination process and engage with the community.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Encourage Diverse Nominations&lt;/strong&gt;: Actively seek out and encourage nominations of individuals from underrepresented regions and backgrounds.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mentorship Programs&lt;/strong&gt;: Establish mentorship programs to guide and support new contributors from diverse communities in their journey within the Python ecosystem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By taking these steps, we can ensure that the PSF truly reflects the global and diverse nature of the Python community, fostering an inclusive environment in which all contributions are valued and recognized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;What Can I Do?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plenty!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, if you're not a PSF member yet, sign up &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/membership/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. If you've done work for the community that makes you eligible to be a &lt;a href="https://psfmember.org/civicrm/contribute/transact/?reset=1&amp;amp;id=32"&gt;Managing, Contributing or Supporting member&lt;/a&gt;, make sure you're recognized as such too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, you can nominate someone! If you've been in your community long enough, I'm sure by the time you're reading this, you'll have the person(s) in mind right now. No one? Are you sure? Well, one example I can give is when I get to a new city or community, I ask a few people who would be the best person to talk to for a newcomer to get involved, and if let's say 75% of them give me the same name, then that person would probably be PSF Fellow material. You can then start by getting to know that person and talking about the work they have done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Community Service Awards (CSA) have an easier criteria to understand, but still a high hurdle to be accepted. An example is the nomination that I made for the PyCon JP Association (read more &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/records/board/resolutions/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/community/awards/psf-awards/#december-2021"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, for the charity talks event that they did to raise money for the PSF on the wake of the pandemic, which had disastrous effects on the PSF financially. Another more recent example is the recognition by the board for &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/records/board/minutes/2024-03-13/#new-business"&gt;Leonard Richardson, Lais Cavalho and Raquel Dou to receive the CSA&lt;/a&gt; for the software or community that they have built and maintained, which benefited the community at large.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Distinguished Service Award (DSA) has a much higher hurdle to clear. Since given out in 2012, only 7 people have
received it. Sometimes a CSA nomination can lead to a DSA being awarded, but that is up to the PSF Board to decide. You
can read on the reasons for the DSA to be awarded &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/community/awards/psf-distinguished-awards/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and if you have someone that you think deserves to stand as
tall as these other recepients, that please make a nomination. Nominations can be sent confidentially by email to the
PSF Board as written &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/community/awards/psf-distinguished-awards/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can of course self-nominate, but I personally find this a very difficult thing to do and very boring, so I'm not interested in doing that. It's more fun to write about other people!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, you can help increase awareness of such opportunities to recognize, acknowledge, and elevate your fellow Pythonistas through these nominations: When I'm at PyCon or a Python meetup, I've started to include the amount of nominations I've made in my self-introduction, something like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hey, my name is Iqbal. I sometimes help around here, and have nominated xxx people to the PSF Fellow and xxx for the CSA. Would you like to know more about that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and sometimes I'll be pleasantly surprised that the person I'm talking to will know the person I nominated, and that becomes a great conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have someone in mind that should be recognized but you still don't know how to do it, you can just quickly drop
me a message through my &lt;a href="https://mtd.pythonasia.org/@iqbalabd"&gt;Mastodon&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://x.com/iqbalabd"&gt;X&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="linkedin.com/in/iqbalabd/"&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt; and I'll be happy to help whatever I can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;FAQ&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During my Open Space about PSF Nominations, these are some of the questions we had:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Can you self-nominate?&lt;/strong&gt; - Yes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What's the difference between the Community Service Award (CSA) and PSF Fellow?&lt;/strong&gt; - You can read the official description of what the CSA is for &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/community/awards/psf-awards/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and the PSF Fellow &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/fellows/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. In a nutshell, the CSA celebrates particular acts of service, while the PSF Fellow membership recognizes an individual's comprehensive and distinguished contribution to the Python ecosystems and community.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What's the requirement to nominate someone for the PSF Fellow?&lt;/strong&gt; - There are no hard requirements, but contributions that clearly go beyond your casual organizer or contributor. A good place to get examples are the nomination statements themselves, which are published &lt;a href="https://wiki.python.org/moin/PythonSoftwareFoundation/FellowNominations"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for the PSF Fellow nominations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How do these nominations get decided upon?&lt;/strong&gt; - Anyone can nominate someone, but the nominations are deliberated, accepted or rejected by different groups within the PSF. The PSF Fellow nominations are decided by the &lt;a href="https://wiki.python.org/psf/FellowWG/Charter"&gt;PSF Fellow Workgroup&lt;/a&gt;, the CSA by the &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/board/"&gt;PSF Board&lt;/a&gt; while the Outstanding PyLady Award by the &lt;a href="https://pyladies.com/blog/Announcing-the-Inaugural-PyLadies-Global-Council/inaugural-pyladies-council/"&gt;PyLadies Global Council&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thank you to &lt;a href="https://x.com/cheukting_ho"&gt;Cheuk&lt;/a&gt; for reviewing this post&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2024"></category><category term="pycon"></category><category term="psf"></category><category term="community"></category></entry><entry><title>Python Software Foundation (PSF) で Pythonista をノミネートしよう</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/ja/posts/2024/05/nominating-pythonistas-at-the-psf/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-05-20T09:20:00+09:00</published><updated>2024-05-23T20:27:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabdullah.net,2024-05-20:/ja/posts/2024/05/nominating-pythonistas-at-the-psf/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;PSF で仲間の Pythonista をノミネートするための README&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;PSF であなたの好きな頑張っている人やグループをノミネートして、彼らの仕事を認めることができるって知っていましたか？しかもこれがすべて無料でできるんです！（無料と言っても無料のお茶みたいな感じで）&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;彼らを認めて感謝しよう: 仲間の Pythonista をノミネートする&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2014 年以前、Python Software Foundation (PSF) には正式なノミネーションプロセスや基準がありませんでした。PSF がオープンメンバーシップ組織に移行したとき（基本的に誰でも PSF のメンバーになれるという意味です）、コミュニティのメンバーに特別な認識を与えるための正式なノミネーションプロセスが作られました。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2024 年の PyCon US では、私の経験を共有し、このトピックに関する質問に答えるためにオープンスペースを行いました。会議の閉会時に、PSF のエグゼクティブディレクターである &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/denicholson/"&gt;Deb Nicholson&lt;/a&gt; さんがステージに上がり、今年はノミネーションが不足しているため、コミュニティサービス賞 (CSA) を授与できなかったことを指摘しました。毎年たくさんの素晴らしいことが行われているのに、誰も CSA に値しないとは考えにくいので、私たちのコミュニティがこのようなノミネーションができることを十分に認識していないのだと思います。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;何をノミネートできるの？&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CSA だけじゃありません。仲間の Pythonista を以下のようなものにノミネートできます：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PSF フェロー&lt;/strong&gt;: PSF フェローメンバーシップは、Python コミュニティに重要な貢献をした個人に与えられる特別なメンバーシップです。これには、Python の開発への貢献、インフラのサポート、イベントの企画、その他の影響力のある活動が含まれます。PSF フェローのノミネーションは &lt;a href="https://wiki.python.org/psf/FellowWG/Charter"&gt;PSF フェロー ワークグループ&lt;/a&gt; によって処理され、決定されます。詳細は &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/fellows/"&gt;PSF フェローメンバーシップページ&lt;/a&gt; をご覧ください。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PSF コミュニティサービス賞&lt;/strong&gt;: これが CSA です。Python コミュニティのために特別なボランティアサービスを行った個人やグループを認めます。イベントの企画、教育リソースへの貢献、コミュニティイニシアティブのサポートなど、さまざまな方法でコミュニティを改善するために多大な時間と労力を費やした人々を称賛します。CSA の授与は PSF ボードによって決定されます。詳細は &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/community/awards/psf-awards/"&gt;PSF コミュニティサービス賞ページ&lt;/a&gt; にあります。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Outstanding PyLady Award&lt;/strong&gt;: この賞は、Python コミュニティ内で多様性を促進し、女性や性別少数派を支援する PyLadies コミュニティに重要な貢献をした個人に与えられます。メンタリング、イベントの企画、包括的な環境の育成において卓越した活動を行った人々を称えます。Outstanding PyLady Award の授与は PyLadies グローバルカウンシルによって決定されます。この賞についての詳細は &lt;a href="https://kit.pyladies.com/en/latest/global/award.html"&gt;こちら&lt;/a&gt; をご覧ください。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PSF 功労賞&lt;/strong&gt;: これは財団の最高賞です。PSF 功労賞は、Python コミュニティへの継続的な模範的貢献に対する認識の申し出です。この賞は、コードの貢献、コミュニティ活動への努力、その他の手段を通じて Python の世界を形作る重要な影響を与える行動に対して授与されます。コミュニティサービス賞と同様に、コミュニティへのこのようなサービスが認識と報酬につながることを示すことが意図されており、貢献者に直接的なインセンティブを提供することが目的ではありません。この賞について詳しくは&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/community/awards/psf-distinguished-awards/"&gt;こちら&lt;/a&gt;をご覧ください。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;これらの賞と認識は、世界中の Pythonista の貴重な貢献を強調し、祝う素晴らしい方法です。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PSF ボードディレクターシップ&lt;/strong&gt;: これは賞ではなく責任ですが、ディレクターシップへのノミネートも意味があります。PSF ボードオブディレクターは、財団の活動を監督し、その使命が効果的に実行されるようにします。ボードディレクターは PSF メンバーシップによって選出され、戦略的な意思決定とガバナンスにおいて重要な役割を果たします。詳細は &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/"&gt;PSF ボード選挙ページ&lt;/a&gt; をご覧ください。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;なぜノミネートするべきなの？&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Python Software Foundation (PSF) 内で誰かをノミネートすることは、ただの形式ではありません。これは、Python コミュニティのメンバーがエコシステムに投資した努力と献身を祝福し、認める強力な方法です。個人やグループを認めることは：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ポジティブなコミュニティ精神を促進&lt;/strong&gt;: 貢献を認めることで、感謝とモチベーションの文化を育て、より多くの人々がコミュニティに参加し、貢献することを奨励します。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;多様な貢献を強調&lt;/strong&gt;: 異なる個人の仕事を認めることで、コード、コミュニティの組織化、教育、アドボカシーなど、人々が貢献できるさまざまな方法を示します。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;継続的な関与を奨励&lt;/strong&gt;: コミュニティメンバーに賞を与えることで、彼らの仕事が評価され、注目されていることを知り、努力を続ける動機になります。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;強いネットワークを構築&lt;/strong&gt;: 成果を祝うことで、コミュニティ内のつながりを強化し、メンバー間の協力とサポートを促進します。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;私たちはギフトエコノミーの中で生きています。ギフトが私たちの世界を動かしています。オープンソースはギフトです。オープンソースを支えるために人々が行う無償の労働もギフトです。年齢、性別、経済状況、教育レベルに関係なく、人々を私たちのコミュニティに歓迎することもギフトです。コミュニティの仲間に感謝し、認めることも彼らへの恩返しとなるギフトです。Naomi Ceder は彼女の &lt;a href="https://www.naomiceder.tech/posts/pycon_keynote_2022/"&gt;A Time of Gifts キーノート&lt;/a&gt; でこれを最もよく表現しています。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;しかし、認識プロセスが包括的であり、多様な Python グローバルコミュニティを代表するものであることが重要です。特定のグループは、技術とコミュニティリーダーシップの役割で過小評価されてきました。例えば、私の地域（東アジア、南アジア、東南アジア）のコミュニティは、約 500 人の PSF フェローと約 100 人の CSA 受賞者のうち、18 の PSF フェローシップと 2 人の CSA 受賞者（1 グループを代表する）しかいませんでした。これは全体の約 4% と 2% にすぎません。世界中に約 &lt;a href="https://thefortunate.blog/diversification-is-the-future-for-the-psf.html"&gt;820 万人の Python 開発者またはユーザーがいる&lt;/a&gt; と考えると、私の地域での最大の成長があるとき、それは明らかに過小評価されています。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;どのようにノミネートするの？&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PSF で誰かを認識するためにノミネートするプロセスは簡単です：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;カテゴリーを特定する&lt;/strong&gt;: ノミネートしたい個人やグループに最も適した賞や認識を決定します。これには、PSF フェロー、コミュニティサービス賞、ボードディレクターシップ、または Outstanding PyLady Award が含まれます。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ノミネーションを準備する&lt;/strong&gt;: ノミネートする人の情報を集めます。これには、Python コミュニティへの貢献、具体的な業績、その他関連する詳細が含まれます。ノミネーションは、なぜその人が認識に値するのかを強調するべきです。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ノミネーションを提出する&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PSF フェロー&lt;/strong&gt; のノミネーションはメールで提出できます。詳細は PSF フェローメンバーシップページでご覧ください &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/fellows/"&gt;こちら&lt;/a&gt;。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;コミュニティサービス賞&lt;/strong&gt; の詳細と提出手順は、&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/community/awards/psf-awards/"&gt;PSF コミュニティサービス賞ページ&lt;/a&gt; にあります。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PSF ボードディレクターシップ&lt;/strong&gt; のノミネーションは通常、年次選挙プロセスの一部です。詳細は &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/"&gt;PSF ボード選挙ページ&lt;/a&gt; をご覧ください。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Outstanding PyLady Award&lt;/strong&gt; の詳細は &lt;a href="https://kit.pyladies.com/en/latest/global/award.html"&gt;こちら&lt;/a&gt; で確認できます。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PSF Distinguished Service Award&lt;/strong&gt; の詳細は&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/community/awards/psf-distinguished-awards/"&gt;こちら&lt;/a&gt; から確認できます。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;より良い代表性の必要性&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PSF は、&lt;a href="https://wiki.python.org/psf/DiversityandInclusionWG"&gt;D&amp;amp;I ワークグループ&lt;/a&gt; の設立や、2023 年にアフリカおよびアジアのコミュニティへの助成金の増加など、多様性と包括性の促進に向けた大きな進展を遂げましたが、個人やグループの仕事を認める上で、世界中の異なるコミュニティからのより良い代表性が必要です。多くの地域が PSF のリーダーシップと認識プログラムにおいて過小評価されています。この代表性の欠如は、新しい貢献者の参入障壁を生み出し、コミュニティ内のアイデアと視点の多様性を制限する可能性があります。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;これに対処するために、以下のことを行う必要があります：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;意識の向上&lt;/strong&gt;: 過小評価されているグループの間で、ノミネーションプロセスと認識の機会についての認識を高める。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;サポートの提供&lt;/strong&gt;: 多様な背景を持つ個人がノミネーションプロセスをナビゲートし、コミュニティと関わるのを助けるリソースとサポートを提供する。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;多様なノミネーションを奨励する&lt;/strong&gt;: 過小評価されている地域や背景を持つ個人のノミネーションを積極的に探し、奨励する。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;メンターシッププログラム&lt;/strong&gt;: 多様なコミュニティからの新しい貢献者を支援し、彼らが Python エコシステム内での旅を案内するメンターシッププログラムを確立する。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;これらのステップを踏むことで、PSF が Python コミュニティのグローバルで多様な性質を真に反映し、すべての貢献が評価され認識される包括的な環境を育むことができます。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;何ができるの？&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;たくさんあります！&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;まず、まだ PSF のメンバーでない場合は、&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/membership/"&gt;こちら&lt;/a&gt; からサインアップしましょう。コミュニティのために行った仕事が &lt;a href="https://psfmember.org/civicrm/contribute/transact/?reset=1&amp;amp;id=32"&gt;Managing, Contributing, または Supporting メンバー&lt;/a&gt; に該当する場合は、そのように認識されることを確認してください。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;次に、誰かをノミネートできます！コミュニティに長くいるなら、この記事を読んでいる間に思い浮かぶ人がいるはずです。誰もいない？本当に？例えば、新しい都市やコミュニティに来たときに、何人かの人に新人が関与するのに最適な人は誰かを尋ねてみます。そして、もし 75% の人が同じ名前を挙げるなら、その人はおそらく PSF フェローにふさわしい人物でしょう。その人を知り、彼らが行った仕事について話し始めることができます。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;コミュニティサービス賞（CSA）は理解しやすい基準がありますが、受け入れられるためのハードルは依然として高いです。一例として、私が行った PyCon JP 協会のノミネーションがあります（詳細は &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/records/board/resolutions/"&gt;こちら&lt;/a&gt; と &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/community/awards/psf-awards/#december-2021"&gt;こちら&lt;/a&gt; をご覧ください）。これはパンデミックの影響で財政的に大打撃を受けた PSF のために資金を集めるためのチャリティトークイベントを開催したことに対するものです。もう一つの最近の例は、&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/records/board/minutes/2024-03-13/#new-business"&gt;Leonard Richardson, Lais Cavalho と Raquel Dou が CSA を受け取ったことを認める&lt;/a&gt;もので、彼らが構築し維持してきたソフトウェアやコミュニティが全体としてのコミュニティに利益をもたらしたためです。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;功労賞 (DSA) は、はるかに高いハードルがあります。2012年にはじめて授与されて以来、これまでに7人しか受賞していません。時には CSA のノミネーションが DSA 授与につながることもありますが、それは PSF 理事会の判断に委ねられています。DSA が授与される理由については&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/community/awards/psf-distinguished-awards/"&gt;こちら&lt;/a&gt;をお読みいただき、他の受賞者と肩を並べるにふさわしいと思う方がいれば、ぜひノミネーションを行ってください。ノミネーションは&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/community/awards/psf-distinguished-awards/"&gt;こちら&lt;/a&gt;に記載されているように、PSF 理事会に電子メールでノミネートすることができます。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;もちろん、自己推薦することもできますが、私は個人的にはこれを非常に難しく、非常に退屈だと感じるので、それをすることには興味がありません。他の人について書く方が楽しいです！&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;最後に、これらのノミネーションを通じて、Pythonista の仲間を認識し、評価し、高める機会の認識を高める手助けをすることができます。PyCon や Python ミートアップにいるとき、自己紹介にこれまでに行ったノミネーションの数を含めるようにしています。例えば：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;こんにちは、私は Iqbal です。ここで時々手伝っています。これまでに xxx 人を PSF フェローに、xxx 人を CSA にノミネートしました。それについてもっと知りたいですか？&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;そして、時々話している人が私がノミネートした人を知っていて、素晴らしい会話が生まれます。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;誰かを認識するべきだと思っているけれど、まだ方法がわからない場合は、&lt;a href="https://mtd.pythonasia.org/@iqbalabd"&gt;Mastodon&lt;/a&gt;、&lt;a href="https://x.com/iqbalabd"&gt;X&lt;/a&gt; または &lt;a href="linkedin.com/in/iqbalabd/"&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt; を通じて私にメッセージを送っていただければ、できる限りお手伝いします。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;FAQ&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PSF ノミネーションについてのオープンスペースでの質問は以下の通りです：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;自己推薦できますか？&lt;/strong&gt; - はい&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;コミュニティサービス賞（CSA）と PSF フェローの違いは何ですか？&lt;/strong&gt; - CSA が何のためのものかについての公式説明は &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/community/awards/psf-awards/"&gt;こちら&lt;/a&gt; を、PSF フェローについては &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/fellows/"&gt;こちら&lt;/a&gt; をご覧ください。簡単に言えば、CSA は特定の奉仕行為を祝うものであり、PSF フェローメンバーシップは Python エコシステムとコミュニティへの包括的で顕著な貢献を認識するものです。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PSF フェローに誰かをノミネートするための要件は何ですか？&lt;/strong&gt; - 明確な要件はありませんが、通常のオーガナイザーや貢献者を超えた貢献が必要です。良い例は、PSF フェローノミネーションのために公開されているノミネーション文自体であり、&lt;a href="https://wiki.python.org/moin/PythonSoftwareFoundation/FellowNominations"&gt;こちら&lt;/a&gt; に掲載されています。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;これらのノミネーションはどのように決定されますか？&lt;/strong&gt; - 誰でも誰かをノミネートできますが、ノミネーションは PSF 内の異なるグループによって審議され、受け入れられるか拒否されます。PSF フェローノミネーションは &lt;a href="https://wiki.python.org/psf/FellowWG/Charter"&gt;PSF フェローワークグループ&lt;/a&gt; によって決定され、CSA は &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/board/"&gt;PSF ボード&lt;/a&gt; によって、そして Outstanding PyLady Award は &lt;a href="https://pyladies.com/blog/Announcing-the-Inaugural-PyLadies-Global-Council/inaugural-pyladies-council/"&gt;PyLadies Global Council&lt;/a&gt; によって決定されます。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;この投稿をレビューしてくれた &lt;a href="https://x.com/cheukting_ho"&gt;Cheuk&lt;/a&gt; に感謝します&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2024"></category><category term="pycon"></category><category term="psf"></category><category term="コミュニティ"></category></entry><entry><title>Going To PyCon US 2024 - Heading To Pittsburgh (Part 1)</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/posts/2024/05/going-to-pycon-us-2024-in-pittsburgh-part-1/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-05-09T22:20:00+09:00</published><updated>2024-05-27T11:50:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabdullah.net,2024-05-09:/posts/2024/05/going-to-pycon-us-2024-in-pittsburgh-part-1/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The first part of my journey across the world in May/June 2024.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;First Stop: PyCon US 2024 via New York&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were two events which I needed to attend in May this year:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://us.pycon.org/2024/"&gt;PyCon US 2024 in Pittsburgh&lt;/a&gt; (From May 15th to May 19th)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://latitude59.ee"&gt;Latitude59 in Tallinn&lt;/a&gt; (From May 22nd to May 24th)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem with this is that both events are only a few days apart from each other, but at totally different places on the planet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Booking Travel and Accommodations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Flights&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of these two places that I needed to go, I decided to take the &lt;a href="https://roundtheworld.staralliance.com/staralliance/EN/round-the-world"&gt;Round The World ticket from Star Alliance&lt;/a&gt; (also known as RTW) because I am an ANA member. It's actually much better deal to take the RTW ticket compared to a multi-city ticket, unless you want to go down the route of building your own flight plan through low-cost airlines. Even then, if you travel often, you might lose out on the Miles benefits if you take the multi-low-cost airlines route.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tip: The RTW ticket allows you to change your flights (add, remove or change), but try not to do that. They will charge you USD 150 every person for each time&lt;/em&gt;. If you have to change though, it's pretty easy: Just send them an email and they will figure it out for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Hotels&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Afiza handles our accommodations when we travel. She has a membership with the Marriott group hotels and her membership level gives her useful perks when we stay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I can say is that prices of accommodation have at least doubled since a year ago, while the quality hasn't changed much and depends very much on the establishment you stay at.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Packing for the Trip&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been doing multi-month travels over multiple cities, countries, timezones, and climates since 2013. Over the years, the amount that I pack has gone way down. When I started out, I called it "&lt;em&gt;Defensive Packing&lt;/em&gt;" where you get as many things as possible to handle all possibilities when you're traveling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I have transitioned to "&lt;em&gt;Aggressive Packing&lt;/em&gt;" where you get only essentials for your comfort and try to get anything else that you'd need along the way. When you're away from home for months in different cities and countries the "what ifs" pile up. 
It takes years to get to know yourself and the people you travel with to get this part right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your mileage may vary, but here's what I've got:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Essentials: Clothes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I travel, the maximum amount of clothes I bring is six nights. This requires that I go to a laundry at least every five days. Hotel laundries are &lt;strong&gt;expensive&lt;/strong&gt; (unless you're in a particular hotel in Istanbul, maybe I'll write about that one day). &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At least two pairs of shoes: One for running, and another is a pair of Dr. Martens boots. Sneakers are too painful for my feet when I walk on European cobblestones. Black boots are also useful when I need to go to a posh restaurant or business meeting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uniqlo light down. Alongside a hoodie, this combination can get me through tempreatures of as low as 14C.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A nice dinner jacket that can be rolled up and doesn't crease.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Essentials: Travel Goods&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Portable bidet. Living in Japan and around South East Asia, we take our toilet time seriously.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Portable water pot to boil water. I have a habit of not drinking cold drinks. US hotels also don't have water pots for you to boil water. Because our world mostly works on two different voltages, certain trips require me to bring two types of water boilers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Essentials: Medication and Toiletries&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't forget your medication and prescriptions. I have been so far blessed with good health, so I usually only pack painkillers, stuff like skin cream for itches, bandages, and band-aids which will come in handy if you get blisters. Anything beyond this, I usually will go to the local clinic or hospital. Exercising while travelling is an important part of my routine and is part of my effort to keep things this way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I strongly suggest you obtain travel insurance&lt;/strong&gt;. Due to travel stress or being overzealous at experiencing the local delicacies, I have had the pleasure of experiencing the local medical facilities in Bangalore, Istanbul, Madrid, Marrakech, Kuala Lumpur, and Barcelona in the past. They cost money, and some facilities actually require proof of travel insurance from you before accepting you. You'll need to pay upfront, but with travel insurance, you can claim those expenses back when you get home. &lt;strong&gt;Remember to keep your receipts!&lt;/strong&gt;
If you have a credit card, chances are there's already travel insurance that comes with your contract. Mine do, and I print out the local phone numbers of the concierge that can help us if we need assistance while traveling. I've actually called them twice in my past travels to get help on which hospital to visit when I was sick, and they were really helpful.
Beware of CBD products: Now in Japan, CBD products are getting widespread, and some people find them useful. However, remember not to bring them on your trip because not all countries are acceptable with CBD. It could get you into a lot of trouble at customs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Essentials: Work Items&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're like me, you'll still be working while traveling. The work items that I bring with me are the things that I use daily when I'm at home, so I appreciate it that they also give me a reminder of home when I travel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Laptop (Dell XPS-13) and 65W Ravpower charger&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Two cables that can handle PD and USB-C/USB-A ports&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A dongle that plugs into my laptop's USB-C and gets me connected on HDMI if I need to do presentations, and also Ethernet when it's available&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Moleskin notebook and my Lamy pen. Writing things down on a piece of paper is still one of the most effective ways for me to gather my thoughts. It's also an effective way to pass someone information. I also love my Lamy pen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kindle&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.glocalme.com/product/numen-air/"&gt;Numen Air 5G router&lt;/a&gt; which works as a backup. The cheapest way to get data plans is usually through a local SIM. If you travel to many countries, though, buying local SIMs for each country might be costly. In this case, I usually use &lt;a href="https://www.celcomdigi.com/roaming"&gt;Celcom's Multi Country Pass&lt;/a&gt; where you pay a flat MYR98 fee for a whole month and gets you 2GB per day on 70 over countries.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Others&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Others stuff that I bring along for pleasure:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A few packets of one-cup drip coffee (or pour-over as they are known in the US). I like the coffee from the usual place that I buy when I'm home. They remind me of home and I also get to save some money by drinking coffee instead.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Skipping rope. This is a form of exercise I picked up a few years ago. A half-hour skipping rope session can give me a decent workout. The ropes don't take up much space, and I only need a small area to do my workout. I bought the ropes from &lt;a href="https://www.crossrope.com"&gt;Crossrope&lt;/a&gt;. I have a whole set of four types of rope of different weights, but when I travel I only bring the 1/4 and 1/2 pound ropes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Packing It All Up&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Packing is done over a period of around a week. I'll gather everything piece by piece into one place based on a list, and get them all into the suitcases while also taking into account the clothes I need to still wear at home before leaving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I started traveling, I used to stuff everything into those big backpacks that backpackers use, but it turns out I can fit more, get my stuff organized better &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; get my luggage weight down by using those &lt;a href="https://shop.samsonite.com/collections/lightweight/?prefn1=collection&amp;amp;prefv1=Cosmolite%203.0&amp;amp;srules=category-position"&gt;Samsonite Cosmolite&lt;/a&gt; suitcases. They're spacious, lightweight, and durable. For longer than a week's travel, I usually have two with me: the 125L and the carry-on smaller type. If we're taking connecting flights, I will have 2- days' worth of basic clothing and toiletries in my carry-on and everything else in the bigger bag. This is to take into account my checked-in bag gets lost in transit, which did happened to me once when I went to Munich many years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been using the Samsonites for nearly 10 years now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;And We're Set&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After all that, everything gets packed into one large and one small suitcase and my backpack. You can see how my luggage
looks like below. We're now ready to go!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="A picture of my luggage for one month" src="https://iqbalabdullah.net/images/one-month-luggage.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2024"></category><category term="pycon"></category><category term="pittsburgh"></category><category term="may-2024-trip"></category><category term="travel"></category></entry><entry><title>Weblog Update (Finally!)</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/posts/2024/05/weblog-latest-update-2024/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-05-01T13:22:00+09:00</published><updated>2024-05-01T13:22:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabdullah.net,2024-05-01:/posts/2024/05/weblog-latest-update-2024/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Updating this weblog for 2024 and my 5-year diary&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Weblog Update&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I finally sat down and got to updating this weblog. I write a lot, but most of my writing is work-related and will go to
their respective blogs such as &lt;a href="https://kafkai.com/en/blog/"&gt;Kafkai blog&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://otp.dev/en/blog/"&gt;GetOTP blog&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://lalokalabs.co/en/blog/"&gt;LaLoka Labs's blog&lt;/a&gt;
and after all of that there wasn't enough time for me to write things which are more personal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Started by a 5-Year Diary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="My 5-year diary" src="https://iqbalabdullah.net/images/5-year-diary.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Afiza gave me a "5-year diary" present for my 47th birthday. She enjoyed writing things on it and nearly finished her current diary.
She was recommended to it by a friend, and now she has also recommended it to me. I've started spending two or three minutes at the end of my
day every day to write random things that happened that day in it, and realized the urge to write longer thoughts without thinking about work too much.
That brought me around to updating this personal weblog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Some Fixes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, no point in updating something without fixing things along the way, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Categories&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I realized after all the time I've spent writing that my posts needed to be categorized in a particular way was actually restricting my writing.
I have always been a person who thinks from top to bottom. Categories help if I'm writing for work because we usually have an outcome we want to
achieve and it gives me structure, but when it comes to personal writing, this gets in the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I've decided to just file all my posts under the year they were written and use &lt;a href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/tags.html"&gt;tags&lt;/a&gt; instead as a loose form
of categorization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Non-Translatable Categories in Pelican&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another thing is that sometimes I translate my posts to different languages and I'm using Pelican for this weblog. Pelican does a great job at publishing the
different languages through the &lt;a href="https://qiita.com/agektrombala/items/bc0da1f2bdf9e1f35aeb"&gt;i8n_subsites plugin&lt;/a&gt;, but I haven't found a way to have the categories
(which are decided when you create directories) in Pelican translated. So, just having them as years doesn't require translation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;New Domain&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And finally, this weblog has a new domain. Just like the weblogs of people I read frequently, such as &lt;a href="https://ziade.org/"&gt;Tarek Ziade&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href="https://simonwillison.net/"&gt;Simon Willison&lt;/a&gt;, it just makes more sense to me to have a domain that reflects myself on the internet.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2024"></category><category term="daily stuff"></category><category term="writing"></category><category term="blogging"></category></entry><entry><title>ウェブログの更新 (ついに!)</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/ja/posts/2024/05/weblog-latest-update-2024/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-05-01T13:22:00+09:00</published><updated>2024-05-01T13:22:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabdullah.net,2024-05-01:/ja/posts/2024/05/weblog-latest-update-2024/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;2024年のウェブログの更新と5年日記&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;ウェブログの更新&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ついにこのウェブログの更新に取り組みました。私は多くを書きますが、ほとんどは仕事関連で、&lt;a href="https://kafkai.com/ja/blog/"&gt;Kafkaiブログ&lt;/a&gt;、&lt;a href="https://otp.dev/ja/blog/"&gt;GetOTPブログ&lt;/a&gt;、&lt;a href="https://lalokalabs.co/ja/blog/"&gt;LaLoka Labs's ブログ&lt;/a&gt;などの各個別ブログにアップしています。
そのすべてを終えた後は、より個人的なことを書く時間がもうなくなった。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;5年日記から始まった&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="俺の5年連用日記" src="https://iqbalabdullah.net/images/5-year-diary.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;アフィザは私の47歳の誕生日プレゼントとして「5年日記」をくれました。彼女は日記に書くことを楽しんでおり、現在の1冊目の日記をほぼ完成させています。
友人に勧められたそうで、今では私にもおすすめしてくれました。毎日の終わりに2、3分費やして、その日に起こったランダムなことを書き始めたところ、仕事のことを考えずに、もっと長い考えを書きたくなりました。
それがこの個人ウェブログを更新するきっかけになりました。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;修正点&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;更新するなら、途中で修正点もチェックしておくべきですよね。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;カテゴリ&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;これまで多くを書いてきて気づいたのは、投稿をある特定の方法でカテゴライズする必要があったことが、実は私の書く自由を制限していたということです。私は上から下に考える人間なんだから、
仕事で書く場合はカテゴリがあると役立ちますね。目標とするアウトカムがあり、構造を与えてくれます。でも個人的な書き物の場合は、かえって邪魔になるのです。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;そこで、投稿はすべて書いた年でファイルし、緩やかな分類法として&lt;a href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/tags.html"&gt;タグ&lt;/a&gt;を使うことにしました。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Pelicanでの非翻訳カテゴリ&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;もう一つ、投稿を別の言語に翻訳することもあって、このウェブログにはPelicanを使っています。Pelicanは&lt;a href="https://qiita.com/agektrombala/items/bc0da1f2bdf9e1f35aeb"&gt;i8n_subsites plugin&lt;/a&gt;を使って、
さまざまな言語で確実に公開してくれますが、カテゴリ(ディレクトリを作成するときに決まるもの)を翻訳する方法は見つかりませんでした。だから、年ごとにするだけなら翻訳の必要がありません。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;新ドメイン&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;そして最後に、このウェブログには新しいドメインが付きました。私の良く読むブログの人たち、例えば&lt;a href="https://ziade.org/"&gt;Tarek Ziade&lt;/a&gt;や&lt;a href="https://simonwillison.net/"&gt;Simon Willison&lt;/a&gt;のように、
インターネット上の自分を反映するドメインを持つのが私にはより合理的だと思います。&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2024"></category><category term="日常の出来事"></category><category term="執筆"></category><category term="ブログ"></category></entry><entry><title>A step closer to the Future for the Python Software Foundation (PSF)</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/posts/2023/07/a-step-closer-to-the-future-for-the-psf-2023/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-07-06T07:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2023-07-06T09:54:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabdullah.net,2023-07-06:/posts/2023/07/a-step-closer-to-the-future-for-the-psf-2023/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The 2023 PSF Board elections are closed and counted. I supported candidates in the elections, and based on the voting results I wrote my thoughts on the future of the PSF.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;A step closer to the future for the PSF&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;It's the time of the year again!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Four members of the board retire in 2023, paving the way for another election, which represents an opportunity for us to have a more diverse representation on the board level of the PSF.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since &lt;a href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/posts/2020/06/diversification-is-the-future-for-the-psf/"&gt;participating in the elections in 2020&lt;/a&gt;, interest has been growing within the community in which I am involved, particularly the APAC or Asia region, when we talk about diversification of ideas and people within the PSF specifically and the community in general.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2020, I was the only person from within the APAC region to run for election. Now in 2023, we have as many as six people, representing their communities in JP, KR, TH, IN, and BD raising their hands and wanting to be counted and running for a seat on the Board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I knew before the election that at least &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/2023-python-software-foundation-board/nominees/"&gt;3 members of my community&lt;/a&gt; would be running for a seat on the board, and wasn't thinking of running. Unknown to me, Jannis nominated me, and that got me thinking that it would be a good platform to help the campaigns of my fellow compatriots from my region to run, so I decided to accept the nomination and use whatever exposure I get to campaign for them instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am personally happy that all the three candidates that I supported in my own &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/2023-python-software-foundation-board/nominees/iqbal-abdullah/"&gt;nomination statement&lt;/a&gt; got elected to the Board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Managing a worldwide non-profit requires a diverse set of skills and not only technical competency. We now have a much-needed diverse group of people within the PSF Board, not only within the region they are associated with but also the skillset they bring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Voter count&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is one thing of concern though: The voter count and voter turnout&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In 2020, &lt;a href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/posts/2020/06/diversification-is-the-future-for-the-psf/"&gt;1151 people were eligible to vote, with a voter turnout of 40%&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In 2021, &lt;a href="https://discuss.python.org/t/2021-python-software-foundation-board-of-directors-election-results/9418"&gt;1538 people were eligible to vote (34% increase YoY) with a voter turnout of 38%&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In 2022, we had &lt;a href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/posts/2022/07/the-future-is-still-not-here-for-the-psf-2022/"&gt;1459 people eligible to vote (5% decrease YoY) with a voter turnout of 39%&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For the 2023 elections, &lt;a href="https://pyfound.blogspot.com/2023/06/announcing-2023-psf-board-election.html"&gt;affirmed members who are eligible to vote was 877 (40% decrease YoY) with a voter turnout of 70%&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless of the efforts we're putting in, at least from within my community and also from within the &lt;a href="https://wiki.python.org/psf/DiversityandInclusionWG"&gt;D&amp;amp;I Workgroup&lt;/a&gt; which I am part of, we can't seem to get a steadily increasing voter count year-over-year. Although we can never know &lt;em&gt;who&lt;/em&gt; voted, taking into account that our voter turnout jumped to 70% when the vote count was its lowest in 2023 points out the possibility that the voters that vote in the yearly elections are a fixed group of people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I wrote in 2020, increasing the voter count by encouraging participation from much more diverse Python communities is still very much a work in progress, and, is taking a step backward if we look at the 40% decrease year over year in 2023.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The summary above is flawed. Read on in the Updates section below&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A small win though: As I wrote above, the amount of participation in the number of candidates related to my APAC region has increased.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still think that we need much more participation from community members that reside in non-West Europe and North American regions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Special thanks go to Jay Miller for contributing to the election process by caring and &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PL9MuO5r3rpXJ5k-NEI3Gc6S3CZU7mGwvP"&gt;creating videos&lt;/a&gt; for the candidate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;So what's next?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For 2023, and within the context of diversity and inclusion from within my region, we're seeing a step forward; we still have much work to do:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Increasing the voter base and participation in the elections&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Better distribution of grants, Fellow memberships and awards (i.e. &lt;a href="https://lalokalabs.co/en/2023/04/attending-pycon-us-2023/"&gt;only 2% of grants go to the Euroasia/Asia continent&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we have a more diverse group of people now in the Board: The Board now needs to deliver by coming back to the community and showing results such as a better distribution of grants, Fellow memberships, and also awards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They, of course, can only do this if there are requests, nominations, and commendations from the community itself, but they can help that by being present within these underrepresented communities and making sure that they are aware of all of these ways to acknowledge the wonderful work done by our diverse communities. Now with a more diverse Board that has stronger connections with these different communities, there is one less reason to not be able to find ways of doing so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, I do realize that the Board alone can't do all of these: A group of 10 or 12 people can't represent a community of 8 million worldwide. That said, the PSF Board has Workgroups at their disposal. There should be more listening and consultation with the community through these Workgroups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Workgroups have practical knowledge and connections to the different communities that they are in, and along with the Board of the PSF and &lt;em&gt;in tandem with other Workgroups&lt;/em&gt;, they should work together to address the two items above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're reading this and thinking, "I want to help", go on over to the list of &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/workgroups/"&gt;active Workgroups that the PSF has&lt;/a&gt; and find a WG that interests you most.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it is though, I am excited to see the new Board for this year and wish them all the best. Hopefully, we'll get to meet again at the next PyCon somewhere. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Updates 2023-07-06&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After putting out the above post, I received &lt;a href="https://discuss.python.org/t/psf-board-election-dates-for-2023/26699/29/"&gt;a comment from C.A.M Gerlach&lt;/a&gt; about how I'm misinterpreting the numbers of the election results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main point is that starting from the 2023 elections, &lt;a href="https://discuss.python.org/t/important-affirm-your-psf-membership-voting-status/27502/"&gt;how "eligible voter" is counted has changed&lt;/a&gt;. This is because the PSF needs to protect its quorum to satisfy its bylaws. In the past, this was not enforced due to technical reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before 2023, I have personally taken the number of eligible voters as a proxy to gauge participation in the community, through registrations as Fellows, Managing, Supporting and Contributing Members. This is the most important number, at least for me regardless of actual participation in the election itself. Because how we count the number of "eligible voters" has changed, using this number as the proxy for participation is no longer valid. The decrease in 40% YoY vs. 2022 of people voting, as it is, doesn't mean anything as we're not comparing to the same thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is also good news. C.A.M Gerlach also pointed out data which I did not look at: The cumulative increase in the absolute number of people voting. &lt;strong&gt;It has increased 33% from 460 in 2020 to 614 in 2023.&lt;/strong&gt; . We are getting more people involved, at least where the election is concerned, and voting for a more diverse group of people, at least from what we see in the 2023 elections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would like to believe that, the work done by me and my compatriots in the D&amp;amp;I WG as also those from within my APAC/Asia community contributed in part to this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm leaving the original article I wrote above as it is so that it will be beneficial in the future if I need to do a &lt;em&gt;diff&lt;/em&gt; on what and why I wrote and thought about something.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2023"></category><category term="psf"></category><category term="politics"></category><category term="community work"></category><category term="elections"></category><category term="python community"></category></entry><entry><title>The future is still not here for the Python Software Foundation (PSF)</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/posts/2022/07/the-future-is-still-not-here-for-the-psf-2022/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-07-02T10:30:00+09:00</published><updated>2022-07-02T16:42:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabdullah.net,2022-07-02:/posts/2022/07/the-future-is-still-not-here-for-the-psf-2022/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The 2022 PSF Board elections are closed and counted. I failed to make the cut, and so wrote my thoughts down in this post.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;The future is still not here for the Python Software Foundation (PSF)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In June 2022, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/iqbalabd/status/1535270196654575616?src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;I ran for the third time&lt;/a&gt; for a seat in the Python Software Foundation (PSF) Board of directors. Initially I wasn't thinking of running, but Dustin Ingram of PyPi encouraged me to run again at the last minute and so I did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;It didn't quite work out...&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, a big congratulations to the newly elected and returning Board members! They are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DawnWagesSays"&gt;@DawnWagesSays&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/simonw"&gt;@simonw&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/kushaldas"&gt;@kushaldas&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/jezdez"&gt;@jezdez&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I was also not elected again this time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the &lt;a href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/posts/2022/06/psf-board-2022-nomination-statement/"&gt;agenda and vision that I put forth for the 2022 elections&lt;/a&gt; remain the same as those in the 2020 and &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/2021-python-software-foundation-board/nominees/iqbal-abdullah/"&gt;2021&lt;/a&gt; elections, out of a total of 4115 votes given to all nominees, I only had 250, which is 6.08%. This was less than the 7.34% I had in the 2021 elections. As a note, I managed to get only 4.78% votes in the 2020 elections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also had 5% fewer people who were eligible to vote, down to 1459 from 1538 in the 2021 elections. Those who &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; voted, however, basically remained the same, at around 39% voter turnout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But for me, the most worrying thing is that with Marlene exiting the Board, we are now &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/CodenameTim/status/1542895106918961154?S=20&amp;amp;T=KkwPKOrVlpC2fPUy26v8_g"&gt;down to only two non-US/Europe directors on the Board&lt;/a&gt; out of 13. This doesn't look well if we want to talk about global representation and diversity. This condition slowly pushes us towards a defensive narrative if questioned on our diversity and inclusion efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;But other things &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; go well...&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, other things did go well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I announced my self-nomination for the Board, I also sent an &lt;a href="https://groups.google.com/g/pycon-organizers-apac/c/3J9rLJT8LAo"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt; to our APAC PyCon Organizers group, urging others to run alongside me. This time, I had another two influential contributors from my East Asia and South East Asia region, Georgi and Kwon Han, to run with me. We didn't have nominees from our region in the past other than myself, and I believe that my work in promoting diversity, representation, and involvement within the APAC community and the PSF has increased visibility, interest, and inspired others to also run for the Board elections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of particular note which I am proud to mention is the election results for Georgi. Although she was not elected, she did manage to get 6.29% of the total votes and was just shy of 14 votes to be elected in her first election to the Board.
Interest to serve the community through a seat on the Board continues to be strong. We had a record number of 26 nominees, similar to what we had in 2020. This is more than the 19 nominations we saw in 2021.
I am also really happy to see that &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/cmaureir/status/1542877794778087430?lang=en"&gt;Cristián&lt;/a&gt; continues to run advocating representation for Latin America, our Spanish-speaking compatriots and i18n efforts for the PSF.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There seem to be more nominees who have openly championed diversity in representation within the PSF Board of directors and less reliance on PyCon US for financing, more than we have seen in the past.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;To sum up&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be honest, I did not expect to get elected this time because nothing much has significantly changed since the last two elections, either on my end or through any initiatives by the PSF or the community to address the perceived lack of global representation on the PSF Board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be fair though: At least since 2020 more people have pointed out the problem of a skewed representation within the Board. Some say it's the way the elections are done, and there are &lt;a href="https://discuss.python.org/t/psf-board-election-reform/4527"&gt;suggestions on changing the way voting is done&lt;/a&gt; for the elections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the 2020 elections, the PSF has also put out a short and medium-term &lt;a href="https://pyfound.blogspot.com/2020/06/2020-python-software-foundation-board_26.html"&gt;plan&lt;/a&gt; to address this issue, which includes collecting location data on the voters themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a nominee for the past three elections, having data on who our voters are is important. Without it, I do not know who I am talking to and what is important to them. Even if the &lt;a href="https://www.zdnet.com/article/programming-languages-python-developers-now-outnumber-java-ones/"&gt;8 million or so Python users&lt;/a&gt; think any one person should be on the Board, if that person could not convince the 500 or so people who will be voting, then there's very slim chance of getting elected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our work within the D&amp;amp;I WG also has led us to data collection to understand better who our community members are, although I suspect not many of them are voters (yet). From preliminary data, general apathy towards the work the PSF does and the elections in general seems to be the biggest hurdle we need to overcome to get more of our non-US/Europe community members to participate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it is, I can also honestly say that taking part, being active and visible to the US Python community specifically seems to be a prerequisite to be successful in getting elected to the PSF Board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Not only as Board member&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what happens to you, the avid Python user/developer/organizer who is burning with the desire to help your fellow community members, but so happens to be having a life in an area that &lt;em&gt;is not&lt;/em&gt; the 10% of the world's landmass that is the United States or Europe?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many other ways for us to contribute and make an impact. Some good suggestions are listed &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/get-involved/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; on the PSF's website. If you're interested in a very specific cause, there are the &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/committees/"&gt;PSF Working Groups&lt;/a&gt; (also known as committees) that you can ask to join and participate in. I am currently participating in the Trademark WG and the D&amp;amp;I WG, which has given me knowledge from diversity policies, trademark law, other Python communities in the world, and opportunities to learn from those more experienced and knowledgeable than myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But from experience, I think &lt;strong&gt;the best way to make an impact is to join or start something within your own local area&lt;/strong&gt;. We never have enough people to organize meet-ups, start a local conference, do weekend hackathons, guide newcomers to the community, or write and maintain software for the use of the local community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Credits go to&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, &lt;strong&gt;big thank-yous&lt;/strong&gt; to (in no particular order)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;James&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dustin&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;David&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Marc-André&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Georgi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kwon Han&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thomas&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wei Lee&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yuggun&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Aiko&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kamal&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the D&amp;amp;I WG&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PyCon JP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the kind folks on Twitter and LinkedIn who liked and shared my content&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the folks who voted for me&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and the PyCon APAC Organizers group&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;for supporting my nomination and sharing my vision. I am only human, and forgive me if I missed anyone in the credits roll above. I'm sorry to have disappointed all of you due to my own inadequacies. But we are only human, and maybe we can try again in the future.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2022"></category><category term="psf"></category><category term="politics"></category><category term="community work"></category><category term="elections"></category><category term="python community"></category></entry><entry><title>A guide to the PSF board elections 2022: How should you decide?</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/posts/2022/06/guide-for-the-psf-board-elections-2022-how-to-decide/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-06-22T22:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2022-06-22T22:00:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabdullah.net,2022-06-22:/posts/2022/06/guide-for-the-psf-board-elections-2022-how-to-decide/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A record number of people have raised their hands to serve on the PSF board this year. How do you choose? Who do you choose?&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Choosing the nominees for the PSF board elections 2022&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;First of all, a disclaimer: I am also &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/2022-python-software-foundation-board/nominees/iqbal-abdullah/"&gt;running for a seat&lt;/a&gt; this year.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're seeing a &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/2022-python-software-foundation-board/nominees/"&gt;record number of nominees&lt;/a&gt; raising their hands to serve on the board of the Python Software Foundation (PSF) this year. This is a very good thing for the Foundation and our community, but it might be daunting for you who will be choosing the people you want to see in the board. I believe that most of the eligible voters have voted a few times, but there are some of us who will be voting the first time. Regardless, I hope this post will give you a hint on how to decide which nominees you should choose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;First, it's about you&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, first and foremost, it's about &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt;. How do &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; see the PSF? What future would &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; like the PSF and the Python community to have? What do &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; think?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having some time to sit down and think of what I wanted to see for the PSF, I have decided to focus on these three, which are loosely based on
my &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/2022-python-software-foundation-board/nominees/iqbal-abdullah/"&gt;nomination statement&lt;/a&gt; and my
&lt;a href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/posts/2020/06/diversification-is-the-future-for-the-psf/"&gt;thoughts on the previous election&lt;/a&gt; which I took part in:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Opportunities&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe this is what we can never have enough of. We need more opportunities for the different types of people in our community to participate in the many different things, from technical stuff to community building, that we have and revolves around the Python language. Having a chance to get through the door is the first step to grow and later on open more doors for the people after one selves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Diversity&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Python community is colourful. It's not only painted in the colours of black or white, the Americas or West Europe, or technical and PEPs. Does our board, that represents us through the PSF truly represent us? Do we have the diversity in the people, diversity in the skills, diversity in the thoughts and ideas that will make us stronger and go further?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Experience&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, &lt;a href="https://wiki.python.org/moin/PythonSoftwareFoundation/DutiesAndResponsibilitiesOfDirectors"&gt;the PSF board has many duties and responsibilities&lt;/a&gt;. I would want people who are capable and understand what it takes to work together in an organization to represent us and help our community and our language to evolve and grow. This requires experience. Having said that, having the same group of people to continuously represent us does not help to create opportunities nor a diverse representation, so how do we balance the above two with experience? For me, this is a fine line that is the most difficult part to decide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;There are of course others...&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are of course other valid points that we can think of. Perhaps you would like to see a PSF that has bigger financial resources and can help more communities. Or a PSF that puts more effort in solving packaging issues for Python. Or a PSF that for once and for all solve the issue of a "slow" Python. Or even a PSF that has ambitions to send a rocket to Mars because that's where you believe the future of mankind is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless of what they are, having an idea of what you'd think is important to &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; will be the first step.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Then, it's about the nominees&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, we move on to the nominees. These are the people that will work with you to achieve the important things you have decided above. So what do we look for in these nominees?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, for starters we have their nomination statements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way I do it, I will assign some amount of points to each nominee depending on the four items I focus below. There is a maximum amount of points that each item can have, depending on how important a particular item is. The maximum number of points that a nominee can have is 10. At the end of it, I will choose any nominee with 6 or more points to the board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can always tweak the points system to your taste. You might want more points for a particular item that is close to your heart, and less for those which you think are less important to you. You might want to lower the bar by choosing anyone that has more than 4 points, or raise the bar to anyone that has more than 8 points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are the four items I focus on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Who are they&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will of course be the first thing that I will read. Who are they? What's their name? Have you heard of them before? What community are they from? What's their background? Nearly all nominees will do a good job explaining this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Maximum 1 point)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What do they want to achieve&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where you can see if a particular nominee is trying to push agendas which are similar or close to those that you think are important above. Why are they running? What are they trying to change? What are they trying to improve? Who are they representing?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Maximum 3 points)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Their progression&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A nominee's progression represents their history in working towards a particular point in time. What have they been doing up until this point? Were they committing code to GitHub as a core dev? Were they presenting quality ideas to the community? Were they fund raising to help other communities to do their work?  Were they organizing people for PyCon's?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember that serving on the PSF board is not the only way to have impact on the community or the language. Maintaining a library is one way to do it. We already have the &lt;a href="https://peps.python.org/pep-0013/"&gt;steering council&lt;/a&gt; that will have a more direct impact on how the language evolves. &lt;a href="http://kit.pyladies.com/en/latest/prospective/index.html"&gt;Organizing your local PyLadies&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://organize.djangogirls.org/"&gt;DjangoGirls&lt;/a&gt; chapter will have more impact in opening doors to underrepresented people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also the many &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/committees/"&gt;PSF Workgroups&lt;/a&gt; with various objectives that you can participate in, having a more direct way to have an impact and help shape the future of Python.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, I put progression higher than their reason to run. In my line of work, we have this saying: "What matters is not what the customers are saying; It's what they are doing". More importantly though, it always makes me happy to see the many achievements my fellow compatriots have achieved, and helps me want to do more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Maximum 4 points)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What other people have to say about them&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we have the section where someone else will have a good word or two for the nominee. Acknowledgement of work and character by a different person is always a positive thing. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If that acknowledgement is done by someone you know, respect and trust, then perhaps this is a nominee which you would want to pay attention to. More often than not, it usually means that the nominee holds values that you too consider important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Maximum 2 points)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;What if there are no nominees that champion what you think is important?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then it's time for you to be a nominee yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Finally, it's about the process&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But above all, enjoy the process of having to choose between many different capable people within our community to represent us in the board.
The way the voting process works, you can choose multiple people to the board. The nominees that gets the top votes will be elected to the board equal
to the amount of vacant seats for that particular year. As the voter, you have multiple choices to support different agendas and nominees and it's not a "this-or-that" choice. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, it's a free democratic process, and like any other free democratic process, you are free to choose whomever you like.
You never have to justify your choices to anyone else other than yourself, and you are not obliged to answer who you choose even if asked.
Your vote is secret, and only known to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So before we part ways, I hope you don't think too hard, enjoy the process and enjoy the opportunity to take part. The above thoughts on how to choose a
nominee are only mine, and you should have yours too. Choose whoever you feel like choosing. There will always be next year for you to vote again, and I am
confident that there will be continued interest to help out with the PSF board in the many more years to come, and many more nominees to choose from. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, this is what matters most.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2022"></category><category term="psf"></category><category term="politics"></category><category term="community work"></category><category term="elections"></category><category term="python community"></category></entry><entry><title>Nomination statement for the 2022 Python Software Foundation Board Election</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/posts/2022/06/psf-board-2022-nomination-statement/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-06-10T22:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2022-06-10T22:00:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabdullah.net,2022-06-10:/posts/2022/06/psf-board-2022-nomination-statement/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;My self-nomination statement for the 2022 Python Software Foundation (PSF) Board Election&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Who&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My name is &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/iqbalabd"&gt;Iqbal Abdullah&lt;/a&gt;. I am a Malaysian, based in Japan and have been actively participating with the Python communities around the East Asia and South East Asia region.
I understand fluently three natural languages and am proficient in one. I am a Supporting and Managing Member of the PSF.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I make a living by running a small technology company called &lt;a href="https://lalokalabs.co/en/"&gt;LaLoka Labs&lt;/a&gt; which I am also happy to mention uses &lt;strong&gt;a significant amount&lt;/strong&gt; of Python.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I first ran for a seat on the PSF board in &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/2020-python-software-foundation-board/nominees/iqbal-abdullah/"&gt;2020&lt;/a&gt;.
I received 11th place out of 26 nominees with 4.78% of the votes. Looking at the results, I realized how little representation the PSF has from different communities in other parts of
the world beyond the United States and Western Europe, even though a significant portion of community work and possible opportunities for technical expertise would come from these communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote an essay about this in my blog titled &lt;a href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/posts/2020/06/diversification-is-the-future-for-the-psf/"&gt;Diversification is the Future for the PSF&lt;/a&gt;. 
I ran again in &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/2021-python-software-foundation-board/nominees/iqbal-abdullah/"&gt;2021&lt;/a&gt; with a clearer direction on what I think is needed for the
PSF, based largely on my thoughts from that essay. To sum it up, in 2021 I wanted to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Increase representation and acknowledgement of the diverse communities that we have&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Increase the portion of the PSF revenues from non-PyCon US, specifically from non-US and non-Western Europe sources&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For 2021, I came in 7th place with 7.34% of the votes. It was an improvement, but not good enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will be my third time running for a seat on the PSF board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not much has changed within the past one year, and my objectives running for a seat in 2022 still remain the &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/2021-python-software-foundation-board/nominees/iqbal-abdullah/"&gt;same as 2021&lt;/a&gt;.
I believe these are still relevant and needed to be worked upon. In fact, I am hoping to use my platform as a PSF director, if elected, to accelerate interest within the
East Asia and South East Asia region on what and how we can contribute more to the Python community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other than help managing cooperation between different Python and PyCon organizing communities within the Asia Pacific region, I am still serving as a member of the &lt;a href="https://pyfound.blogspot.com/2020/12/announcing-psf-diversity-and-inclusion.html"&gt;Diversity &amp;amp; Inclusion (D&amp;amp;I) Working Group&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/committees/#trademarks-work-group"&gt;Trademarks Work Group&lt;/a&gt; of the PSF.
I was the chairperson for &lt;a href="https://pycon.my/2015/08/31/pycon-my-2015/"&gt;PyCon MY in 2015&lt;/a&gt;, the chairperson for &lt;a href="https://pycon.my/2017/09/01/pycon-apac-2017-it-s-a-wrap/"&gt;PyCon APAC 2017&lt;/a&gt; and served on the board for &lt;a href="https://www.pycon.jp/committee/english.html"&gt;PyCon JP&lt;/a&gt; from founding in 2013 until 2018.
I was one of the panelist for the &lt;a href="https://lalokalabs.co/en/events/diversity-inclusion-workgroup-panel-at-pycon-apac/"&gt;panel discussion for the Diversity and Inclusion WG for PyCon APAC 2021&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Saying thank you&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was also given the honour to give a keynote for &lt;a href="https://hamburg.python.pizza/"&gt;Python Pizza Hamburg&lt;/a&gt; where I addressed the issue of open source volunteers being taken for granted and more acknowledgement (including helping them with more money and paying our share) that needs to be done. This is an important topic close to our hearts, so within another business I founded, &lt;a href="https://blog.xoxzo.com/en/tag/annual-open-source-grant/"&gt;we annually give out grants to open source projects, including to the Python Software Foundation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;If you've read this far&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For 2022, &lt;em&gt;even if not elected&lt;/em&gt;, I will be happy if I can get a higher result than my previous elections. This will at least mean that the message and ideas I'm trying to bring has gained some traction among the people that matters and are invested: Those of you who will be voting. I can then bring this along with me in the future and tell my story to anyone that wants to listen with hope.
At the very least, regardless of the results, I hope my experience in participating in the elections will open the minds and hearts of the people around me, and doors for them, as by the people that have gone before me have done for me.
Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2022"></category><category term="psf"></category><category term="politics"></category><category term="community work"></category><category term="elections"></category><category term="python community"></category></entry><entry><title>Diversification is the future for the Python Software Foundation (PSF)</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/posts/2020/06/diversification-is-the-future-for-the-psf/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-06-20T16:05:00+09:00</published><updated>2020-06-20T16:05:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabdullah.net,2020-06-20:/posts/2020/06/diversification-is-the-future-for-the-psf/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;My thoughts after my failed attempt at running for the 2020 board of the Python Software Foundation (PSF).&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;The Premise&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since 2019, I have been working on trying to
get our Python community in East/South/South East Asia (collectively called APAC) to move towards a
more coherent direction together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were also plans for a poster session to introduce us to the wider North American and international community
during the annual PyCon 2020 in Pittsburgh, but due to COVID-19, that unfortunately didn't happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PyCon US&lt;sup id="fnref:fn01"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:fn01"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; is an annual Python programming language conference, which is organized by
the Python Software Foundation (PSF) and at the same time is also its single biggest
fundraising event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The Python Software Foundation (PSF)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I have to admit: When I started using Python in 2002, I didn't know about
the existence of the PSF. I only begin to understand that there is such a thing
as the PSF in 2010 when I attended my first PyCon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The PSF has a very important but very much obscure role to maintain and
safeguard the Python language, its ecosystems and the community that use and
depends on it. Read more about what the PSF does &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/#:~:text=The%20mission%20of%20the%20Python,international%20community%20of%20Python%20programmers."&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Running for a seat on the PSF board&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In June 2020, the Python Software Foundation (PSF) had four seats going vacant with
directors fulfilling their term. After many years &lt;a href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/posts/2017/06/changing-the-world-one-pycon-at-a-time/"&gt;working with and building the community on this side of the planet&lt;/a&gt;
I had a feeling that there is a gap between what the PSF, as a US-centric organization thinks it's doing, with what the rest
of the growing community on our part of the world think that they are doing, so I
decided to run for a seat, to at least represent a voice from E/S/SE Asia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have to admit that at that time, my motivations to run were still not very clear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do know that efforts to raise money will be important and I wanted to help: I
have been advocating for us to spread financial love to open source (&lt;a href="https://blog.xoxzo.com/en/2018/05/02/annual-opensource-grant-for-2018/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://www.slideshare.net/xoxzo/lightning-talk-pycon-thailand-2019"&gt;my lightning talk in PyCon TH&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7U2D5tcMZb4&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be&amp;amp;t=2107"&gt;my lightning talk in PyCon JP&lt;/a&gt;)
for the past few years and is something which I would like to continue doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I guess &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/2020-python-software-foundation-board/nominees/iqbal-abdullah/"&gt;my feelings were much stronger to share values and give a greater voice
to the communities which I am involved in&lt;/a&gt; with the greater Python community
through the PSF.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're reading this because you're interested to know what are the responsibilities of a
director of the PSF and what that person does on a day-to-day basis, these resources might be helpful:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://wiki.python.org/moin/PythonSoftwareFoundation/DutiesAndResponsibilitiesOfDirectors"&gt;Duties &amp;amp; Responsibilities of PSF Directors&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZLKj6FaQA4M"&gt;Life as a Python Software Foundation Director&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The results&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the election results was announced, I was in 11th place out of 26
nominees for the four board seats. 1,151 people were eligible to vote, while those that actually voted were 462 persons.
The elected top four nominees was:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/2020-python-software-foundation-board/nominees/nina-zakharenko/"&gt;Nina Zakharenko&lt;/a&gt;
with 263 votes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/2020-python-software-foundation-board/nominees/dustin-ingram/"&gt;Dustin Ingram&lt;/a&gt;
with 249 votes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/2020-python-software-foundation-board/nominees/jeff-triplett/"&gt;Jeff Triplett&lt;/a&gt;
with 240 votes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/2020-python-software-foundation-board/nominees/thomas-wouters/"&gt;Thomas Wouters&lt;/a&gt;
with 237 votes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After analyzing the results and reflecting on my own "campaign", it started to dawn on me
the real issue which I wanted to address which I also strongly believe is the future
for Python and its community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Issue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had the opportunity to participate in a Q&amp;amp;A session question on Slack, which was to
allow nominees or anyone else interested in the elections to ask questions to the
current board members. One of the questions I asked was about "active concerns for the PSF or something that the PSF
had wanted to achieve in the past two years or so".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/glasnt"&gt;Katie McLaughlin&lt;/a&gt; responded that in the short term a lot of work is happening around diversifying
the fundraising efforts especially given PyCon 2020 the biggest PSF fundraising event, didn't happen. In the longer term,
a lot of the efforts should be around focusing on goals, and ensuring that these multi-year efforts have the momentum to
continue and get completed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another insightful view was from &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/jackiekazil"&gt;Jacqueline Kazil&lt;/a&gt;, an outgoing PSF director.
She believes that &lt;a href="https://medium.com/@jackiekazil/elect-more-international-representation-finance-focused-individuals-to-psf-3eedcf0a91a7"&gt;the board needs more international representation and also people from finance backgrounds&lt;/a&gt;
to help with the financial issues and risks the PSF will face when a PyCon is cancelled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The points that they made really rang bells in my head. What we need is &lt;strong&gt;diversification&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Diversification&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The overarching theme of what I perceive as an issue for the PSF right now is
diversification, both in the context of representation of who we are, and also in the
context of financial support. In my view, these are inter-connected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;In representation&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was unfortunate this time that &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/valerybriz"&gt;Valeria Calderon&lt;/a&gt;,
a PyLadies organizer based in Mexico City missed a board seat by a few votes.
Other non-US based nominees such as &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/reydelhumo"&gt;Manuel Kaufmann&lt;/a&gt; who is Latin America Python Ambassador
and &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/muheuenga"&gt;Ngazetungue Muheue&lt;/a&gt; founder of Python
Namibia also didn't make the cut. All of them had the potential of bringing
fresh voices and views about the needs of communities that we have in different
parts of the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike the &lt;a href="https://realpython.com/lessons/python-steering-council/"&gt;Python Steering Council&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/dev/peps/pep-8101/"&gt;elections&lt;/a&gt; which has a technical and trust hurdle that is required for it to maintain
its core technical competency, the PSF board is open for &lt;em&gt;anyone&lt;/em&gt; to run when there are vacant seats.
The PSF board has a wider responsibility to use its resources for the betterment of the future of the
language and the people that rely on it, and technical core competencies are just one part of what you might need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This sends out a very important message: &lt;em&gt;We welcome you to help shape the future and aspirations
of us, whoever and wherever you are.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of the people elected this year are active in communities and speakers at conferences,
are authors of &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/dev/peps/pep-0001/#:~:text=PEP%20stands%20for%20Python%20Enhancement,a%20rationale%20for%20the%20feature."&gt;PEPs&lt;/a&gt; or writers of technical projects.
Some are also Working Group (WG) members in the PSF and one person is a current Python Steering Council member. Half of the elected
directors have directorship experience, one is a returning board member and all are US based persons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question is not that the directors which was elected in this and past
elections shouldn't be there: If they run and received the required votes, they of course should be there.
I am sure anyone elected to the board will have the best interests of all of us at heart and will do their best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question is: &lt;strong&gt;Does the 462 voters fairly reflect the current state and future aspirations of our worldwide Python community?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The PSF is in danger of being looked upon as being elitist, and is only open to a selected group of people who already
have access to a particular network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Increasing voter base&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As of now, there are &lt;a href="https://www.zdnet.com/article/programming-languages-python-developers-now-outnumber-java-ones/#:~:text=According%20to%20SlashData%2C%20there%20are,and%207.1%20million%20Java%20developers."&gt;8.2 million Python developers in the world&lt;/a&gt;.
In terms of developer population growth, the Asia Pacific region is showing the highest growth, with India taking over the US within the
next five years. The Latin America region is showing the second largest growth for the developer population. &lt;sup id="fnref:fn02"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:fn02"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To achieve the target of increasing diversity in representation, we need to increase the overall voter base. This is a tangible
and trackable goal, which we can bring back to the table every year and report on its progress back to the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know many people in JP, TW, KR, MY, ID, TH and ID who contribute their time and energy to actively participate and manage
meetups and conferences that support the ecosystem and would
&lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSfwWBGkzvkWDZrxW3up_M_B7qgt1IWZlx9KJ0ucLA5WJP1vfA/viewform"&gt;qualify as contributing members&lt;/a&gt;
but they are not reflected on our voter base.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why is that?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reflecting on my own experience, perhaps one of the biggest hurdle is &lt;strong&gt;indifference to the PSF within the Python community itself&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Tackling indifference&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another admission from myself: Even after knowing about the PSF in 2010, I
didn't seriously understand the relationship that the PSF could have with myself
and my community. From my point of view, it was an organization in faraway USA,
comprising mostly of white people who are mostly friends of each other and they attend PyCon in the US.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That point of view evolved when we started to apply for grants from the PSF for our own PyCons.
At that point the PSF is now an organization in faraway USA, comprising mostly of white people who mostly friends of each other and they
attend PyCon in the US that also gives out grants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was still not aware of the important work that the PSF was doing, like supporting our infrastructure through projects that it
funds, or what initiatives it has to increase inclusivity within our community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Increasing the voter base will directly result in community members which are
invested in knowing about all of the good and important work done by the PSF.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The PSF has done a great job at &lt;a href="http://pyfound.blogspot.com/2015/02/enroll-as-psf-voting-member.html"&gt;opening up memberships&lt;/a&gt;.
Other than the most obvious way of being a paying member to be a voting member, the revamped membership structure also
allows members who are active in other ways such as writing code or managing meetups and conferences to also become a
voting member.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The door has been set in place, so we next need to get people through that door.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The PSF should approach advocating about what it does like what tech companies do now days when they are hiring:
By stressing the impact of and influence its work on how their customers live their lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Advocating about these should not only be left to the project maintainer,
but everyone involved in the process from planning to approving the projects. In
this regard, the board of the PSF plays an important role to advocate and
market its role.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, we need to explain better how does&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Funding community initiatives to increase inclusivity like &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PyLadies"&gt;PyLadies&lt;/a&gt; and
  &lt;a href="https://us.pycon.org/2020/speaking/charlas/"&gt;PyCon Charlas&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Protecting the intellectual property of the PSF and it's communities worldwide, such as the name Python&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The technical initiatives funded by the PSF like the &lt;a href="https://beeware.org/"&gt;Beeware project&lt;/a&gt; or
&lt;a href="https://pypi.org/sponsor/"&gt;PyPI&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;affect our community, and most importantly how it will affect us in the future?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having someone come over from the US to talk about this and getting to know communities in
different parts of the world are great and shows that the PSF at least acknowledges the existence of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it is far much better when there is also someone that stays around these communities
and understand them better to carry on talking about the PSF long after &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/ewa_jodlowska"&gt;Ewa&lt;/a&gt;
or &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/naomiceder"&gt;Naomi&lt;/a&gt; has flown back home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;In finance&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Out of USD4.7MM of revenue for the PSF in 2019, around 61% of it came from PyCon.
USD1.9MM was the costs of having PyCon, which means that for every dollar spent
on PyCon, the PSF gets back 1.50 dollars. &lt;sup id="fnref:fn03"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:fn03"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compare that to the 28% of revenue from sponsorship fees, contributions, membership dues, and grants.
What costs were involved to generate these revenue? &lt;sup id="fnref:fn04"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:fn04"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If these are recurring revenue through already established processes, costs per dollar only diminishes
for every dollar we get. I believe the return per dollar invested into them are higher than what
PyCon brings in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps a target of increasing the portion from the non-PyCon revenue even if
the total amount of revenue are the same will make the PSF more resilient in the future against
&lt;a href="https://pyfound.blogspot.com/2020/03/psfs-projected-2020-financial-outcome.html"&gt;shocks like what COVID-19 brought to us&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Increasing the portion of non-PyCon revenue will require more understanding and
empathy from the wider base of our community. Who better can we tap other
than those who have already shown their commitment, either by the money they
have paid or the time and effort they have put in. This means building a
stronger relationship to the people that matter to us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As written when &lt;a href="https://pycon.blogspot.com/2020/03/pycon-us-2020-in-pittsburgh.html"&gt;PyCon 2020 cancellation was announced&lt;/a&gt;, 
some of the ways the community can help are getting employers involved in
sponsorships. Having invested members will help us advocate our mission to the
their immediate communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bigger investments in terms of bigger portion of grants given and time taken to
reach out to non-US communities, especially to the growing communities in
Asia and Latin America signals that the PSF is now shifting to investing &lt;strong&gt;for the
future&lt;/strong&gt; instead of the present. Bigger investment shows commitment, which
breeds goodwill, trust and paves the way for a stronger relationship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The PSF is already heading in the right direction in this aspect, although I
believe there are more ways we can improve, like the quantum of grant portions.&lt;sup id="fnref:fn05"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:fn05"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id="fnref:fn06"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:fn06"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With better relationship, we should next try to expand the supporting members
group, who directly contribute money to the PSF. I believe this is the one group
which we should really focus more on, as the returns from investing time and effort
to increase this base come at multiple levels: Not only on the financial support
that they give, but from the advocacy help that they will also bring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the context of commercial support and donations, we can try to diversify income
to non-US based companies. Perhaps we can use the percentage of grants given to
a certain region as a target for the amount of matching corporate sponsorships and
individual membership fees that we can expect to get from that region. Again,
in order for us to do that, we need a wider base of supporters on the ground
from that region to make it work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many successful local companies in each region and country that directly or indirectly
use Python in their businesses. Only our community members in those countries can tell us who
they are and connect us to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;In summary&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It all comes down to diversifying: To gain acceptance, understanding and finally
support from a much wider base of people, fitting the PSF as a worldwide organization supporting
its community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now at the end of writing this post, I believe that it is the &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; future for the PSF.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thank you to &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/terapyon"&gt;terapyon&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/scari_net"&gt;scari_net&lt;/a&gt; for proofreading
and reviewing this post. Thank you to &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/ewa_jodlowska"&gt;Ewa&lt;/a&gt; for proofreading and revewing the financial numbers&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:fn01"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going forward the PSF is rebranding PyCon to PyCon US since they happen everywhere according to Ewa&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:fn01" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:fn02"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.daxx.com/blog/development-trends/number-software-developers-world"&gt;How Many Software Developers Are There in the World?&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:fn02" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:fn03"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Total revenue in 2019 was $4,481,192 and $2,852,109 was from PyCon according to Ewa&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:fn03" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:fn04"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contributions and Grants were $1,165,278. We can also factor in PSF sponsorship fees, which are another $248,343. If we factor that in, that is ~32% according to Ewa&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:fn04" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:fn05"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/annual-report/2019/"&gt;PSF Annual Report 2018&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:fn05" title="Jump back to footnote 5 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:fn06"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/annual-report/2020/"&gt;PSF Annual Report 2019&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:fn06" title="Jump back to footnote 6 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="2020"></category><category term="psf"></category><category term="politics"></category><category term="community"></category><category term="2020"></category></entry><entry><title>多様化がPythonソフトウェア財団（PSF）の将来像</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/ja/posts/2020/06/diversification-is-the-future-for-the-psf/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-06-20T16:05:00+09:00</published><updated>2020-06-20T16:05:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabdullah.net,2020-06-20:/ja/posts/2020/06/diversification-is-the-future-for-the-psf/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Pythonソフトウェア財団（PSF）の2020年理事会選挙に立候補し落選して思うこと。&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;前提&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2019年以降、私は東アジア、南アジア、東南アジア（まとめてAPACと呼ばれる）にあるPythonコミュニティがより一貫した方向に進めるよう尽力してきた。
毎年北米で開催されるPyCon(今年はピッツバーグで開催)の期間中に、より広範な北米および国際コミュニティに
紹介するコミュニティブースも予定されていたが、COVID-19のため残念ながら中止になった。
PyCon US&lt;sup id="fnref:fn01"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:fn01"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; とはPythonソフトウェア財団（PSF）が主催する年に1度のプログラミング言語Pythonに関するカンファレンスで、
同時に唯一の大規模な資金調達イベントでもある。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Pythonソフトウェア財団（PSF）とは&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;まず、次のことを私は認めざるを得ない。2002年にPythonを使い始めたとき、PSFの存在については知らなかった。
2010年にPyConに初めて参加し、PSFというものの存在を理解し始めた。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PSFは、Python言語、そのエコシステム、それを使用し依存しているコミュニティを維持し保護するために非常に重要な、
しかし極めて一般的にあまり知られてないな役割を担っている。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PSFの取り組みについては&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/#:~:text=The%20mission%20of%20the%20Python,international%20community%20of%20Python%20programmers."&gt;こちら&lt;/a&gt;を参照してください。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;PSF理事会のポストに立候補&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2020年6月、任期が満了するPSFのディレクター(理事のこと)の4つの席が空席になる。
長年、&lt;a href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/posts/2017/06/changing-the-world-one-pycon-at-a-time/"&gt;地球の裏側でコミュニティを構築するために働きながら&lt;/a&gt;
私は米国中心の組織であるPSFが実行していると思っていることと、世界の他の場所で拡大しているコミュニティが実行していると思っていること
の間にギャップがあると感じていたので、少なくとも東・南・東南アジアの声を代弁するため、ディレクターに立候補することを決心した。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;正直に言うと、その時点でのモチベーションはそれほど明確ではなかった。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;資金調達の努力が重要だと知っており、次のようなことを支援したかった。
私は過去数年にわたり、オープンソースに対し金銭的な愛を広めるよう&lt;a href="https://blog.xoxzo.com/en/2018/05/02/annual-opensource-grant-for-2018/"&gt;ここで&lt;/a&gt;、&lt;a href="https://www.slideshare.net/xoxzo/lightning-talk-pycon-thailand-2019"&gt;PyCon THでのLTで&lt;/a&gt;および&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7U2D5tcMZb4&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be&amp;amp;t=2107"&gt;PyCon JPでのLTで&lt;/a&gt;)提唱してきたし、これからも続けたいと思っている。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;しかし、PSFを通じてより大きなPythonコミュニティが一緒になれば&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/2020-python-software-foundation-board/nominees/iqbal-abdullah/"&gt;価値観を共有する私の思いはさらに強まり、関わっているコミュニティへの発言権ももっと大きくなった&lt;/a&gt;と思う。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ちなみに、PSFディレクターが担う責任と日常的な活動を知りたくてこれを読んでいるなら、次のリンクが役立つかもしれない。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://wiki.python.org/moin/PythonSoftwareFoundation/DutiesAndResponsibilitiesOfDirectors"&gt;PSFディレクターの任務と責任&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZLKj6FaQA4M"&gt;Pythonソフトウェア財団ディレクターとしての生活&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;選挙の結果&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;選挙結果が発表され、私は空席4に対する候補者26人中11位だった。見事に落選 😅&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;投票権持つ1,151人のうち、実際に投票したのは462人だけだった。
選出された上位4名は、以下のとおり。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/2020-python-software-foundation-board/nominees/nina-zakharenko/"&gt;Nina Zakharenko&lt;/a&gt;
得票数 263&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/2020-python-software-foundation-board/nominees/dustin-ingram/"&gt;Dustin Ingram&lt;/a&gt;
得票数 249&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/2020-python-software-foundation-board/nominees/jeff-triplett/"&gt;Jeff Triplett&lt;/a&gt;
得票数240&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/2020-python-software-foundation-board/nominees/thomas-wouters/"&gt;Tomas Wouters&lt;/a&gt;
得票数 237&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;結果を分析し自分自身の「選挙活動」を振り返った後、私がPythonとそのコミュニティの将来像だと強く確信し取り組みたいと考えていた、
本当の課題が鮮明に見えてきた。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;その課題とは&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;私はSlackでの質疑応答セッションに参加する機会があったが、そこでは立候補者または選挙に関心を持つほかの誰でも現在の理事会メンバーに
質問することができた。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1つ私が尋ねたのは、「PSF、あるいは過去数年間PSFが達成を望んでいた事柄に関して今取り組んでいる懸念事項」のことだった。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/glasnt"&gt;Katie McLaughlin&lt;/a&gt;さんは、特に最大のPSF資金調達イベント、PyCon 2020が開催されなかったことを考えると、
短期的には資金調達の努力を多様化するために多くの施策が行われている、と回答した。長期的には、多くの取り組みは目標に焦点を当て、
この何年にもわたる努力が継続し完了するための勢いを確保するべきだ。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;任期満了するもう一人のPSFディレクター&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/jackiekazil"&gt;Jacqueline Kazil&lt;/a&gt;さんからも、
洞察力に富んだ別の見解をもらった。
彼女は、PyConが中止された際PSFが直面する財務上の問題とリスクを支援するために、
&lt;a href="https://medium.com/@jackiekazil/elect-more-international-representation-finance-focused-individuals-to-psf-3eedcf0a91a7"&gt;理事会はより国際的な代表の選出と、ファイナンス関連の知識を持つ人物を必要としている&lt;/a&gt;と考えている。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;こうした主張を聞き、私たちに必要なのは&lt;strong&gt;多様化&lt;/strong&gt;であることピンときた。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;多様化&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;私たちの代表を選出する点でも資金面のサポートという点でも、現時点でPSFの問題として私が把握した包括的なテーマは、多様化であること。
私思うのは、この両方は相互に関連している。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;代表の選出&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;今回PyLadiesのメキシコ拠点オーガナイザー、&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/valerybriz"&gt;Valeria Calderon&lt;/a&gt;さんが数票差で落選したのは残念だった。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;その他米国以外の立候補者、中南米のPython Ambassadorである&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/reydelhumo"&gt;Manuel Kaufmann&lt;/a&gt;さんや、
Python Namibiaの創立者&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/muheuenga"&gt;Ngazetungue Muheue&lt;/a&gt;さんなども落選した。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ちなみにManuelさんは&lt;a href="https://pycon.jp/2018/"&gt;PyCon JP 2018のキーノートスピーカの一人だった&lt;/a&gt;。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;これら全員が、世界のさまざまな地域に存在するコミュニティのニーズに関して新鮮な意見や見解を持ち込む可能性があった。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;中核となる技術的コンピテンシーを維持するため求められる技術力と信頼性のハードルが高い&lt;a href="https://realpython.com/lessons/python-steering-council/"&gt;Python意思決定議会&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/dev/peps/pep-8101/"&gt;選挙&lt;/a&gt;とは異なり、
PSF理事会は空席があれば誰でも立候補できる。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PSF理事会はこの言語とそれに依存する人々の将来を向上させるためにリソースをうまく活用する責任があり、
技術的なコア・コンピテンシーは必要となるかもしれない素質の一部に過ぎない。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;これは、非常に重要なメッセージを発信している。
&lt;em&gt;あなたがどこにいる誰であっても、私たちの将来を形作り願望を実現する手助けは歓迎される。&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;今年の当選者は全員コミュニティで活発に活動しており、カンファレンスのスピーカーであり、
&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/dev/peps/pep-0001/#:~:text=PEP%20stands%20for%20Python%20Enhancement,a%20rationale%20for%20the%20feature."&gt;PEP&lt;/a&gt;の著者または技術プロジェクトのライターでもある。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PSFのワーキンググループ（WG）メンバーも数人おり、1人は現行のPython意思決定議会メンバーである。
当選者の半分はディレクター業務の経験があり、1人は理事会メンバーへの復帰であり、全員が米国を拠点としている。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;今回あるいは過去の選挙で当選したディレクターがふさわしいかどうかが問題なのではない。
立候補し、必要な得票数に達していれば、当然ディレクターになるべき。
私は選出された理事会メンバーが、私たち全員の利益を最優先に考え最善を尽くすことを確信している。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;問題は、&lt;strong&gt;投票した462人というのは、世界中のPythonコミュニティが抱く将来への願望と現在の状況を公正に反映しているのか？&lt;/strong&gt;
ということ。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PSFはエリートとみなされる危険があり、すでに特定のネットワーク関われている人々のグループに対してのみ開かれている。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;投票権持つ者のベースの拡大&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;現在、世界には&lt;a href="https://www.zdnet.com/article/programming-languages-python-developers-now-outnumber-java-ones/#:~:text=According%20to%20SlashData%2C%20there%20are,and%207.1%20million%20Java%20developers."&gt;820万人のPython開発者&lt;/a&gt;がいる。
開発者人口の増加という点で、アジア太平洋地域は最高の成長率を示しており、インドは今後5年以内に米国に取って代わる。
中南米地域は、2番目に高い開発者人口の成長率を示している。&lt;sup id="fnref:fn02"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:fn02"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;代表者の多様性を高めるという目標を達成するには、全体的な有権者ベースを増やす必要がある。毎年検討を繰り返し、
進捗状況をコミュニティに報告すれば、これは目に見える追跡可能な目標である。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;日本、台湾、韓国、マレーシア、インドネシア、タイ、フィリピンなどにいるたくさんの人材が、エコシステムをサポートする
会合やカンファレンスに積極的に参加したり開催したりするため時間とエネルギーを費やしており、
&lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSfwWBGkzvkWDZrxW3up_M_B7qgt1IWZlx9KJ0ucLA5WJP1vfA/viewform"&gt;補助メンバーとして適任である&lt;/a&gt;
ことを私は知っているが、彼らは投票権持ってないし、このベースに反映されていない。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;どうしてでしょうか？&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;自分自身の経験を振り返ってみて、おそらく最大級のハードルは&lt;strong&gt;Pythonコミュニティ自体に内在するPSFに対する無関心&lt;/strong&gt;だろう。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;無関心への取り組み&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;あともう一つのざんげ。
2010年にPSFについて知ったにもかかわらず、PSFが自分自身とコミュニティにどう関係するのか、真剣に考えていなかった。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;私の視点からは、米国のPyConに参加している大半が友達同士の白人たちで構成された、遠く離れた米国の組織だった。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;その視点は自分たちのPyConのためにPSFの助成金を申請し始めたときに進化した。
その時点においてPSFは助成金も出してくれる同じ組織であることを再確認された。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;資金供給するプロジェクトを通して私たちのインフラをサポートしたり、コミュニティ内の参加性を促進する取り組みを率先したりといった、
PSFが行っている重要な業務についてまだよく分かっていなかった。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;有権者ベースの拡大は、投資を受けたコミュニティ・メンバーがPSFの行っている重要な業務すべてを知ることにそのままつながるのである。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PSFは&lt;a href="http://pyfound.blogspot.com/2015/02/enroll-as-psf-voting-member.html"&gt;会員制をオープンする&lt;/a&gt;にあたり、実に大きな前進だった。
投票権を持つメンバーとなるために会費を支払うという最も分かりやすい方法に加え、
刷新した会員制度ではコードを書いたり会合やカンファレンスを主催したりする活動的なメンバーにもまた投票権が与えられる。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;扉は所定の位置に設置されているのだから、次にやるべきはその扉から入ってくるよう人々を促すことである。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PSFは、現在テクノロジー企業が採用の際に行っているようなことを提唱するアプローチを取る必要がある。
顧客の生活に及ぼす効果や影響を強調することによってである。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;こうしたことを提唱するにあたり、プロジェクト管理者に丸投げするべきでなく、
プロジェクトの発案から承認に至るプロセスに関わった全員が行うべきだ。
この点において、PSF理事会はその役割を提唱し売り込む上で重要な役割を担っている。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;例えば、次のことをより詳しく説明する必要がある。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PyLadies"&gt;PyLadies&lt;/a&gt;や&lt;a href="https://us.pycon.org/2020/speaking/charlas/"&gt;PyCon Charlas&lt;/a&gt;など
への参加性を促進するため資金調達においてコミュニティで率先すること&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pythonの名前など、PSFおよび世界中にあるコミュニティの知的財産を保護すること&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://beeware.org/"&gt;Beeware project&lt;/a&gt;や&lt;a href="https://pypi.org/sponsor/"&gt;PyPI&lt;/a&gt;など
PSFが資金提供する技術的な取り組みが私たちのコミュニティに影響し、さらに重要なことに未来にどう影響するか&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;米国から誰かを招いてこうしたことを話し合い、世界の他の場所にあるコミュニティについて知ることは重要であり、
少なくともPSFはそのコミュニティの存在を認識していることを示せる。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;とはいえそのようなコミュニティの近くにとどまり、コミュニティをよりよく理解し、&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/ewa_jodlowska"&gt;Ewa&lt;/a&gt;
あるいは&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/naomiceder"&gt;Naomi&lt;/a&gt;が去った後もずっとPSFについて語り続けられる人物がいれば、
そのほうがずっと良いだろう。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;財政に関して&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2019年のPSF収益USD450万のうち、その61%以上がPyConから得たものだった。
PyCon開催費用の総額はUSD190万なので、つまりPSFがPyConに1ドルを投じること対して1.50ドルが戻ってくるという計算になる。
&lt;sup id="fnref:fn03"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:fn03"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id="fnref:fn05"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:fn05"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;これを、寄付、会員費、助成金から成る収益の残り28%と比較してみよう。その種の収益を得るのに、どれほどの費用がかかるだろうか。&lt;sup id="fnref:fn04"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:fn04"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
すでに確立されたプロセスを通した継続的な収益の場合、1ドルあたりの費用は収益を得るたびに減少する。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;投資した1ドルあたりの利益率はPyConのそれより高いと思う。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;総収益額が変わらずともPyCon以外からの収益を増やすという目標により、PSFは将来&lt;a href="https://pyfound.blogspot.com/2020/03/psfs-projected-2020-financial-outcome.html."&gt;COVID-19が与えたような衝撃&lt;/a&gt;に対してより柔軟に対応できるようになるだろう。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PyCon以外からの収益を増やすには、コミュニティのより広範なベースからの理解と共感を必要なのだ。
認識して手を差し伸べないといけないのはお金や投入した時間と労力ですでに高い関心を示してくれてるコミュニティーの皆、他でもない。
こうして、私たちにとって大切な人々とより強い関係を築くことになる。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://pycon.blogspot.com/2020/03/pycon-us-2020-in-pittsburgh.html"&gt;PyCon 2020中止の発表&lt;/a&gt;に記載されているように、
雇用主にスポンサーシップに参加してもらうことも関心が高いコミュニティができる支援策にもなれる。関心が高い、関わりたい気持ちを
持つメンバーがいれば、彼らの身近なコミュニティに対し私たちの目標を提唱する助けになる。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;米国以外のコミュニティ、特にアジアや南米の拡大しているコミュニティに手を差し伸べるため費やした助成金の大部分と
時間という観点での大きな投資は、PSFが現在ではなく&lt;strong&gt;未来のため&lt;/strong&gt;投資していることを示している。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;大きな投資は大きな関心を意味し、それが好意と信用を生み、より強固な関係への道を開く。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PSFはすでにこの面において正しい方向に向かっているが、助成金の配分量など、さらなる改善の余地があると思っている。&lt;sup id="fnref2:fn05"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:fn05"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id="fnref:fn06"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:fn06"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;より良い関係を築くために、次はPSFへ直接資金援助してくれる支援メンバーのグループ拡大に尽力すべきだ。
このグループを私たちが本当に重視すべきグループで、うまく拡大できれば、財政的なサポートだけでなく、
彼らがもたらすアドボカシーからの支援も得られる。いろんなレベルでプラスになることだろう。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;商業的なサポートと寄付という観点から、米国拠点ではない企業からの収益を多様化するよう尽力もできる。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;具体的に理事会として特定の地域に与えられた助成金の割合を、その地域から得られる企業のスポンサーシップや個人の会費を同額になるよう、
という目標を設定することも考えられる。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;また、それを実行するにあたり、状況を有利に生かすためその地域に根付いたより広範な支援者ベースを必要とする。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;各地域および国には、直接または間接的に事業でPythonを使う、成功した地元の企業が多数存在する。
その国のコミュニティ・メンバーだけがそれを知っており、互いの架け橋となってくれる。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;結論&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;すべては多様化に行き着くことになる。受容の幅を広げ、理解し、最終的に広範なベースの人々から支援されるため、
コミュニティを支援する世界的な組織としてPSFを適合させていく。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;この投稿を終えるにあたり、それがPSFにおける唯一の将来像であると確信している。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;この投稿をレビューしてくれた&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/terapyon"&gt;terapyon&lt;/a&gt;に感謝します&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:fn01"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going forward the PSF is rebranding PyCon to PyCon US since they happen everywhere according to Ewa&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:fn01" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:fn02"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.daxx.com/blog/development-trends/number-software-developers-world"&gt;How Many Software Developers Are There in the World?&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:fn02" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:fn03"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Total revenue in 2019 was $4,481,192 and $2,852,109 was from PyCon according to Ewa&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:fn03" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:fn04"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contributions and Grants were $1,165,278. We can also factor in PSF sponsorship fees, which are another $248,343. If we factor that in, that is ~32% according to Ewa&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:fn04" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:fn05"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/annual-report/2019/"&gt;PSF Annual Report 2018&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:fn05" title="Jump back to footnote 5 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref2:fn05" title="Jump back to footnote 5 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:fn06"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/annual-report/2020/"&gt;PSF Annual Report 2019&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:fn06" title="Jump back to footnote 6 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="2020"></category><category term="psf"></category><category term="政治"></category><category term="コミュニティ"></category><category term="2020"></category></entry><entry><title>Digital IDs for Malaysia</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/posts/2018/10/digital-ids-for-malaysia/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-10-21T18:40:00+09:00</published><updated>2018-10-21T18:40:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabdullah.net,2018-10-21:/posts/2018/10/digital-ids-for-malaysia/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Digital IDs to verify identities will propel us forward.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is an article on my opinion concerning the plan for digital IDs for Malaysians. It was not published.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Bringing back the idea&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since Minister Gobind brought back the idea of a &lt;a href="http://www.bernama.com/en/news.php?id=1651523"&gt;digital ID for Malaysians&lt;/a&gt;, we are seeing a healthy debate going on concerning the feasibility or even the need for a national digital ID. I would like to also contribute to this debate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;I am who I say I am&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The internet was originally designed to be "stateless", which basically means it has no memory. This means that if you visit a website and come back 3 seconds later, the website will treat you like a totally new person on your subsequent visits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is obviously an issue when you need to get things done. You won't have shopping carts, Instagram timelines, or friends on Facebook because the internet cannot differentiate between you and your grandmother.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along the way, innovative ways were invented to work around this limitation, such as "cookies" and sessions, which have evolved to produce the user registration, username, and password combination that we so much love today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One problem with this method is that no one is vouching for you: You come up saying "this is who I am, and I'm vouching for myself that this is true". For Facebook or Instagram, where the most complex everyday use case is sharing pictures of cats or your rented Chanel handbags, this is all fine. But if you need to do anything more that comes with responsibilities and social consequences, like registering your newborn child, renewing your business license, or making a loan application, someone needs to make sure that you are who you say you are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This should be the main and only purpose a national ID program should perform: verifying that you are who you say you are, or in other words, creating a "platform of trust", as termed by Minister Gobind.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;I don't trust you, but I trust that person who you trust&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By design and nature of the internet, I cannot trust you, but the funny thing is, I will trust something that you also trust. This "something" naturally falls to some central authority like a government, because they are the issuer of identities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is interesting to note that this concept is not new: we are already using it in the HTTPS/TLS scheme (the padlock that you see in your browser's address bar, which ensures you're accessing a secure site).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Private entities, such as banks, are also able to connect to this central system. Using a state-issued ID card, you can access the myriad of private services that connect to the state and verify that you are who you are. Once they know who you are, you are then authorized to carry out actions based on the services you're currently accessing, such as making money transfers from your bank account or renewing your driving license.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A platform of trust, based on officially sanctioned national ID, to directly verify identity is more meaningful than indirect methods, such as sending SMS to mobile numbers, which prove possession rather than identity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, the central authority should not (or must not) have access to whatever you're doing online once you've passed the verification phase. What you do, once you've been verified, will only be between you and the services you're utilizing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;A paper photocopied IC is not "verification"&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current way of doing things, as practiced by the majority of Malaysians regarding identity verification, is broken at best. We take our physical ID and make physical paper copies of it to sign up for services from opening bank accounts to subscribing to mobile plans. This is far from secure nor is it an effective form of identity verification and can be easily abused. We have read of many cases where someone else has signed up for something, which the real owner of that identity does not know about and instead is paying for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An online platform of trust will help us reduce the likelihood of abuse by taking away the physical aspect of identity verification, which will also lead to a more efficient workflow since data can be processed much more easily than physical records.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, but having said that, we also must understand and appreciate this: No technology is perfect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;It's Not If, But When&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fear that a central authority can be hacked is justified, and it is a risk that needs to be mitigated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the technology context, we mitigate this risk by increasing the hurdles before any hacked data is made usable, and minimizing the damage &lt;strong&gt;when&lt;/strong&gt; (and not if) there is a data breach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do this by ensuring that hacked data is unusable without a second factor, such as an encrypted physical ID, which is not connected in any way to the central system. Those physical IDs can also be locked by passwords, which are stored on the ID itself and supposedly known only to the ID holder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means that if an aspiring hacker wants to steal the data of citizens in Malaysia, they need to hack the central system and steal 30 million ID cards, as well as figure out the password to access that physical device. At the same time, third-parties like banks which access the central system to verify identity will not have the identity verification information on them, which means if the banks are hacked, the hacker will know how much money an account has but will not know who that account belongs to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Estonia's E-Residency Programme&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am enrolled in the Estonian E-Residency programme, where the state vouches for you and issues a state-sanctioned ID card which you can use to connect to state services online. The ID card does not have my picture on it, and is not valid as a self-identification document in the physical world. Estonia's E-Residency system employs the same scheme for personal verification and authentication I have explained above. It is also used by her 1.3 million citizens to access government services, other than e-residents (which can access the same services too!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thousands of kilometers away, day or night, in my living room or at my favorite local café, I can sign agreements, check the status of my applications, and operate my business without having to wait in line or get stuck in traffic because all the different moving parts that I need to interact with know with a very high probability and confidence that I am who I say I am.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I know 1.3 million people versus Malaysia's 30 million people is a huge difference, but that's the beauty of technology - you can scale it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;So...&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do we need this? I truly believe so. In fact, I believe it is inevitable. The technology is already there; it's open and we have no need to invent anything new. The actual example of implementing it statewide is also there (Estonia), as well as any leanings or know-how. It has been done and it has been proven.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The right to be connected online is now starting to be accepted as a universal human right. Coupled with the constant business need to get better efficiency and savings, being able to do work and business online will become increasingly necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Allowing us to do business and deal with bureaucracy online will free up a tremendous amount of time that we can use to enrich ourselves in many other ways. This is, in the end, what technology is supposed to be about: empowering human beings by allowing us to regain our most valuable resource – time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more relevant and important question is, when?
Obviously, as a country with limited resources, there is the question of prioritization. I will leave that question as a homework assignment to be answered by our elected representatives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But before we embark on this project, an important issue we must address, as &lt;a href="https://www.malaymail.com/s/1683682/dear-politicians-digital-ids-are-a-terrible-idea"&gt;pointed out by Ms. Erna Mahyuni in her piece&lt;/a&gt;, is that Malaysia does not have a good track record of enforcing privacy laws, and to top it off, there is a very low understanding of privacy and privacy rights. This is a larger issue which should be addressed, regardless of having a national digital ID or not, as it affects us all, right here, right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I believe the creation of a national digital ID as a basis for a platform of trust to empower citizens of Malaysia is inevitable in order to remain relevant and competitive.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2018"></category><category term="current affairs"></category><category term="malaysia"></category><category term="estonia"></category><category term="tech"></category></entry><entry><title>Your roots and your identity</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/posts/2017/10/your-root-and-your-identity/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-10-06T23:40:00+09:00</published><updated>2017-10-06T23:40:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabdullah.net,2017-10-06:/posts/2017/10/your-root-and-your-identity/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Your roots are not your identity; It does not define who you are.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;62-year old &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kazuo_Ishiguro"&gt;Kuzo Ishigoro&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/books/2017/oct/05/kazuo-ishiguro-wins-the-nobel-prize-in-literature"&gt;won
the Nobel Prize in Literature&lt;/a&gt;
for 2017. I saw him on TV and he was talking about his Japanese roots,
and that got me thinking about &lt;em&gt;roots&lt;/em&gt; and how we confuse it with our &lt;em&gt;identity&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many upheaval caused by nationalist movements in the current world around us right
now are symbols of the assertion of identity and stem from the need to differentiate. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe though, contrary to popular belief, your roots are not your identity.
Our roots are our past and history, mostly events in our lives in which we do not
have much say due to our dependence on our parents and immediate families.
Our roots are emotional attachments and memories of the past, that allow us to
return to a place where we came from, physically or emotionally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Identity though, is forward-facing: Identity is who you are, or who you strive to be
in the future. You can choose to identify yourself with someplace or something, like the
town you're staying in or an idea that feels right to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your identity is a conscious choice, for better or for worse, which you can define.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be defined by your roots, and then have your identity set upon you based on
some set values of your roots are just too inhumane and unfair.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knowing where you come from does help in figuring out where you will be heading,
but it does not define your destination.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2017"></category><category term="identity"></category></entry><entry><title>Changing the world one PyCon at a time</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/posts/2017/06/changing-the-world-one-pycon-at-a-time/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-06-15T16:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2017-06-15T16:00:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabdullah.net,2017-06-15:/posts/2017/06/changing-the-world-one-pycon-at-a-time/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Thinking back on what I've done through PyCon and how it all started in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Changing the world one PyCon at a time&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an engineer, programming languages are very important tools to solve the
problems that you face. As an entrepreneur, they are also important tools to
bring your imagination to life, to get that profit and make that difference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Python is a magnificent programming language. Although first released in 1991, it &lt;em&gt;arguably&lt;/em&gt;
only started to become mainstream&lt;sup id="fnref:fn01"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:fn01"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; when
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guido_van_Rossum"&gt;Guido van Rossum&lt;/a&gt;, the creator of
Python joined Google in 2005. That made many people start to notice how serious
the tech giant was investing in Python. In the same year, the web framework
Django which is written in Python was released, and that further pushed Python into the limelight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, even our very much loved
&lt;a href="https://thenewstack.io/instagram-makes-smooth-move-python-3/"&gt;Instagram uses Python&lt;/a&gt; 
to handle its hundreds of millions of requests. Python is also used in
scientific and academic fields&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been using Python since 2002, and in many ways, it has given me the
intellectual challenge I craved, allowed me the freedom to bring my imagination
to life, and PyCon, has allowed me to meet wonderful people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;My First PyCon, APAC 2010 in Singapore&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But a programming language is only as good as the people who use it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Python_Conference"&gt;PyCon&lt;/a&gt; is, in essence, a conference
centred around the Python programming language. Its roots started with the first PyCon in
Washington D.C in 2003 and has expanded to many parts of the world, from Europe, Japan,
China, India, HK, Taiwan, Australia, New Zealand, Singapore and also Malaysia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Up until 2010, before attending my first PyCon, I had been using Python for fun
and profit for 8 years. I find the language easy to use, has a design that fits
with my mind and how I believe coding should be, and most importantly I enjoyed using
it to build stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So when I saw the poster for the first PyCon APAC in Singapore in 2010, I
decided to meet the people behind it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="PyCon APAC 2010 Singapore" src="https://iqbalabdullah.net/images/pycons/pycon-apac-2010-poster.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn't know anyone there but I thought I'd just make new friends and see
what other cool stuff everyone else was building. And made friends I did: I met up with
three other participants from Japan: Manabu Terada
(&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/terapyon?lang=en"&gt;@terapyon&lt;/a&gt;),
Yasuhi Masuda(&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/whosaysni?lang=en"&gt;@whosaysni&lt;/a&gt;) and Ian
Lewis(&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/ianmlewis?lang=en"&gt;@ianmlewis&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it turns out, the chairperson for the first PyCon APAC in Singapore was Liew Beng Keat
(&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/bengkeatliew"&gt;@bengkeatliew&lt;/a&gt;) a Malaysian from Kuala
Lumpur. We have more in common than I thought!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bringing PyCon to the region&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was then that Beng Keat was telling me the reason he wanted to organize a
regional version of PyCon APAC: Beng Keat had the opportunity to attend PyCon in
the United States, and although he enjoyed the conference and came back enlightened,
he also realized how prohibitive it is to travel from Asia to the United States
and so he thought: &lt;em&gt;If we can't go to PyCon in the US, we'll bring
PyCon here.&lt;/em&gt; And since Singapore was such a small place, it makes more sense to
make it a regional conference instead of just a local conference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The concept of having a regional PyCon is in essence a very simple one, with a
well defined purpose: We understand that nearly all of the advances made in
technology by the programming language, new concepts and philosophy in thinking about the
language and even how communities are organized towards the greater good for
everyone at large originates mostly in the United States and Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we cannot be in the United States to meet and listen to the great minds that shape
the programming language, its community and its future, let us have those minds
here instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And at that first APAC PyCon in Singapore, one of the keynote speakers was &lt;a href="https://github.com/holdenweb"&gt;Steve
Holden&lt;/a&gt;, who was the chairman for PSF&lt;sup id="fnref:fn02"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:fn02"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, 
who later on was a pivotal figure in the growth of PyCon within APAC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Building the Japan PyCon community, circa 2011&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We invited Steve to come to Tokyo after APAC, and over dinner, we talked about
having an annual conference to get Pythonistas from all over the country to come
and share their work and discuss their ideas. Steve was instrumental in providing
us, who had no experience at all running conferences, to take the idea
seriously. Given the fact that Python was still considered an obscure
language in Japan as opposed to PHP, Java or Ruby, we were also sceptical that
there would be any traction at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Steve Holden in Tokyo" src="https://iqbalabdullah.net/images/pycons/steve-holden-in-tokyo-02.jpg"&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Dinner with Steve in Roppongi&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Steve Holden in Tokyo" src="https://iqbalabdullah.net/images/pycons/steve-holden-in-tokyo-01.jpg"&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;With Masuda-san and Takizawa-san&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following that dinner with Steve, Terada-san, Masuda-san and I met again on the
1st of July 2010 in an underground Turkish restaurant in Shibuya and over dinner decided
to have our first stab at a PyCon in Japan. We agreed to start small, and host
APAC when we are ready.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Email calling for the first PyCon meeting" src="https://iqbalabdullah.net/images/pycons/shibuya-email.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had our first &lt;a href="https://sites.google.com/site/pyconminijp/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;mini&lt;/em&gt; PyCon JP&lt;/a&gt; 
on a cold January morning in 2011 at the Rakuten offices in Tokyo. I was 
involved as the program manager, choosing talks and deciding the contents of the conference.
130 people came for the mini-conference, and we all had a great time listening
to talks, learning and making new friends. The conference was free, and everyone
had bento for lunch provided by our generous sponsors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Encouraged by the turnout and how the first conference went, we then decided to
have a major PyCon JP for the first time in the summer of 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PyCon JP has been held every year around summer since then and in 2016 our
attendees topped 700 people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back to 2012: An issue that we faced after the second PyCon in 2012 was that it was getting
too big, and the leftover money from sponsors was getting too much to handle
out from an individual account. We also needed a face for the public and a
definite entity that will take responsibility for managing the annual conference
in Japan. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of that, the non-profit PyCon JP was established in March 2013, and I
am still currently serving as part of the board members.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To prepare to host APAC, since 2012 we needed to give an international flavour for the
conference, and we made it a point to have at least one track which will be in
English only. This has attracted participation from nearby countries, such as
South Korea and Taiwan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To also attract interest from the public, and because our
non-profit run on money gained from public interests, we also made it a point to
have an open non-profit general meeting during the local PyCons. It is here
where we met other people who are thinking or are interested in running their
own PyCons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;PyCon APAC in Japan, 2013&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Singapore has been organizing the APAC conference for 3 years in a row since
2010, and following the model of PyCon US of moving the venue to different cities
every two years, 2013 they approached us in Japan to take over APAC and organize
it is in Japan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have been preparing for this since 2011, so we agreed. Our Taiwan counterpart
was also keen on running APAC, but after discussions they agreed to bid for
2014 instead. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was good for us in the region on 2 accounts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The regional conference APAC has finally moved away from Singapore to a
  different city&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We have another host decided for 2014.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So in August 2013, we organized PyCon APAC in Shinjuku, Tokyo, and that is where
we met all the many people who will spread PyCon across the region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Asia Pacific Connection&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regionally, we have a loosely knit community that drives PyCon APAC
(Asia Pacific). Ideally, PyCon APAC is a regional conference that rotates
between cities within the APAC region, and aims to be an international
and bigger conference allowing the regional python
community to come together at a more accessible and affordable location compared to
having to travel to the United States or Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the APAC conference in Tokyo in 2013, there was consensus from the regional
community representatives such as Singapore and South Korea which we managed to
get in touch with when they came to APAC in Tokyo, to move the APAC conference to Taipei.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since there was no other community which has shown interest in hosting APAC for
2015, the conference stayed in Taipi until 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="PyCon APAC dinner in Taipei" src="https://iqbalabdullah.net/images/pycons/pycon-apac-tw-06-2015.jpg"&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;With Van Lindberg, Chairperson for the PSF, Beng Keat, and our friends and staff organizing
PyCon APAC TW in 2015.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The South Korean community, after having their first local PyCon in
2015 stepped up to the plate to host APAC in 2016 and was successful with over 1000 attendees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="PyCon APAC meeting in Seoul 2016" src="https://iqbalabdullah.net/images/pycons/apac-meeting-seoul-2015.jpg"&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;A community meeting of representatives from the different countries in APAC
during the 2016 APAC conference: KR, JP, VN, TW, PH, MY, HK and SG were present&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="PyCon APAC meeting in Seoul 2016" src="https://iqbalabdullah.net/images/pycons/pycon-apac-seoul-2016-group.jpg"&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Group picture after the community meeting&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The regional communities have done a wonderful job of boosting their local PyCon
conferences to be a well-known annual event to gather and share knowledge among
their Python users. The regional APAC conferences have also proved to be a platform where new community leaders from neighbouring countries come to connect
and learn how to organize their own local PyCons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We make it a point to reach out to fellow community members from countries which up until now
have no representation in our loose groups, like Myanmar or Vietnam.  I've seen fellow Pythonistas
who came to a PyCon APAC for the first time, and their eyes light up and they smile and say
now they want to start something in their city and their community after
experiencing the conference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="PyCon APAC dinner in Taipei" src="https://iqbalabdullah.net/images/pycons/dylan-jay-bangkok.jpg"&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Meeting up with Dylan Jay in Bangkok. Dylan is the former lead for the Sydney
Python Users Group&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The collective knowledge of all of us helps to remove some anxiety and helps guide
them on what are the points that they'll need to keep in mind to start something
for their city, from organizing know-how to even getting sponsorship
funding. The PSF in this regard has been supportive in providing grants and
also speakers at the APAC conferences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Connecting Pythonistas in Malaysia&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After helping out with running PyCon in Japan, I realized that all the PyCons
that we had in the APAC region has all been on the north-eastern part of Asia
Pacific, except Singapore, but all of them were either cost or time
prohibitive to the rest of Asia Pacific.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that begins my next project: To kickstart an annual PyCon in Malaysia grown
for the locals, from the locals, and bring APAC and the rest of the world to Kuala Lumpur.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I aim to have an APAC conference here in Kuala Lumpur as I believe, compared
to the north-east of Asia Pacific, a conference here will be more accessible to
much more people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If we can't go to PyCon, we'll get PyCon here.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Malaysia, the history of PyCon started in 2014 when we had our
first mini PyCon (1 day, single track and 70 people attended) and
continued with PyCon MY 2015 (2 days, 2 tracks and around 140 people
attended) and PyCon MY 2016 (2 days, 2 tracks and around 100 people
attended). I was involved as the co-chair and finance person for the mini
PyCon 2014, the chair for PyCon MY 2015, and co-chair again in 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can read more about us at &lt;a href="https://pycon.my/"&gt;https://pycon.my/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But before we start running an international conference like the APAC, we need
to know &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; to at least run a conference. Having local experienced people to organise
conferences will also allow us to convince the other regional members that we
are up to the job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2014 there was already a loose group of Python users, who had meetups once every
2 or 3 months mainly around the Kuala Lumpur area, usually attended by more or less 10 people.
As is common for any non-profit, grass-roots volunteer-driven small meetups with no
monetary or marketing support from commercial entities, these meetups were mostly
attended by the same group of people and before long you'll have organizers burning out,
running out of steam and also things to talk about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The de-facto organizer for these meetups then was Swee Meng, and I met him for the first
time at one of Singapore's PyCon. When I suggested to him an annual PyCon for Malaysia,
he was sceptical at first, given his bitter experience with user meetups. He was not convinced
that people would come, but I told him that that was beside the point. If only 10 or
20 people come, so be it. That will be our Malaysian PyCon. Either way, it goes,
that will be our learning experience, and we'll see where that leads us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since our first mini PyCon in 2014, many people have helped us, especially the
kind generosity of venue providers, like iTrain, University Malaya and
International University of Malaya-Wales. Nearly all the time we've had help
from the academic staff of the universities who use Python as a learning tool
and wanted their students to get involved in academic conferences like
PyCon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="mini PyCon MY 2014" src="https://iqbalabdullah.net/images/pycons/mini-pycon-my-2014.jpg"&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Our keynote for mini PyCon MY, &lt;a href="http://ericholscher.com/"&gt;Eric Holscher&lt;/a&gt; giving
his talk. Eric was in Kuala Lumpur for vacation and also decided to
contribute.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="PyCon APAC dinner in Taipei" src="https://iqbalabdullah.net/images/pycons/pycon-my-um-02-08-2015.jpg"&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Members of PyCon JP coming in to support our first PyCon MY in the University
Malaya&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="PyCon MY 2015" src="https://iqbalabdullah.net/images/pycons/pycon-my-2015-hello.jpg"&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Kicking off PyCon MY 2015.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="PyCon MY 2015" src="https://iqbalabdullah.net/images/pycons/pycon-my-2015-group.jpg"&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;A group picture at the end of PyCon MY 2015.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="PyCon MY 2016" src="https://iqbalabdullah.net/images/pycons/pycon-my-2016-group.jpg"&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;And the group picture at the end of PyCon MY 2016.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As if coming to a full circle, one of the keynote speakers for the first APAC in
Singapore in 2010 (Steve Holden), and another keynote speaker for the first PyCon JP in 2011
(&lt;a href="https://ziade.org/resume.html"&gt;Tarek Ziadé&lt;/a&gt;, who works remotely in the bushes of Dijon, for Mozilla)
was our keynote speaker in 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am happy to report that Tarek enjoyed his first-ever durian here in Kuala Lumpur when keynoting for us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following the model that we did in Japan, we have also set up a &lt;a href="https://pycon.my/about/pycon-my-plt/"&gt;partnership&lt;/a&gt;
in Malaysia to facilitate managing funds and also as a public-facing entity to be
responsible for managing PyCon in Malaysia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The local sponsors&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our local sponsors who have supported us until now are mostly small companies with
personal relations to one of the members of the staff, that uses Python in their
products or day-to-day operations. These companies are the most generous. They
do not sponsor large amounts, but they are always ready
to give a helping hand. I believe they are the ones who truly understand
and appreciate how difficult it is to organize such a conference and the value
that it will bring to them and the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For our 1st local PyCon, we did have big-name companies that sponsored us, like
Amazon Web Services (AWS) and &lt;a href="https://www.braintreepayments.com/"&gt;Braintree&lt;/a&gt; a 
subsidiary of PayPal. However, the young and still inexperienced Python crowd in Malaysia
might not be a compelling reason yet for them to continue sponsoring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;PyCon APAC in Kuala Lumpur&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For 2017, after proposing the APAC community, we have been
selected to hold the responsibility of having PyCon APAC 2017 in Kuala Lumpur,
which will be held in August.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I would like to take the opportunity to highlight here is the
wonderful work the community has done to bring PyCon APAC 2017, from
universities, student volunteers, local companies and most of all the
people that make up the community itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally in the Malaysian context, I believe we need more makers or
programmers in our ecosystem. I feel that we focus too much on the
business side of things, with "business-focused" conferences like
match-making or raising venture capital. But these are all moot without the
actual people and know-how to build what we want to sell. PyCon MY is
that small ripple we're making to have a positive contribution to the
overall builders and programming ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the title of being a regional conference, we now have the clout to invite
successful technology practitioners from overseas to give talks and share their
insights and ideas with the local crowd. This will hopefully spark interest and motivate
them to further improve their skills and knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Changing the world one PyCon at a time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through PyCon, the community also tries to practice common ground principles
based on universally accepted ideas and ideals. All regional or local PyCons which request
grants from the PSF &lt;a href="http://pyfound.blogspot.jp/2012/12/psf-moves-to-require-code-of-conduct.html"&gt;are required to have a &lt;em&gt;Code Of Conduct&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; that governs how the organizers manage the conference, &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; 
also how the attendees behave and interact with one another during the conference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These Code Of Conduct (CoC) reflects the values of the community and what they think
is important. Not all talks during PyCons are about programming, web frameworks
or libraries: Some of them are about the experiences of the speaker walking the
path to become a female developer in an industry widely regarded as male-dominated,
or the need to have more diversity and how it's achieved through free community
training programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Focused groups like PyLadies (a Python group focused on women),
DjangoCon (Conference focused on the Django framework) and SciPy
(Conference for the users of Python in academics and science
fields) also all contribute to these same ideas and ideals while adding more
spice to the already vibrant Python community. In all this PyCon is the general
conference that tries to cover many usages of Python.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following the spirit of the community at large and the values and ideals that we
try to have, for APAC this year and for the first time in the history of PyCon in Malaysia,
we are trying a few new things, such as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Financial Aid&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tie up with Women Who Code (WHC)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Having the conference at a commercial conference venue&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reducing waste&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Subsidized ticketing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Financial Aid, tie-up with WHC and subsidized ticketing all aim to increase
participation from underrepresented groups who could not have attended the
conference due to financial reasons, or also from female tech communities, which
historically have little participation in tech conferences locally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So in a way, PyCons are not &lt;em&gt;only just&lt;/em&gt; a technical conference that you might
expect from practitioners of a certain technology: It's also sort of a social
movement. Although in PyCons you do have booths for companies the commercial
aspects are very much watered down (as opposed to RISE or Web Summit).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the PyCon and its culture blooming in this part of the world, I
hope it will continue to be a place Pythonistas regardless of experience
continue to meet, exchange ideas, interact and grow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In essence, the aim of a conference like a PyCon, similar to the experience museums
or art galleries offer is to enlighten you and transform you into a different person intellectually
from the person that you were before attending the conference. In the context of
conferences, this is mostly achieved from the human interaction that you've
achieved by listening to and discussing talks and interacting with other attendees.
These transformations do not have to be huge leaps. Knowledge transfers take
time and require us to work on the new information many times in our minds before we can fully
appreciate and understand it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Changing the world starts here, by us, one good idea at a time and through one PyCon at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:fn01"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://softwareengineering.stackexchange.com/questions/27207/why-was-pythons-popularity-so-sudden"&gt;Why was Python's popularity so sudden?&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:fn01" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:fn02"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/"&gt;Python Software Foundation, a non-profit in the US that holds the
intellectual rights of Python&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:fn02" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="2017"></category><category term="pycon"></category><category term="japan"></category><category term="malaysia"></category><category term="apac"></category><category term="community work"></category><category term="kuala lumpur"></category></entry><entry><title>Disunity via Schools</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/posts/2017/05/disunity-in-malaysian-schools/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-05-28T11:40:00+09:00</published><updated>2017-05-28T11:40:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabdullah.net,2017-05-28:/posts/2017/05/disunity-in-malaysian-schools/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;My thoughts after listening to BFM's TALKBACK THURSDAY: UNITY IN SCHOOLS&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The question of Malaysia's schools not doing its part in fostering unity among
Malaysians have been brought up again due to TN50&lt;sup id="fnref:Ref1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:Ref1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, and Business FM did a program to
source opinions from the general public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I followed the podcast on &lt;a href="http://www.bfm.my/talkback-thursday-unity-in-schools.html"&gt;BFM's TALKBACK THURSDAY: UNITY IN SCHOOLS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was an enlightening podcast that puts light on the thoughts and feelings of the
general public on where they think the schooling institutions in Malaysia should
head in the context as a tool to promote social unity. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Education_in_Malaysia"&gt;Education in Malaysia&lt;/a&gt; for a 
quick primer on the history of schools in Malaysia, or search for &lt;a href="https://www.google.co.jp/search?q=controversy+vernacular+schools+malaysia&amp;amp;oq=controversy+vernacular+schools+malaysia&amp;amp;aqs=chrome..69i57.6788j0j7&amp;amp;sourceid=chrome&amp;amp;ie=UTF-8#q=pros+and+cons+of+vernacular+school"&gt;controversy of vernacular schools 
in Malaysia&lt;/a&gt;
for some more background reading. The &lt;a href="http://penanginstitute.org/v3/resources/articles/statistics/714-demographics-of-a-diverse-malaysia"&gt;Penang
Institute&lt;/a&gt;
also has data on the diverse demographics of children attending the different
schools. &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tony_Pua"&gt;Tony Pua&lt;/a&gt; also
&lt;a href="http://educationmalaysia.blogspot.jp/2007/03/national-vs-vernacular-schools.html"&gt;wrote&lt;/a&gt;
about vernacular schools with insights on how the vernacular school
educationists look at the rhetoric of their schools being the reason for our
disunity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The current times question the difference&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By and large, the callers supported a single-stream school, but many with
caveats, such as pointing to the failures of the so-called national school to be
to be regarded as a symbol of excellence and is part of to blame for the rise of
so-called vernacular schools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Twitter poll by BFM also suggested that the majority who took the poll
supported a single-stream school:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="BFM's Poll for Single Stream School" src="https://iqbalabdullah.net/images/bfm-single-stream-school-unity.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have my thoughts on schools in Malaysia, and their perceived position as a
tool for national unity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why is education a partisan issue?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Education for our children, by itself, is a subject that we should all agree on. &lt;em&gt;All&lt;/em&gt; of us want the best for our children. We want them to have
good grades, enjoy school life, eat nutritional food at school and grow up a
happy, compassionate, intelligent and balanced child. But this issue now has become a partisan
issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am also sure that we all agree that as a nation, a good education for our children is an
an important part of building the future of our nation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, it has become a partisan issue when we take things which are not directly
related to education that aims to develop our children into balanced human
being, such as racial or religious identity into the equation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Racial or religious identity is exclusive to a particular person or group in the society
and these are the things that put us apart instead of bringing us together.
When we bring these identities to the public sphere and relate to them it will
of course, creates exclusivity and if it's something that not all of us can strive to be (like
race for example) then it will eventually create resentment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, there is absolutely nothing wrong with being a Dayak who is a Buddhist
a half-Thai half-Chinese Christian or a Javanese half-Bajau Muslim. All are
Malaysians and all want a better future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the context of our children what is important is that they know that these people 
exist in our society. They are our neighbours, the people that we see at shops, buy things
from, and sell things to. They are the ones whom we should help when they ask for
help, and they are also the ones who will help us when we need help.
They too want their children to grow up compassionate, intelligent and healthy
member of society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unless we can scientifically prove that excellence is born in a certain race, 
it doesn't make any sense to insist a person of a certain skin colour is
only eligible to run a certain public school. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of trying to satisfy nonsense demands and requirements that do not
improve the education level of our children, our public education should 
refocus itself on what is universally important to the growth of a child to become 
a young adult capable of thinking for herself what is good for her future, 
regardless of skin colour or faith.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The public school focus is on education, and not just a tool to unite society&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look at it another way: The current rhetoric that we're seeing also
says that part of the blame for our national disunity is on schools, but when in fact schools in
Its pure form should only be focusing on giving education to our children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The subject of national unity is &lt;em&gt;beyond&lt;/em&gt; our public schools and doesn't stop
there. Our 7-year-old child starting her formal education doesn't care what skin
colour she is, or what colour her new friend that'll be sitting next to her in
class will be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Disunity is not a problem that the schools started&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every child when born doesn't know what race or religion is. If they know that
they are &lt;em&gt;different&lt;/em&gt; from other people and should only stick to their kind the time 
they get to primary school, then the problem of disunity has started even before
getting to the schools. How would we expect schools to solve a problem which it
did not start?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't make our public schools one of the scapegoats of our inability to get our
act together, and don't expect the schools to solve a problem it did not
start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Focusing on good education and it's resources&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To achieve the level of education that we expect for our children requires us to
step back and reassess the ability of us to educate them the way we want them to
be. It is a fool's errand to say that we want the best when we are only willing
or able to move forward at a mediocre level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having capable teachers, and teachers who can focus only on teaching without
being burdened with administrative tasks is a no-brainer and I know we are aware 
of the need to focus and fix these problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One other aspect that has not been discussed though is the fact that we're
spreading our resources thin due to political pressure based on racial or
religious identity instead of educational needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, if a child wants to learn a particular language, why would she
need to go to a vernacular school to do so? Why shouldn't we allow &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; our children to learn these different languages at any
school that they go to?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only obvious reason this is happening is that we don't
have enough capable teachers to go around all of our schools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It does not make rational or scientific sense to say we need a different
school stream just to learn a language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of having teachers assigned to different schools all over the
country, we should have a lesser amount of schools. The different languages, or
subjects that are being taught differently at vernacular schools should be
made available and taught at all the schools that we have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What works at the better schools should be shared and emulated among other
schools, increasing the education level bar evenly across all our schools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Robin, one of the callers pointed out that vernacular schools strive because they do
offer something or maybe even do something better which is missing from the national schools.
We should figure this out, and emulate them in all our schools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It makes sense to have a single-stream school, where everyone can learn all
these different languages with everyone else. We will have a single budget, and
a single focus on education, practicing best practices learned via a single way to run
all our schools, with less overhead burden due to the different wants or
political needs that have nothing to do with a good education. Our teaching resources will be
more focused on teaching rather than being bogged down by non-educational matters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within the public education sphere, languages should be regarded as just
another tool to communicate and to educate our children, and are
just subjects to be learned instead of them being symbols of racial or religious
identities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Mixed signals: It's confusing and it's insane&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Judging from the perspective that our general public is viewing our school
system, we're not doing very well. Most of us complain that our children are
being burdened by more and more things to learn, and at the same time, they are
not getting to know one another any better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Year in and year out, we focus on the amount of &lt;em&gt;As&lt;/em&gt; that our children get, how
many did not get the scholarship that they wanted, how many couldn't speak good
English, and how they are getting more and more polarised day by day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the fact is in essence we're not changing the way we're teaching our
children. We think we educate them by adding all these new information
and subjects at school for them to pass exams, and we think we're giving them
"education", but are we?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we read the news of children killing themselves because they did not get
the results that they wanted, we raise our hands and say what have we done? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But we continue to demand as if this is the only way forward and complain
when there are not enough places in the universities because tens of thousands of
other children also received more &lt;em&gt;As&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same goes for putting the schools as a scapegoat for our disunity. We say we want
our people to unite and be treated as one and as equals, but when we say all our
schools should be one and all our children learn under a single roof, we raise
our hands and shout and say that &lt;em&gt;we need to protect culture&lt;/em&gt; and it's &lt;em&gt;racism
and discrimination&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are just making our children confused by saying something and doing something
else. They will just grow up cynical and untrusting of the adults they see, and
worse, they will grow up &lt;em&gt;into&lt;/em&gt; those same adults.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, sixty years down the road when we started with our current formula of
education, have we achieved in terms of quality or strength among our society
that we wanted to achieve at that time? Just judging from what our society is
debating right now, it does not seem so. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we expect different results now, but without changing the approach we have been
taking all this while, we are insane!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Our multiculturalism does not die with the schools.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It dies when we only care about our lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remove all references to a particular language or race type of school, 
from vernacular schools, the Malay College to the MRSM schools by MARA&lt;sup id="fnref:footnote1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:footnote1"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 
schools and make all these schools accessible without prejudice to any child of Malaysia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we want to play divisive politics and call out each other by their skin
colour, fine. But leave our children and &lt;em&gt;their&lt;/em&gt; schools out of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:Ref1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://mytn50.com/?language=eng"&gt;TN50&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:Ref1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:footnote1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ironically &lt;strong&gt;Majlis Amanah Rakyat&lt;/strong&gt;, despite it's name, doesn't seem to
consider non-bumiputras as &lt;em&gt;rakyat&lt;/em&gt; to be helped as its mandate is focused only on helping bumiputras&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:footnote1" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="2017"></category><category term="malaysia"></category><category term="education"></category><category term="current affairs"></category><category term="national unity"></category><category term="bfm"></category></entry><entry><title>Malaysia's Brain Drain Dilemma</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/posts/2017/01/the-malaysian-brain-drain-dilemma/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-01-28T11:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2017-01-28T11:00:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabdullah.net,2017-01-28:/posts/2017/01/the-malaysian-brain-drain-dilemma/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;My take on the Malaysian brain-drain dilemma&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is the original article which was published on 28th Feb 2017 in The Malay Mail Online
titled &lt;a href="http://m.themalaymailonline.com/what-you-think/article/believing-in-malaysias-future-and-potential-iqbal-abdullah"&gt;Believing in Malaysia’s Future and
potential&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://m.themalaymailonline.com/malaysia/article/the-other-side-of-malaysias-brain-drain-story"&gt;This&lt;/a&gt; 
article concerning Malaysia's brain drain phenomena on The Malay Mail Online 
brought me thinking on this fine Saturday morning on the 1st day of the
New Lunar Year, and I want to write about what I think of the &lt;em&gt;Malaysian Brain Drain Dilemma&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Malaysia spends time, money and effort to attract Malaysians overseas to return
to Malaysia and contribute back to the country. The idea of getting people to
contribute to the development of the country is on the right track: Heck, it's
the only track that we have! There are no alternatives to &lt;em&gt;not
wanting people&lt;/em&gt; to contribute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, I do not see the point of getting &lt;em&gt;Malaysians to Malaysia&lt;/em&gt; to achieve that. I feel the narrative of showing better lives for
Malaysians who returned home after years away, or Malaysians who succeeded
&lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; they left home is missing the point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;In the 21st century you can be anywhere and still contribute&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, improvements in infrastructure, information technology and travel make
it possible for any of us to be anywhere on this planet. In 8 hours you
can be in Helsinki or if you spend 30 hours, you can be in Buenos Aires. You can
communicate via email, share information on websites and discuss ideas face-to
face via Hangouts or Facetime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People who want to contribute to something are passionate about what they do and 
will know that they want to contribute. The missing piece is the effort that we
spend to identify these people, reach out to them and connect them to like-minded
people or institutions that can help them amplify their contributions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TalentCorp says they have approved 4000 people within 5 years since
2011. Malaysians overseas are estimated at 1 million people, which translates to
only 0.004%. Is 1000 per year of people enough to contribute? Is 0.004% an
acceptable acceptance rate after 5 years? Are we doing too little, or is this too much?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps TalentCorp's mandate is to identify and attract talents with skills that
can only be utilized if they are present in the country like surgeons to do
surgery. But we know contributing to something is more than that, and we need all the help
we can get, not only from the sciences but also from engineering and arts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also must not forget the homegrown talents and people that are doing
wonderful jobs. Overseas Malaysians have different backgrounds, ideas and
approaches to the same problem we all have and these differences are what we
want to be accessible to our homegrown talents. They can learn from each other,
improve and make something better together. Creating the missing piece of connecting
these dots between locals and abroad Malaysiams is where we should put more effort in,
regardless if the overseas talent will be coming home or not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The writer checking email in front of Mont Saint Michel" src="https://iqbalabdullah.net/images/montsaintmichel.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a picture of the writer checking his email taken in front of Mont Saint Michel&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Home is where the heart is&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second part is the most important factor of all: Where we call home. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Home is not where we were born. Making a place home is a self-conscious
decision based on the different situations, personalities and opportunities of any
given individual. This should and must be the overarching target for any 
returning program that we want to carry out: &lt;strong&gt;Making Malaysia home.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once someone calls a place home, the good and the bad will be taken in stride.
It is human nature to better their own home, for themselves and the generations
to come, and when we can get people who want to contribute calling Malaysia
their home, it will be a sustainable success story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, based on the article above, some individuals would return 
to Malaysia because they did not find the bed or roses they thought were waiting
for them wherever they were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Who cares if there’s corruption and crime in Malaysia? I just go back, make
heaps of money, and then live in a condo with proper security. Solved. Whereas
here, I’m just an average Joe, and I’m struggling just to keep my head above
water".  - See more at:
&lt;a href="//m.themalaymailonline.com/malaysia/article/the-other-side-of-Malaysia's-brain-drain-story#sthash.Z6zLaSYD.dpuf"&gt;http://m.themalaymailonline.com/malaysia/article/the-other-side-of-malaysias-brain-drain-story#sthash.Z6zLaSYD.dpuf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These people do not call Malaysia their home. Making money is their intention,
and when there are better opportunities elsewhere, they move on. What we should
focus on for the long term are the stayers, the builders and the committed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given this is what we agree to, to make Malaysia home, the next big question is: 
&lt;em&gt;How do you convince people to call Malaysia their home?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, let's think of &lt;em&gt;what makes a good home?&lt;/em&gt;. You would not want to
live in a home that is fighting all the time. You do not want to live in a home
that is wrapped in poisonous polluting gasses. You &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to live in a home that
is peaceful, clean and conducive to health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We should accept and understand that the universal values that attract human beings 
with a purpose applies and this is where we should concentrate our effort: 
The values of justice, fairness, equality, fair reward for hard work, 
a genuine effort for betterment, a chance to better oneself, rule of law: 
Similar to the so-called &lt;strong&gt;The American Dream&lt;/strong&gt;, a slogan that made
America is the place to be for all people having dreams of a better future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We do have an upper hand over overseas Malaysians to call Malaysia home, as they 
have family, roots and an eternal love for Malaysian food. But we should not take 
those for granted. More things need to be done. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;And then it's not only Malaysians&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's face it: Globalisation means people, capital and goods will move around at
a much easier and faster pace than it has ever before. Our competition is no
longer our neighbours like Singapore, Thailand or Indonesia, but it's New York,
Rio de Janeiro, Beirut, Paris or even Banjul. It's not countries anymore but cities: 
Cities now try to attract the best people from anywhere around the world to come and live there.
If people do not want to stay in Kuala Lumpur, all of these other cities will
woo them and are more than happy to welcome their wealth, expertise and passion.
The faster we realize this, the better it is for us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point here is that when we get our head around at aiming to make Malaysia our
home, the universal values that apply to a good home will apply and attract many more
people, regardless of nationality, colour and creed. This is what makes a
country great: People believing in it and wanting to participate in its growth
process. All these believers will come, and call Malaysia their home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And when we reach this stage, we will be on a different playing field altogether. 
It will no longer be what race we are, or who are sons of soil, or where we are
from but we will be in the race to be the best in the world. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe in this vision of our country, where everyone wants to make it their
home and believe in its potential and future. In the end, this is what we
mostly desire now: Believers in our country, its potential and its future.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2017"></category><category term="current affairs"></category><category term="malaysia"></category></entry><entry><title>Yang di-Pertuan Agong is not "king".</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/posts/2016/12/agong-and-not-king/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-12-05T10:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2016-12-05T10:00:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabdullah.net,2016-12-05:/posts/2016/12/agong-and-not-king/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Malaysians do not have a king, but the Yang di-Pertuan Agong.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This was an email I sent to The Star on referring to the Malaysian Head of State
using the appropriate proper noun. It was not published.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I refer to your news article on 16th Nov 2016 with the title
&lt;a href="http://www.thestar.com.my/news/nation/2016/11/16/king-and-queen-attend-parade-of-thanks-for-14th-yang-dipertuan-agong/"&gt;King and Queen attend parade of thanks for 14th Yang di-Pertuan
Agong&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every time I read in your paper news about our Yang di-Pertuan Agong
and your paper refers to him as King and his consort as Queen, I
cringe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We Malaysians do not have a king. Spain has a king. Sweden has a king.
Monaco has a king. Japan has an emperor, while we Malaysian have our
Agong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a unique position even within this small world of ours. A king
generally implies a hereditary line of monarchs with power passed down
between families. Our Yang di-Pertuan Agong is elected and even has a
deputy which are not from the same family unlike kings which have
crown princes which are nearly the time sons of the same family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our passports also refers to the Agong as "His Majesty the Yang
di-Pertuan Agong of Malaysia".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Agong is not a hereditary role, is a proper noun and referring to
a specific and important role in our country. There is no equivalent
english translation for our Agong, as the English language came from a
region and time where a ruler is a king and have absolute powers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an alternative, you can refer to our Agong by addressing him by
"His Majesty" and his consort as "Her Majesty", or even the "Supreme
Commander of the Malaysian Armed Forces" if you'd like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As one of the few English papers with wide circulation in the country,
we can assume that your good paper will be read by many foreigners
visiting our shores. It would be best to give the proper introduction
to them concerning our Yang di-Pertuan Agong, by correctly referring
to our unique elected Head of State lest they'l have the impression
that the Federation of Malaysia have "kings".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><category term="2016"></category><category term="current affairs"></category><category term="malaysia"></category><category term="politics"></category></entry><entry><title>Let's stop saying hello</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/posts/2016/11/no-greeting-condo/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-11-09T08:30:00+09:00</published><updated>2016-11-09T08:30:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabdullah.net,2016-11-09:/posts/2016/11/no-greeting-condo/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The cutting edge on living together in a condo&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So I saw this on Twitter:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Letter to the editor on no greeting condo" src="https://iqbalabdullah.net/images/no-aisatsu-twitter.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A person wrote to the local newspaper telling the story of his condominium making a new rule to not allow greeting each other. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the story goes, one of the parents was telling the management committee that they were teaching their children to not greet anyone that they know, and since it's difficult for children to know whether a person is an occupant of the condo complex or not, the parents were asking the committee to make a rule to not allow greetings in the condo complex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, one of the older occupants was also saying that since their greetings always go unanswered and don't make them feel any better, why not we just stop with all the greetings altogether? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so the occupants have reached an agreement not to greet each other, and now they need to publish the new rule so that the rest of the condo complex occupants know and follow it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2016"></category><category term="everyday life"></category><category term="japan"></category><category term="comedy"></category></entry><entry><title>あいさつをやめましょう。</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/ja/posts/2016/11/no-greeting-condo/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-11-09T08:30:00+09:00</published><updated>2016-11-09T08:30:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabdullah.net,2016-11-09:/ja/posts/2016/11/no-greeting-condo/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;日本の近所付き合いの最先端だそうです。&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Twitterで以下の投稿を見かけたが、&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Letter to the editor on no greeting condo" src="https://iqbalabdullah.net/images/no-aisatsu-twitter.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;読んでビックリした。教育上だからと言って周りの社会まで巻き込んで近所の付き合い方（というか防犯対策上も問題になりそうだが）を根本的に変えちゃう
というのはどうかと思うけど。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;「マンション内のあいさつは禁止」&lt;/strong&gt; という張り紙でもだすのでしょうか。やっぱりこっちも理解苦しんでいるわ。&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2016"></category><category term="近所付き合い"></category><category term="マンション生活"></category><category term="喜劇"></category></entry><entry><title>Can Entrepreneurship Be Taught?</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/posts/2015/03/can-entrepreneurship-be-taught/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-03-12T10:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2015-03-12T10:00:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabdullah.net,2015-03-12:/posts/2015/03/can-entrepreneurship-be-taught/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;My story on learning how to be an entrepreneur&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.mymagic.my/about/"&gt;MaGIC&lt;/a&gt;'s &lt;a href="https://cherylyeoh.com/"&gt;Cheryl Yeoh&lt;/a&gt; 
gave her views on whether entrepreneurship can be taught in &lt;a href="http://bit.ly/1FbbK89"&gt;The Star, March 3
2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would like to add my comments, based on my different experiences and motivation from the context of teaching entrepreneurship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My views on entrepreneurship are purely based on experience. I did not have any
formal education on entrepreneurship, (I am trained as an engineer) nor my immediate family members have been examples of entrepreneurship. As it is now, out of my siblings and my parents, only I am currently earning a living from a business that I run.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From these experiences of mine, I believe that entrepreneurship is not dissimilar to fado, the traditional music of Lisbon. You can nurture the feel for fado (having many fado houses and public performances, as well as exposure from the media), you can learn how to write and perform fado (by watching and learning from the great fado maestros on how they perform their art) but alas you cannot teach fado. There will be pointers on techniques which you can pass on, but you can't teach "how to fado". This sentiment is echoed by all the great fado players, and I am very sure it is the same for any art form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which brings me to an interesting take on entrepreneurship that I believe in: That it is a mix of science and art forms. It is science from the way that you measure success: Because it is a business, you can measure what is the profit margin, or the earnings per stock, or valuation or market capitalization. Based on these numbers, so-called investors will tell you if a business is growing, stagnating or losing ground and if you should invest in a certain business. The more these numbers show a positive trend, the better it is for the business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But how do you get to that measurable success is, at the very best, not measurable. Best practices from a certain market, when brought over might not work the same way in a different market. The best we have is the franchise types turn-key model which implements best practices but by different people, but even that still doesn't work the same all the time everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Successful entrepreneurship requires more than understanding the numbers and theories like what we learn in a business school sitting for an MBA. Business and entrepreneurship are two different animals: A successful entrepreneur can create a successful business, but a successful business might not create the successful entrepreneur.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In that context, I very much agree with what Cheryl has pointed out: The Stanford Technology Ventures Program (STVP) does not look at purely the numbers of startup companies created. A performance indicator to gauge if entrepreneurship is taking hold based on the number of companies created is nonsensical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It doesn't make sense and it doesn't show anything other than, well, the amount of companies created.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A top-down approach stating a target of so and so amount of companies should be created to boost entrepreneurship, which I have noticed we, from time and time again prefer to do, will only lead to more insubstantial companies and nonsense capital distribution, with very little impact on creating resilient and successful entrepreneurs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, a much more pedal-to-steel indicator that directly connects to the would-be entrepreneurs will serve this purpose better. We can learn from Stanford on how they use the amount of students who oversubscribe to their courses or the ratings the students have given. Entrepreneurship is a career path; For me, it is a way to live.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We should treat entrepreneurship like any other career path. Students from young should know that being an entrepreneur is also a viable career, like being a policewoman, a mechanic, a pilot, a lawyer or a doctor. But unlike a policewoman who enforces the law a pilot who flies a plane, an entrepreneur creates value to the public and her customers by solving problems with a purpose that will be sustainable for her, her family and her employees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in the end, it is up to the entrepreneur why she decides to become one. For the pilot, it might be the blue skies and travelling the world. For the policewoman, it might be because of her sense of justice and conviction. This reason or purpose, in the end, is the single most important driver behind successful entrepreneurs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knowing wanting to achieve this goal and being able to do so by creating sustainable value is the first step of being an entrepreneur. Unfortunately, this cannot be taught. What we, as a society and the education system, can best do is to say that these goals can be achieved and have tangible tools like infrastructure and access to human and monetary capital accessible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like any good artist, give them the tools, step back and watch them work! &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2015"></category><category term="current affairs"></category><category term="malaysia"></category><category term="entrepreneurship"></category></entry><entry><title>So you're CEO</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/posts/2012/10/so-you-are-ceo/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-10-21T10:20:00+09:00</published><updated>2012-10-21T10:20:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabdullah.net,2012-10-21:/posts/2012/10/so-you-are-ceo/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Being CEO is a maximizing your balancing act and not a zero-sum game&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;On my flight on Singapore Airlines from Changi to KLIA I read an interesting
interview of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tan_Suee_Chieh"&gt;Tan Suee Chieh&lt;/a&gt; in The Straits Times Opinion section (Fri Oct 19
2012 edition).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In that interview, Tan talks about going "from well to good", and how this is a departure from how he usually did things before going on board as head of Singapore's NTUC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find this excerpt of the interview particularly interesting:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"I worked in commercial companies for 25 years. My job as CEO of a listed
company has always been to maximise profits. And my obligation is to give as
little as possible to the customer, subject to market share and profit
considerations. But my job at NTUC Income is to give as much as possible to the
policyholders as a group. It's two different mindsets."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, as an outfit out to make a profit everything is subject to profit considerations. But I feel that being CEO or the leader even for an unlisted, 3-person family business, with obligations to &lt;em&gt;give as little as possible to the customer&lt;/em&gt; while in the same stride talking about &lt;em&gt;maximising profits&lt;/em&gt; is misguided at best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is this how our Asian CEOs in this part of the world generally think what their mandate is all about?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my role as a leader, in a nutshell, my work boils down to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Give good returns to shareholders by maximizing profits, as they are the ones taking the risk to put up the money for the business in the first place.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stand in the customer's shoes and give them as much as possible making them happy, which will get you more money to do point 1 above. You are where you are because your customers are. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Empower your employees and then stand out of their way so that they can please your customer which will lead to point 2 above and consequently to point 1.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It should not be (and it never is) a zero-sum game. Maximising profits does not mean giving as little as possible to your customer.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2012"></category><category term="asian business"></category><category term="leadership"></category><category term="entrepreneurship"></category></entry><entry><title>KTMB should follow right train of thought</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/posts/2009/12/ktmb-should-follow-right-train-of-thought/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2009-12-25T10:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2009-12-25T10:00:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabdullah.net,2009-12-25:/posts/2009/12/ktmb-should-follow-right-train-of-thought/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Why KTMB still in the red&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This was an &lt;a href="http://bit.ly/TxHZCy"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt; I sent to The Star on Christmas Day 2009 about how terrible
KTMB Komuter service was. I was pretty pissed at that time. I don't understand
how KTMB cannot understand this very simple thing on providing a decent service to
it's customers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After I sent the email, I got a call from The Star while I was in Jaya Jusco in
Malacca and the person wanted to confirm that what I wrote about KTMB's aim of
getting MYR1 profit was correct before they published it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ON DEC 12, I took KTM’s Ekspres Sinaran Pagi from KL Sentral bound for
Singapore, which was originally scheduled to depart at 8.30am.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I waited at the terminal, the departure time was rescheduled to 8.40am
and again to 8.55am. The train finally departed at 9am, and we reached
Singapore one hour later than the scheduled time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the KTM Komuter from Mid Valley to Seremban (Rawang-Seremban route) on
Dec 22, we waited from 9.10pm and the train arrived only at 9.40pm. We
finally reached Seremban at around 11pm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;KTMB customers waiting at the Mid Valley station resigned themselves to the
waiting, and some even opened up their work on the cement floor and tried to
get something done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The electronic signs at the platform were confusing and did not show correct
information. We were not notified the reason for the delays.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Certain passengers were inconsiderate, refusing to allow passengers to alight
first before boarding, pushing ahead with their big backpacks, having their
handphone ringtones on full volume and refusing to give up their seats for a
blind mother and child who boarded in Serdang.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The experience of taking the Komuter from Mid Valley to Seremban has left me
tired. I felt I have grown older by 10 years and my will to live has gone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two points that I wish to share with KTMB:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In today’s economy, KTMB must realise that it is not an operator of
      railways. It must realise that it is a service provider, not much different
      from taxis or retail outlets. It just so happens that the service provider
      called KTMB is providing its service through railways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The money is in transporting people, not goods. If KTMB truly wishes to
   reach its stated target of even RM1 profit, stay there or even go beyond
   that, it has to understand that the service of transporting people, in a
   timely and comfortable manner, will be the single most important revenue
   provider.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are important concepts that everyone in KTMB must realise and
understand, from the CEO down to the person maintaining the ticket machines
at the stations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From a layman’s point of view KTMB has great potential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With highways being built every day and airline flights getting cheaper, it
is more important than ever that KTMB realise its potential as a service
provider, and the strength that its assets hold. KTMB owns tracks and
stations which are not affected by traffic yet that go direct to the heart of
towns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Malaysia will change like other developed nations, where more and more people
commute to work from out-of-state into Kuala Lumpur. We see this happening
right here and now, and it is inevitable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are too many cars on the roads and everyone is tired of traffic jams in
the city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everything is in place that will allow KTMB to be the leading transportation
service provider. All that KTMB needs to do is to leverage these assets and
by being reliable and punctual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be reliable and on time do not require KTMB to change its rolling stock
immediately, nor does it require it to send its staff to Tokyo to study how
JR (Japan Railways Group) does its job. All KTMB has to do is ride its own
trains and make notes of what it’s doing right and what it’s doing wrong, and
then fix them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IQBAL ABDULLAH, 
Petaling Jaya.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><category term="2009"></category><category term="current affairs"></category><category term="malaysia"></category><category term="public transportation"></category><category term="letters to the editor"></category></entry><entry><title>Meritokrasi ubat pahit tetapi mujarab</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/posts/2001/08/meritokrasi-ubat-pahit-tetapi-mujarab/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2001-08-09T10:20:00+09:00</published><updated>2010-10-04T18:40:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabdullah.net,2001-08-09:/posts/2001/08/meritokrasi-ubat-pahit-tetapi-mujarab/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;An opinion letter published in Utusan Malaysia concerning meritocracy in schools.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is an opinion letter I wrote when I was staying in Higashi-Kawaguchi, fresh
out of college during the summer of my first job at Sun Microsystems. It was published in 
&lt;a href="http://ww1.utusan.com.my/utusan/info.asp?y=2001&amp;amp;dt=0809&amp;amp;pub=Utusan_Malaysia&amp;amp;sec=Rencana&amp;amp;pg=re_06.htm"&gt;Utusan Malaysia&lt;/a&gt;
on 9th August 2001:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saya percaya dengan tahap teknologi dan capaian media kita sekarang, seseorang
itu tidak perlu lagi lulus universiti untuk mendapatkan kebolehan baik di dalam
bidang tertentu, terutamanya sains maklumat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tetapi pokoknya ia bukan sahaja mengenai minat atau kebolehan, tetapi mentaliti
dan disiplin pelajar Melayu kita. Oleh sebab untuk membaiki mentaliti dan
disiplin pelajar Melayu ini juga, maka Perdana Menteri, Datuk Seri Dr. Mahathir
mencadangkan pelaksanaan sistem meritokrasi (walaupun sebagai eksperimen) mulai
sesi pengambilan pelajar akan datang.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Setelah melalui kehidupan belajar di universiti (walaupun saya belajar di salah
sebuah universiti awam di Jepun), saya dapat memahami jika dikatakan, walaupun
kelulusan yang baik itu penting, tetapi sebenarnya pembelajaran di univerisiti
adalah lebih daripada itu. Jika dibandingkan dengan kursus-kursus lain, kita
sedia maklum memang pembelajaran di universiti lebih susah dan membebankan,
kerana salah satu sebabnya ialah terdapat subjek-subjek lain yang langsung tiada
kaitan dengan kursus seseorang itu, tetapi ia harus diambil bagi memenuhi syarat
kreditnya untuk menamatkan kursus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tetapi tidakkah kita terfikir, jika sistem pendidikan kita mahu menghasilkan
seorang programmer atau seorang jurutera, mengapa tidak dari awal lagi gaya
pembelajaran di univerisiti diubah? Ini kerana institut universiti itu bukan
hanya mahu menghasilkan seorang programmer atau jurutera tetapi seorang
profesional semua bidang, yang berdisiplin dan berwibawa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tidak ada gunanya jika seseorang itu boleh menulis kod program yang cukup bagus
tetapi masih tidak memahami sejarah negaranya, oleh itu tiada sikap patriotik.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bertahan selama empat tahun di universiti dan berhadapan dengan segala macam
masalah, kebanyakan bergantung dari dalam diri sendiri dan selebihnya dari luar,
telah mengajar saya pelbagai perkara. Bukan tidak pernah semasa di universiti,
saya menangis seorang diri di belakang dewan kuliah kerana rasa terlalu tertekan
untuk mendapatkan gred bagus dalam satu subjek yang saya langsung tidak
mempunyai minat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bukan tidak pernah dalam empat tahun itu saya terfikir untuk berhenti sahaja
belajar di universiti kerana saya rasa minat saya tidak ada dalam bidang
tertentu, dan saya percaya kebolehan diri untuk melakukan apa yang saya minat.
Pernah semasa saya di tahun dua, saya berdiri di hadapan pensyarah selama lebih
dua jam, sambil diherdik dan dimarahi kerana tugasan saya yang dikatakannya
tidak berapa elok walaupun saya bersengkang mata lebih tiga hari tiga malam
untuk menyiapkannya. Pada masa itu hanya Tuhan sahaja yang tahu betapa sakitnya
hati saya dan betapa mahu saya pulang saja ke Malaysia kerana tidak tahan lagi
dengan satu sistem pembelajaran yang apa-kenapa-dan-bagaimananya langsung
tidak saya fahami.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Semasa saya di tahun empat, pernah saya diminta oleh pensyarah untuk melakukan
pembentangan mengenai kajian yang sedang saya lakukan. Setelah membuat
pembentangan tersebut, saya telah dimarahi kerana pembentangan saya itu tidak
berapa memuaskan. Pensyarah tersebut berkata, Kenapa kamu tidak lakukan
seperti saya, dengan membuat nota dan rajah yang teliti, seperti saya lakukan
setiap kali kuliah? Saya berkata oleh kerana profesor adalah seorang
profesional dalam bidang tersebut, maka perkara itu sudah menjadi satu benda
yang biasa, dan tidak pula bagi saya.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tetapi beliau kemudian menjawab, Habis, kenapa kamu hadir di univerisiti?
Bukankah untuk menjadi seorang profesional? Saya terdiam. Memang benar kata
pensyarah saya itu.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Setelah memasuki alam pekerjaan, saya dapati sebenarnya apa yang diutamakan oleh
orang Jepun di sini bukanlah kelulusan peperiksaan ataupun kemahiran (walaupun
ia penting) tetapi kendiri dan sikap seseorang itu terhadap pekerjaannya.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kerana belajar itu suatu perkara yang tidak akan habis sehinggalah kita mati,
maka kemahiran dan pengetahuan masih boleh kita timba walaupun setelah tamat
universiti. Tetapi sikap itu harus dipupuk dari muda, bak kata pepatah,
Meluntur buluh biar dari rebungnya.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Empat tahun di universiti mengajar kita untuk bersikap profesional, berdisiplin
untuk mengikut sistem, tidak anti-establishment, sabar, gigih, bersemangat dan
bercita-cita tinggi. Apa yang tersurat di atas segulung ijazah itu tidak dapat
menggambarkan seribu satu perkara yang tersirat. Tetapi malangnya jika dilihat
fenomena pelajar Melayu kita di universiti sekarang, mereka seperti hilang punca
tentang mengapa mereka di sana.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mungkin pelajar Melayu kita, seperti juga remaja Jepun sekarang, yang terlalu
mewah atas titik peluh generasi sebelumnya, tidak faham akan apa itu erti
kesusahan, lantas hilang fokus dan lupa akan matlamat diri sebagai pemuda-pemudi
bangsa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jika seperti selalu, jalan keluar yang senang dan cepat diberikan, sehingga
kiamat pun, orang Melayu kita akan tetap mencari jalan mudah untuk keluar
daripada segala macam masalah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tidak semua orang boleh menjadi genius kerana itu adalah anugerah Tuhan, tetapi
semua orang boleh bersikap profesional dan berdisiplin, kerana sikap itu boleh
dipupuk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kita harus mempunyai keyakinan terhadap pemuda-pemudi Melayu kita yang walaupun
tanpa bantuan kerajaan, masih boleh menunjukkan kelayakan cukup bagus sehingga
boleh memberi persaingan kepada kaum-kaum lain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lebih baik sistem meritokrasi ini dilaksanakan dalam keadaan kita berkuasa dan
boleh mengubahnya semula kepada sistem kuota jika ia tidak mencapai matlamat,
daripada ia dilakukan pada masa kita tiada kuasa dan tidak berkuasa untuk
memperbetulkan keadaan. Pelaksanaan sistem meritokrasi ini, walaupun ia pedih
dan pahit, tetapi saya percaya ia akan memberi ubat yang paling mujarab bagi
pewaris bangsa dan negara kita. Tabik saya kepada bakal mahasiswa Melayu yang
sanggup menerima cabaran ini. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IQBAL ABDULLAH, Kawaguchi, Jepun.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><category term="2001"></category><category term="current affairs"></category><category term="malaysia"></category><category term="education"></category><category term="letters to the editor"></category></entry></feed>