<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Iqbal's Weblog - 2016</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/en/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/feeds/2016.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://iqbalabdullah.net/en/</id><updated>2016-12-05T10:00:00+09:00</updated><entry><title>Yang di-Pertuan Agong is not "king".</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/en/posts/2016/12/agong-and-not-king/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-12-05T10:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2016-12-05T10:00:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabdullah.net,2016-12-05:/en/posts/2016/12/agong-and-not-king/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Malaysians do not have a king, but the Yang di-Pertuan Agong.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This was an email I sent to The Star on referring to the Malaysian Head of State
using the appropriate proper noun. It was not published.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I refer to your news article on 16th Nov 2016 with the title
&lt;a href="http://www.thestar.com.my/news/nation/2016/11/16/king-and-queen-attend-parade-of-thanks-for-14th-yang-dipertuan-agong/"&gt;King and Queen attend parade of thanks for 14th Yang di-Pertuan
Agong&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every time I read in your paper news about our Yang di-Pertuan Agong
and your paper refers to him as King and his consort as Queen, I
cringe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We Malaysians do not have a king. Spain has a king. Sweden has a king.
Monaco has a king. Japan has an emperor, while we Malaysian have our
Agong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a unique position even within this small world of ours. A king
generally implies a hereditary line of monarchs with power passed down
between families. Our Yang di-Pertuan Agong is elected and even has a
deputy which are not from the same family unlike kings which have
crown princes which are nearly the time sons of the same family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our passports also refers to the Agong as "His Majesty the Yang
di-Pertuan Agong of Malaysia".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Agong is not a hereditary role, is a proper noun and referring to
a specific and important role in our country. There is no equivalent
english translation for our Agong, as the English language came from a
region and time where a ruler is a king and have absolute powers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an alternative, you can refer to our Agong by addressing him by
"His Majesty" and his consort as "Her Majesty", or even the "Supreme
Commander of the Malaysian Armed Forces" if you'd like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As one of the few English papers with wide circulation in the country,
we can assume that your good paper will be read by many foreigners
visiting our shores. It would be best to give the proper introduction
to them concerning our Yang di-Pertuan Agong, by correctly referring
to our unique elected Head of State lest they'l have the impression
that the Federation of Malaysia have "kings".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><category term="2016"></category><category term="current affairs"></category><category term="malaysia"></category><category term="politics"></category></entry><entry><title>Let's stop saying hello</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/en/posts/2016/11/no-greeting-condo/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-11-09T08:30:00+09:00</published><updated>2016-11-09T08:30:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabdullah.net,2016-11-09:/en/posts/2016/11/no-greeting-condo/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The cutting edge on living together in a condo&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So I saw this on Twitter:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Letter to the editor on no greeting condo" src="https://iqbalabdullah.net/en/images/no-aisatsu-twitter.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A person wrote to the local newspaper telling the story of his condominium making a new rule to not allow greeting each other. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the story goes, one of the parents was telling the management committee that they were teaching their children to not greet anyone that they know, and since it's difficult for children to know whether a person is an occupant of the condo complex or not, the parents were asking the committee to make a rule to not allow greetings in the condo complex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, one of the older occupants was also saying that since their greetings always go unanswered and don't make them feel any better, why not we just stop with all the greetings altogether? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so the occupants have reached an agreement not to greet each other, and now they need to publish the new rule so that the rest of the condo complex occupants know and follow it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2016"></category><category term="everyday life"></category><category term="japan"></category><category term="comedy"></category></entry></feed>