<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Iqbal's Weblog - 2018</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/en/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/en/feeds/2018.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://iqbalabdullah.net/en/</id><updated>2018-10-21T18:40:00+09:00</updated><entry><title>Digital IDs for Malaysia</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/en/posts/2018/10/digital-ids-for-malaysia/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-10-21T18:40:00+09:00</published><updated>2018-10-21T18:40:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabdullah.net,2018-10-21:/en/posts/2018/10/digital-ids-for-malaysia/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Digital IDs to verify identities will propel us forward&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is an article on my opinion concerning the plan for digital IDs for
Malaysians. It was not published&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Bringing back the idea&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since Minister Gobind brought back the idea of a &lt;a href="http://www.bernama.com/en/news.php?id=1651523"&gt;digital ID for
Malaysians&lt;/a&gt;, we are
seeing a healthy debate going on concerning the feasibility or even
the need of a national digital ID. I would like to also contribute to
this debate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;I am who I say I am&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The internet was originally designed in such a way that it's
"stateless", which basically means it has no memory. This means that
if you visit a website and come again 3 seconds later that website
will treat you like a totally new person on your second and subsequent
visits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is obviously an issue when you need to get things done: You
won't have shopping carts, Instagram timelines, or friends on Facebook
because the internet can't differentiate between you and your
grandmother.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along the way innovative ways was invented to workaround this
limitation, such as "cookies" and sessions, which has evolved to
produce the user registration, username and password combination that
we so much love today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One problem with this method is that no one is vouching for you: You
come up saying "this is who I am, and I'm vouching for myself that
this is true". For Facebook or Instagram where the most complex every
day use case is sharing pictures of cats or your rented Chanel
handbags, this is all fine, but if you need to do anything more that
comes with responsibilities and social consequences like registering
your new born child, renewing your business
license or making a loan application, someone needs to make sure that
you are who you say you are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This should be the MAIN and ONLY purpose a national ID program should
perform: Verifying that you are who you say you are or in other words,
creating a "platform of trust" as termed by Minister Gobind.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;I don't trust you, but I trust that person that you trust&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By design and nature of the internet I cannot trust you, but the funny
thing is I will trust something that you also trust. This "something"
naturally will fall to some central authority like the government,
because they are the issuer of identities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is interesting to note that this concept is not new: We are already
using it in the HTTPS/TLS scheme (the padlock that you see in your
browser address bar to make sure you're accessing a secure site)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Private entities like banks are also able to connect to this central
system. Using the state-issued ID card, you can access the myriad of
private services
that connects to the state and can verify that you are who you are. Once they
know who you are, you are then authorized to carry out actions based on the
services that you're currently accessing, like making money transfers
from your bank account, or renewing your driving license.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A platform of trust based on officially sanctioned national-ID to
directly verify identity is more meaningful than indirect methods such
as sending SMS to mobile numbers that proves possession than identity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, the central authority should not (or MUST not) have access
to whatever you're doing online once you're passed the verification
phase. What you do, once you're verified, will only be between you and
the services you're utilizing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;A paper photostated IC is not "verification"&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current way of doing things by the majority of Malaysians in regards of
identity verification is broken to say the best. We take our physical
ID and make physical paper copies of it to sign-up for services from
opening bank accounts to subscribing to mobile plans. This is far from
secure nor it is an effective form of identity verification and can be
easily abused. We have read of many cases where someone else have
signed up for something which the real owner of that identity doesn't
know of and instead is paying for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An online platform of trust will help us reduce the likelihood of abuse by
taking away the physical aspect of the identity verification, which will also
lead to a more efficient workflow since data can be processed much
more easily than physical record.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But having said that, we also must understand and appreciate this: No
technology is perfect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;It's not if but WHEN&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fear that a central authority being hacked is justified and it is
a risk which needs to be mitigated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the technology context, we mitigate this risk by increasing the hurdles
before any hacked data is made usable, and minimize the damage &lt;strong&gt;WHEN&lt;/strong&gt;
(and not if) there is data breach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We do this by ensuring that the hacked data is unusable without a
second factor, such as an encrypted physical ID which is not connected
in any way to the central system. Those physical ID can also be locked
by passwords which are stored on the ID itself, and supposedly known
only to the ID holder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means that if an aspiring hacker wants to steal the data of the
citizens of Malaysia, they need to hack the central system, and steal
30 million ID cards AND also figure out the password to access that
physical device. At the same time, third-parties like banks which access
the central system to verify identity will not have the identity verification
information on them, which means if the banks are hacked, the hacker will
know how much money an account has but will not know who that account
belongs to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Estonia's E-Residency programme&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am enrolled in the Estonian E-Residency program, where the state
vouches for you and issues a state sanctioned ID card which you can
use to connect to state services online. The ID card does not have my
picture on it, and is not valid as a self-identification document in
the physical world. Estonia's E-Residency system employs the same
scheme for personal verification and authentication I have explained
above. It is also used by her 1.3 million citizens to access
government services, other than e-residents (which can access the same
services too!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thousands of kilometers away, day or night, in my living room or in my
favorite local cafe, I can sign agreements, check the status of my
applications and operate my business and get on with my life without
having to wait in line or getting stuck in traffic because all the
different moving parts that I need to interact with know with a very
high probability and confidence that I am who I say I am.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, I know 1.3 million people versus Malaysia's 30 million people is
a huge difference, but that is the beauty of technology: You can scale it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;So..&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do we need this? I truly believe so. In fact, I believe it is inevitable. The
technology is already there, it is open and we have no need to invent
anything new. The actual example of implementing it state wide is also
there (Estonia) as well as any leanings or know-how. It has been done
and it has been proven.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The right to be connected online is now starting to be accepted as a
universal human right. Coupled with the constant business needs to get
better efficency and savings, being able to do work and business
online will become more and more of a necessity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Allowing us to do business and deal with bureaucracy online will free up
tremendous amount of time that we can use to enrich ourselves in many other
ways. This is in the end what technology is supposed to be about:
Empowering us human beings by allowing us to regain back our most
valuable resource: time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more relevant and important question is when?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously as a country of limited resources there is the question of
prioritization. I will leave that question as a homework to be
answered by our elected representatives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But before go forth, an important issue we must address before we
embark on this project, as &lt;a href="https://www.malaymail.com/s/1683682/dear-politicians-digital-ids-are-a-terrible-idea"&gt;pointed out by Ms. Erna Mahyuni in her
piece&lt;/a&gt;,
is that Malaysia does not have a good track record of enforcing
privacy laws, and top top that off a very low understanding of privacy
and privacy rights. This is a larger issue which should be addressed,
regardless of having a national digital ID or not, as it is effecting
us all, right here, right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I believe the creation of a national digital ID as a base for a
platform of trust to empower citizens of Malaysia is inevitable in
order to continue to being relevant and competitive.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2018"></category><category term="current affairs"></category><category term="malaysia"></category><category term="estonia"></category><category term="tech"></category></entry></feed>