<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Iqbal's Weblog - 2022</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/en/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/en/feeds/2022.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://iqbalabdullah.net/en/</id><updated>2022-07-02T16:42:00+09:00</updated><entry><title>The future is still not here for the Python Software Foundation (PSF)</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/en/posts/2022/07/the-future-is-still-not-here-for-the-psf-2022/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-07-02T10:30:00+09:00</published><updated>2022-07-02T16:42:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabdullah.net,2022-07-02:/en/posts/2022/07/the-future-is-still-not-here-for-the-psf-2022/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The 2022 PSF Board elections is closed and counted. I failed to make the cut, and so wrote my thoughts down in this post.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;The future is still not here for the Python Software Foundation (PSF)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In June 2022 &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/iqbalabd/status/1535270196654575616?s=20&amp;amp;t=KkwPKOrVlpC2fPUy26v8_g"&gt;I ran for the third time&lt;/a&gt; for a seat in the Python Software Foundation (PSF) Board of directors. Initially I wasn't thinking of running, but &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/di_codes"&gt;Dustin Ingram of PyPi&lt;/a&gt; encouraged me to run again at the last minute and so I did. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;It didn't quite work out...&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of, a big congratulations to the newly elected and returning Board members! They are&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DawnWagesSays"&gt;@DawnWagesSays&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/simonw"&gt;@simonw&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/kushaldas"&gt;@kushaldas&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/jezdez"&gt;@jezdez&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I was also not elected again this time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the &lt;a href="https://thefortunate.blog/psf-board-2022-nomination-statement.html"&gt;agenda and vision that I put forth for the 2022 elections&lt;/a&gt; remain the &lt;a href="https://thefortunate.blog/diversification-is-the-future-for-the-psf.html"&gt;same as the 2020&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/2021-python-software-foundation-board/nominees/iqbal-abdullah/"&gt;2021&lt;/a&gt; elections, out of the total 4115 votes given to all the nominees, I only had 250 which is 6.08%. This was less than the 7.34% which I had in the 2021 elections. As a note I managed to only get 4.78% votes in the 2020 elections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also had 5% less people who were eligible to vote, down to 1459 from 1538 in the 2021 elections. Those that &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; vote though basically remained the same, at around 39% voter turnout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But for me, the most worrying thing is that with Marlene exiting the Board, we are now &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/CodenameTim/status/1542895106918961154?s=20&amp;amp;t=KkwPKOrVlpC2fPUy26v8_g"&gt;down to only two non-US/Europe directors on the Board&lt;/a&gt; out of 13. This doesn't look well if we want to talk about global representation and diversity. This condition slowly pushes us to a defensive narrative if questioned on our diversity and inclusion efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;But other things &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; go well...&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, other things did go well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I announced my self nomination for the Board, I also sent an &lt;a href="https://groups.google.com/g/pycon-organizers-apac/c/3J9rLJT8LAo"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt; to our APAC PyCon Organizers group urging for the rest of us to run alongside myself. This time I had another two influential contributors from my East Asia and South East Asia region to run with me, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/georgically1"&gt;Georgi&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/darjeelingt"&gt;Kwon Han&lt;/a&gt;. We didn't have nominees from our region in the past other than myself, and I believe as little impact as it might have been, my work in promoting diversity, representation and involvement within the APAC community and the PSF have increased the visibility, interest and inspired others to also run for the Board elections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of a particular note which I am proud to mention is the election results for Georgi. Although she was not elected, she did manage to get 6.29% of the total votes and was just shy of 14 votes to be elected in her first election to the Board. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interest to serve the community through a seat on the Board continues to be strong. We had a record number of 26 nominees, similar to what we had in 2020. This is more than the 19 nominess we saw in 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am also really happy to see that &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/cmaureir/status/1542877794778087430?s=20&amp;amp;t=8qJW1ooFrjgWzPI4YZiOpw"&gt;Cristián&lt;/a&gt; continues to run advocating representation for Latin America, our Spanish speaking compatriots and i18n efforts for the PSF.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There seem to be more nominees which have openly championing diversity in representation within the PSF Board of directors and less reliance to the PyCon US for financing, more than we have seen in the past&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;To sum up&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be honest, I did not expect to get elected this time because nothing much has significantly changed since the last two elections, either on my end or through any initiaitves by the PSF or the community to address the perceived lack of global representation on the PSF Board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be fair though: At least since 2020 more people have pointed out to the problem of a skewed representation within the Board. Some say it's the way the elections are done, and there are &lt;a href="https://discuss.python.org/t/psf-Board-election-reform/4527"&gt;suggestions on changing the way the voting is done&lt;/a&gt; for the elections. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the 2020 elections, the PSF too has also put out a short and medium term &lt;a href="https://pyfound.blogspot.com/2020/06/2020-python-software-foundation-board_26.html"&gt;plan&lt;/a&gt; to address this issue, which includes collecting location data on the voters themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a nominee for the past three elections, having data on who our voters are is important. Without it, I do not know who I am talking to, and what is important to them. Even if the &lt;a href="https://www.zdnet.com/article/programming-languages-python-developers-now-outnumber-java-ones/"&gt;8 million or so Python users&lt;/a&gt; think any one person should be on the Board, if that person could not convince the 500 or so people who will be voting, then there's very slim chance of you getting elected. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our work within the D&amp;amp;I WG also has led us to data collection to understand better who our community members are, although I suspect not many of them are voters (yet). From preliminary data, general apathy towards the work the PSF does and the elections in general (i.e why does it concern me?) seems to be the biggest hurdle we need to overcome to get more of our non-US/Europe community members to participate. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it is, I can also honestly say that taking part, being active and visible to the US Python community specifically seems to be a pre-requisite to be succesfull to be elected to the PSF Board. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Not only as Board member&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what happens to you, the avid Python user/developer/organizer that is burning with the desire to help your fellow community members, but so happens to be having a life in an area which &lt;em&gt;is not&lt;/em&gt; the 10% of the world's landmass that is the United States or Europe?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many other ways for us to contribute and make an impact. Some good suggestions are listed &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/get-involved/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; on the PSF's website. If you're interested in a very specific cause, there are the &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/committees/"&gt;PSF Working Groups&lt;/a&gt; (also know as committees) that you can ask to join and participate in. I am currently participating in the Trademark WG and the D&amp;amp;I WG, which has given me knowledge from diversity policies, trademark law, other Python communities in the world and opportunities to learn from those more experienced and knowledgeable than myself. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But from experience, I'd think &lt;strong&gt;the best way to make an impact is to join or start something within your own local area&lt;/strong&gt;. We never have enough people to organize meet-ups, start a local conference, do weekend hackathons, guide new comers to the community, or write and maintain software for the use of the local community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Credits go to&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, &lt;strong&gt;big thank yous&lt;/strong&gt; to (in no particular order)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;James&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dustin&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;David&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Marc-Andre&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Georgi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kwon Han&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thomas&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wei Lee&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yuggun&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Aiko&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kamal&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the D&amp;amp;I WG&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PyCon JP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the kind folks on Twitter and LinkedIn that liked and shared my contents&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the folks who voted for me&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and the PyCon APAC Organizers group&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;for supporting my nomination and sharing my vision. I am only human, and forgive me if I missed you in the credits roll above. I am only human, and
I'm sorry I dissapointed all of you due to my own inabilities. But we are only human, and maybe we can try again in the future.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2022"></category><category term="psf"></category><category term="politics"></category><category term="community work"></category><category term="elections"></category><category term="python community"></category></entry><entry><title>A guide to the PSF board elections 2022: How should you decide?</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/en/posts/2022/06/guide-for-the-psf-board-elections-2022-how-to-decide/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-06-22T22:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2022-06-22T22:00:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabdullah.net,2022-06-22:/en/posts/2022/06/guide-for-the-psf-board-elections-2022-how-to-decide/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A record number of people have raised their hands to serve on the PSF board this year. How do you choose? Who do you choose?&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Choosing the nominees for the PSF board elections 2022&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;First of all, a disclaimer: I am also &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/2022-python-software-foundation-board/nominees/iqbal-abdullah/"&gt;running for a seat&lt;/a&gt; this year.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're seeing a &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/2022-python-software-foundation-board/nominees/"&gt;record number of nominees&lt;/a&gt; raising their hands to serve on the board of the Python Software Foundation (PSF) this year. This is a very good thing for the Foundation and our community, but it might be daunting for you who will be choosing the people you want to see in the board. I believe that most of the eligible voters have voted a few times, but there are some of us who will be voting the first time. Regardless, I hope this post will give you a hint on how to decide which nominees you should choose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;First, it's about you&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, first and foremost, it's about &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt;. How do &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; see the PSF? What future would &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; like the PSF and the Python community to have? What do &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; think?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having some time to sit down and think of what I wanted to see for the PSF, I have decided to focus on these three, which are loosely based on my &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/2022-python-software-foundation-board/nominees/iqbal-abdullah/"&gt;nomination statement&lt;/a&gt; and my &lt;a href="https://thefortunate.blog/diversification-is-the-future-for-the-psf.html"&gt;thoughts on the previous election&lt;/a&gt; which I took part in:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Opportunities&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe this is what we can never have enough of. We need more opportunities for the different types of people in our community to participate in the many different things, from technical stuff to community building, that we have and revolves around the Python language. Having a chance to get through the door is the first step to grow and later on open more doors for the people after one selves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How would a nominee increase opportunities within our community? This is a question I ask myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Diversity&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Python community is colourful. It's not only painted in the colours of black or white, the Americas or West Europe, or technical and PEPs. Does our board, that represents us through the PSF truly represents us? Do we have the diversity in the people, diversity in the skills, diversity in the thoughts and ideas that will make us stronger and go further? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Diversity is closely related to the opportunities above but distinctive on it's own. I believe a diverse community will naturally create more opportunities and vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Experience&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, &lt;a href="https://wiki.python.org/moin/PythonSoftwareFoundation/DutiesAndResponsibilitiesOfDirectors"&gt;the PSF board has many duties and responsibilities&lt;/a&gt;. I would want people who are capable and understand what it takes to work together in an organization to represent us and help our community and our language to evolve and grow. This requires experience. Having said that, having the same group of people to continuously represent us does not help to create opportunities nor a diverse representation, so how do we balance the above two with experience? For me, this is a fine line that is the most difficult part to decide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;There are of course others...&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are of course other valid points that we can think of. Perhaps you would like to see a PSF that has bigger financial resources and can help more communities. Or a PSF that puts more effort in solving packaging issues for Python. Or a PSF that for once and for all solve the issue of a "slow" Python. Or even a PSF that has ambitions to send a rocket to Mars because that's where you believe the future of mankind is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless of what they are, having an idea of what you'd think is important to &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; will be the first step.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Then, it's about the nominees&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, we move on to the nominees. These are the people that will work with you to achieve the important things you have decided above. So what do we look for in these nominees? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, for starters we have their nomination statements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way I do it, I will assign some amount of points to each nominee depending on the four items I focus below. There is a maximum amount of points that each item can have, depending on how important a particular item is. The maximum number of points that a nominee can have is 10. At the end of it, I will choose any nominee with 6 or more points to the board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can always tweak the points system to your taste. You might want more points for a particular item that is close
to your heart, and less for those which you think are less important to you. You might want to lower the bar by choosing
anyone that has more than 4 points, or raise the bar to anyone that has more than 8 points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are the four items I focus on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Who are they&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will of course be the first thing that I will read. Who are they? What's their name? Have you heard of them before? What community are they from? What's their background? Nearly all nominees will do a good job explaining this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Maximum 1 point)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What do they want to achieve&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where you can see if a particular nominee is trying to push agendas which are similar or close to those that you think are important above. Why are they running? What are they trying to change? What are they trying to improve? Who are they representing?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an important part of the nomination statement, so we should read these carefully, and should be a big consideration on your part when choosing a nominee. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Maximum 3 points)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Their progression&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A nominee's progression represents their history in working towards a particular point in time. What have they been doing up until this point? Were they committing code to GitHub as a core dev? Were they presenting quality ideas to the community? Were they fund raising to help other communities to do their work?  Were they organizing people for PyCon's? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember that serving on the PSF board is not the only way to have impact on the community or the language. Maintaining a library is one way to do it. We already have the &lt;a href="https://peps.python.org/pep-0013/"&gt;steering council&lt;/a&gt; that will have a more direct impact on how the language evolves. &lt;a href="http://kit.pyladies.com/en/latest/prospective/index.html"&gt;Organizing your local PyLadies&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://organize.djangogirls.org/"&gt;DjangoGirls&lt;/a&gt; chapter will have more impact in opening doors to underrepresented people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also the many &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/committees/"&gt;PSF Workgroups&lt;/a&gt; with various objectives that you can participate in, having a more direct way to have an impact and help shape the future of Python.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, I put progression higher than their reason to run. In my line of work, we have this saying: "What matters is not what the customers are saying; It's what they are doing". More importantly though, it always makes me happy to see the many achievements my fellow compatriots have achieved, and helps me want to do more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Maximum 4 points)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What other people have to say about them&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we have the section where someone else will have a good word or two for the nominee. Acknowledgement of work and character by a different person is always a positive thing. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If that acknowledgement is done by someone you know, respect and trust, then perhaps this is a nominee which you would want to pay attention to. More often than not, it usually means that the nominee holds values that you too consider important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Maximum 2 points)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;What if there are no nominees that champion what you think is important?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then it's time for you to be a nominee yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Finally, it's about the process&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But above all, enjoy the process of having to choose between many different capable people within our community to represent us in the board. The way the voting process works, you can choose multiple people to the board. The nominees that gets the top votes will be elected to the board equal to the amount of vacant seats for that particular year. As the voter, you have multiple choices to support different agendas and nominees and it's not a "this-or-that" choice. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, it's a free democratic process, and like any other free democratic process, you are free to choose whomever you like. You never have to justify your choices to anyone else other than yourself, and you are not obliged to answer who you choose even if asked. Your vote is secret, and only known to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So before we part ways, I hope you don't think too hard, enjoy the process and enjoy the opportunity to take part. The above thoughts on how to choose a nominee are only mine, and you should have yours too. Choose whoever you feel like choosing. There will always be next year for you to vote again, and I am confident that there will be continued interest to help out with the PSF board in the many more years to come, and many more nominees to choose from. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, this is what matters most.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2022"></category><category term="psf"></category><category term="politics"></category><category term="community work"></category><category term="elections"></category><category term="python community"></category></entry><entry><title>Nomination statement for the 2022 Python Software Foundation Board Election</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/en/posts/2022/06/psf-board-2022-nomination-statement/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-06-10T22:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2022-06-10T22:00:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabdullah.net,2022-06-10:/en/posts/2022/06/psf-board-2022-nomination-statement/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;My self-nomination statement for the 2022 Python Software Foundation (PSF) Board Election&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Who&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My name is &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/iqbalabd/"&gt;Iqbal Abdullah&lt;/a&gt;. I am a Malaysian, based in Japan and have been actively participating with the Python communities around the East Asia and South East Asia region. I understand fluently three natural languages and am a basic at one. I am a Supporting and Managing Member of the PSF.
I make a living by running a small technology company called &lt;a href="https://lalokalabs.co/en/"&gt;LaLoka Labs&lt;/a&gt; which I am also happy to mention uses &lt;strong&gt;a lot&lt;/strong&gt; of Python.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I first ran for a seat on the PSF board in &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/2020-python-software-foundation-board/nominees/iqbal-abdullah/"&gt;2020&lt;/a&gt;. I received 11th place out of 26 nominees with 4.78% of the votes. Looking at the results, I realized how little representation the PSF has from the different communities in other parts of the world beyond the United States and Western Europe, even though a significant portion of community work and possible opportunities for technical expertise would come from these communities. I wrote an essay about in my blog titled &lt;a href="https://thefortunate.blog/diversification-is-the-future-for-the-psf.html"&gt;Diversification is the Future for the PSF&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ran again in &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/2021-python-software-foundation-board/nominees/iqbal-abdullah/"&gt;2021&lt;/a&gt; with a clearer direction on what I think is needed for the PSF, based largely on my thoughts from that essay. To sum it up, in 2021 I wanted to:
- Increase representation and acknowledgement of the diverse communities that we have
- Increase the portion of the PSF revenues from non-PyCon US, specifically from non-US and non-Western Europe sources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For 2021, I came in 7th place with 7.34% of the votes. It was an improvement, but not good enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will be my third time running for a seat on the PSF board. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not much has changed within the past one year, and my objectives running for a seat in 2022 still remains the &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/2021-python-software-foundation-board/nominees/iqbal-abdullah/"&gt;same as 2021&lt;/a&gt;. I believe these are still relevant and needed to be worked upon. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, I am hoping to use my platform as a PSF director, if elected, to accelerate interest within the East Asia and South East Asia region on what and how we can contribute more to the Python community. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need more people who can be community leaders to give ideas and manage programs, more people that understand how to manage money to support open source, more people that understand law to help support our intellectual properties, and most importantly, more people that care.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other than help managing cooperation between the different Python and PyCon organizing communities within the Asia Pacific region, I am still serving as a member of the  &lt;a href="https://pyfound.blogspot.com/2020/12/announcing-psf-diversity-and-inclusion.html"&gt;Diversity &amp;amp; Inclusion (D&amp;amp;I) Working Group&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/committees/#trademarks-work-group"&gt;Trademarks Work Group&lt;/a&gt; of the PSF.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was the chairperson for &lt;a href="https://pycon.my/2015/08/31/pycon-my-2015/"&gt;PyCon MY in 2015&lt;/a&gt;, the chairperson for &lt;a href="https://pycon.my/2017/09/01/pycon-apac-2017-its-a-wrap/"&gt;PyCon APAC 2017&lt;/a&gt; and served on the board for &lt;a href="https://www.pycon.jp/committee/english.html"&gt;PyCon JP&lt;/a&gt; from founding in 2013 until 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was one of the panelist for the &lt;a href="https://lalokalabs.co/en/events/diversity-inclusion-workgroup-panel-at-pycon-apac/"&gt;panel discussion for the Diversity and Inclusion WG for PyCon APAC 2021&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Saying thank you&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was also given the honour to give a keynote for &lt;a href="https://hamburg.python.pizza/"&gt;Python Pizza Hamburg&lt;/a&gt; where I addressed the issue of open source volunteers being taken for granted and more acknowledgement (including helping them with more money and paying our share) that needs to be done. This is an important topic close to our hearts, so within another business I founded, &lt;a href="https://blog.xoxzo.com/en/tag/annual-open-source-grant/"&gt;we annually give out grants to open source projects, including to the Python Software Foundation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;If you've read this far&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For 2022, &lt;em&gt;even if not elected&lt;/em&gt;, I will be happy if I can get a higher result than my previous elections. This will at least mean that the message and ideas I'm trying to bring has gained some traction among the people that matters and are invested: Those of you who will be voting. I can then bring this along with me in the future and tell my story to anyone that wants to listen with hope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the very least, regardless of the results, I hope my experience in participating in the elections will open the minds and hearts of the people around me, and doors for them, as by the people that have gone before me have done for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2022"></category><category term="psf"></category><category term="politics"></category><category term="community work"></category><category term="elections"></category><category term="python community"></category></entry></feed>