<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Iqbal's Weblog - 2024</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/en/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/en/feeds/2024.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://iqbalabdullah.net/en/</id><updated>2024-06-17T21:30:00+09:00</updated><entry><title>Getting Started With Python in Malaysia</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/en/posts/2024/06/getting-started-with-python-in-malaysia/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-06-17T21:30:00+09:00</published><updated>2024-06-17T21:30:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabdullah.net,2024-06-17:/en/posts/2024/06/getting-started-with-python-in-malaysia/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Tips and resources to start learning Python without spending (much) money if you're in Malaysia&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Python Is The Rage Now&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read &lt;a href="https://x.com/reviewbyyasmin/status/1802258242342736212"&gt;on the internet&lt;/a&gt; about people wanting to join Python and data science-related courses offered by government-led agencies. These courses are mostly free (funded by taxpayers) but have limited space, and some are restricted to those under 30 years old.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upskilling isn't just for the young, and learning Python shouldn't require significant financial investment. You can start immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Python is a versatile language used in various domains, from powering the internet and &lt;a href="https://huggingface.co/learn/nlp-course/en/chapter0/1"&gt;developing AI applications&lt;/a&gt; to being utilized in &lt;a href="https://datatas.com/does-nasa-use-python/"&gt;outer space&lt;/a&gt;. Its popularity and success stem from being &lt;a href="https://github.com/python/cpython"&gt;open-source&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/downloads/"&gt;free to download and use&lt;/a&gt;, which lowers barriers to its use and improvement by the public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Learning Python For Free&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I first picked up Python in 2002 (v1.5.2) without spending a sen, and so can you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are numerous online resources available for free to start learning Python. Sifting through them all might be overwhelming, so I'll suggest a few built on another reason for Python's popularity: its community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Learn By Doing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had tasks I wanted to automate, like pulling data from a website or sending SMS from my computer. You likely have your projects in mind. Spend a few minutes considering them, and start exploring how you can accomplish these tasks with Python. Hands-on experience is the fastest way to learn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some free materials that will be useful:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn To Program. For Free: Al Sweigart's &lt;a href="https://inventwithpython.com"&gt;Invent With Python&lt;/a&gt;
    I met Al at PyCon PH in 2018. He writes books for beginners and generously makes these materials available for free. His book &lt;a href="https://automatetheboringstuff.com"&gt;Automate The Boring Stuff With Python&lt;/a&gt; is particularly useful for generating ideas on what you can build with Python.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Join a &lt;a href="https://t.me/belajarpythonbot"&gt;local Telegram group "BelajarPythonBot"&lt;/a&gt; maintained by &lt;a href="https://x.com/k4ml"&gt;Kamal Mustafa&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://x.com/AmirulAbu"&gt;Amirul&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trey Hunner's &lt;a href="https://www.pythonmorsels.com/newsletter/"&gt;Python Morsels newsletter&lt;/a&gt;
    I met Trey at PyCon US. He writes newsletters and &lt;a href="https://x.com/treyhunner"&gt;tips on X&lt;/a&gt; about Python. His material might be intermediate level, but skimming through it can help familiarize you with technical terminology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Learn By Listening&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learning a new spoken language effectively often involves listening to it spoken. Initially, you might not understand the words, but getting a feel for the language's rhythm and expression can enhance your understanding when you start practicing. The same applies to programming languages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mike Kennedy's &lt;a href="https://talkpython.fm"&gt;Talk Python To Me&lt;/a&gt;
    I met Mike at PyCon PH in 2024. His podcast features interviews with people working with or using Python in various capacities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Learn Python Together&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next step is motivating yourself to continue learning and upskilling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After familiarizing yourself with the syntax and technical language, meeting people can provide motivation and reduce the likelihood of giving up after a few months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Python community is incredibly welcoming. Find a group near you and get involved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Meetups: Community members sometimes organize meetups to learn together. While there aren't many Python user groups in Malaysia, there are some related ones.&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://tfugmy.peatix.com"&gt;Artificial Intelligence And Machine Learning Malaysia User Group&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Women-driven data analytics, data science, data engineering, and ML community &lt;a href="https://x.com/WanitaData"&gt;Wanita Data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PyCons: Python conferences, known as PyCons, occur at both country levels, like &lt;a href="https://pycon.my/"&gt;PyCon MY (Malaysia)&lt;/a&gt;, and regionally, such as &lt;a href="https://europython.eu"&gt;EuroPython&lt;/a&gt; for Europe and &lt;a href="https://pycon.asia"&gt;PyCon APAC&lt;/a&gt; for Asia-Pacific.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Specific interest groups, like the women-led &lt;a href="https://pyladies.com/locations/"&gt;PyLadies&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://www.meetup.com/PyDataKL/"&gt;PyData&lt;/a&gt;, provide safe spaces for minorities within our community to learn.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meetups are often free, but PyCons usually have an entry fee. However, PyCons strive to keep ticket prices affordable or they wouldn't be considered PyCons. Most also offer travel grants and free tickets through sponsorships.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Happy Coding&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learning Python in Malaysia is accessible and affordable thanks to numerous free resources and a supportive community. By leveraging materials like Al Sweigart's books and Trey Hunner's newsletters, you can begin learning without financial strain. Engaging with the community through meetups, user groups, and PyCons not only enhances your learning experience but also provides motivation and support from like-minded individuals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Python's versatility and widespread use across industries make it a valuable skill. Consistency is crucial when learning Python or anything new. Spending an hour a day for a month is more effective than cramming 10 hours into three days. Celebrate your progress and enjoy the journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happy coding, and may your Python journey be as rewarding as it is exciting!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P.S: &lt;em&gt;Thanks to &lt;a href="https://x.com/sweemeng"&gt;Swee Meng&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://x.com/k4ml"&gt;Kamal&lt;/a&gt; for proofreading this post.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2024"></category><category term="python"></category><category term="newbie"></category><category term="learning"></category><category term="my"></category></entry><entry><title>Nominating Pythonistas For Stuff At The Python Software Foundation (PSF)</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/en/posts/2024/05/nominating-pythonistas-at-the-psf/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-05-20T09:20:00+09:00</published><updated>2024-05-23T20:27:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabdullah.net,2024-05-20:/en/posts/2024/05/nominating-pythonistas-at-the-psf/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A README to nominating your fellow Pythonistas for stuff at the PSF&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Do you know that you can nominate your favorite hardworking person or group for stuff and recognize them for their work at the PSF, and do all this for &lt;em&gt;free&lt;/em&gt;? (i.e., free as in free tea)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Acknowledge And Thank Them: Nominating Your Fellow Pythonistas&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before 2014, the Python Software Foundation (PSF) didn't have a formal nomination process or criteria. When they moved to an open membership organization (basically meaning anyone can join as a member of the PSF), they created formal processes for nomination and granting special recognition to members of its community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did an Open Space during PyCon US 2024 in Pittsburgh to exactly share my experiences and answer questions on this topic. During the closing of the conference, &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/denicholson/"&gt;Deb Nicholson&lt;/a&gt; – who is the Executive Director of the PSF – got on stage and pointed out that we've had no Community Service Award (CSA) to present this year due to a lack of nominations. With all the great things everyone is working on in any particular year, it's really difficult to think that no one deserves the CSA; so the only possible thing is that our community just aren't aware enough that they can do such nominations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;What Can You Nominate For?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's more than just the CSA. You can nominate your fellow Pythonistas for these:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PSF Fellow&lt;/strong&gt;: The PSF Fellow membership is a special membership awarded to individuals who have made significant contributions to the Python community through their work, including contributions to the development of Python, supporting the infrastructure, organizing events, and other impactful activities. PSF Fellow nominations are handled and decided upon by the &lt;a href="https://wiki.python.org/psf/FellowWG/Charter"&gt;PSF Fellow Workgroup&lt;/a&gt;. More details can be found on the &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/fellows/"&gt;PSF Fellow Membership page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PSF Community Service Award&lt;/strong&gt;: This is the CSA. It recognizes individuals or groups that have performed exceptional volunteer service for the Python community. It highlights those who have dedicated significant time and effort to improve the community through various means, such as organizing events, contributing to educational resources, or supporting community initiatives. The decision to award the CSA to an individual or a group is decided by the PSF Board. Details are available on the &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/community/awards/psf-awards/"&gt;PSF Community Service Award page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Outstanding PyLady Award&lt;/strong&gt;: This award is given to individuals who have made significant contributions to the PyLadies community, which is dedicated to promoting diversity and supporting women and gender minorities in the Python community. It celebrates those who have gone above and beyond in mentoring, organizing events, and fostering an inclusive environment. The decisions on awarding the Outstanding PyLady Award are done by the PyLadies Global Council. You can learn more about this award &lt;a href="https://kit.pyladies.com/en/latest/global/award.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PSF Distinguished Service Award&lt;/strong&gt;: This is the Foundation's highest award. The Distinguished Service Award is an offer of recognition for sustained exemplary contributions to the Python community. This award is given for actions which carry significant impact that shapes the Python world, whether through contributions of code, efforts in community action, or otherwise. As with the Community Service Award, the intention is to demonstrate that such service to the community does lead to recognition and reward, rather than to provide a direct incentive to contributors. You can learn more about this award &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/community/awards/psf-distinguished-awards/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These awards and recognitions are excellent ways to highlight and celebrate the invaluable contributions of Pythonistas around the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PSF Board Directorship&lt;/strong&gt;: Although a responsibility, not an award, nominating someone for Directorship is still meaningful. The PSF Board of Directors oversees the Foundation's activities and ensures its mission is carried out effectively. Board Directors are elected by the PSF membership and play a crucial role in strategic decision-making and governance. Read more on the &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/"&gt;PSF Board Elections page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Why Should You Nominate?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nominating someone for recognition within the Python Software Foundation (PSF) is not just a formality – it's a powerful way to celebrate and acknowledge the hard work and dedication that Python community members invest in the ecosystem. Recognizing individuals and groups:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Promotes Positive Community Spirit&lt;/strong&gt;: By acknowledging contributions, we foster a culture of appreciation and motivation, which encourages more people to get involved and contribute to the community.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Highlights Diverse Contributions&lt;/strong&gt;: Recognizing the work of different individuals showcases the variety of ways people can contribute, whether through code, community organizing, education, or advocacy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Encourages Continued Involvement&lt;/strong&gt;: Awarding community members can incentivize them to continue their efforts, knowing that their work is valued and noticed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Builds a Stronger Network&lt;/strong&gt;: Celebrating achievements helps build stronger connections within the community, facilitating collaboration and support among members.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're living in the gift economy. Gifts turn the wheels in our world. Open source is a gift. The unpaid labor that people do to support the community around open source is a gift. Welcoming people into our community regardless of age, gender, economic status or education level is a gift. Saying thank you and acknowledging our peers in the community is also a gift that pays them back. Naomi Ceder says this best in her &lt;a href="https://www.naomiceder.tech/posts/pycon_keynote_2022/"&gt;A Time of Gifts keynote&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it's crucial to ensure that the recognition process is inclusive and represents the diverse Python global community. Certain groups have been underrepresented in technology and community leadership roles. For example, the communities from my region (the East Asia, South Asia and Southeast Asia) only had 18 PSF Fellow memberships and 2 CSA recipients (one representing a group), out of around a total of 500 PSF Fellows and around 100 individuals for the CSA. That's just around 4% and 2% of the total recipients. When we consider there are around &lt;a href="https://thefortunate.blog/diversification-is-the-future-for-the-psf.html"&gt;8.2 million Python developers or users worldwide&lt;/a&gt; and the biggest growth is within my region, &lt;em&gt;that is&lt;/em&gt; underrepresentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;How Do You Nominate?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The process for nominating someone for recognition at the PSF is straightforward:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Identify the Category&lt;/strong&gt;: Determine which award or recognition is most appropriate for the individual or group you want to nominate. This could be a PSF Fellow, Community Service Award, Board Directorship, or Outstanding PyLady Award.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prepare the Nomination&lt;/strong&gt;: Collect information about the nominee, including their contributions to the Python community, specific achievements, and any other relevant details. The nomination should highlight why the nominee deserves the recognition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Submit the Nomination&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For &lt;strong&gt;PSF Fellow&lt;/strong&gt; nominations, you can submit via email. Read more on the PSF Fellow membership page &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/fellows/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For the &lt;strong&gt;Community Service Award&lt;/strong&gt;, details and submission instructions can be found on the &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/community/awards/psf-awards/"&gt;PSF Community Service Award page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nominations for &lt;strong&gt;PSF Board Directorship&lt;/strong&gt; are typically part of the annual election process. More information can be found on the &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/nominations/elections/"&gt;PSF Board Elections page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Outstanding PyLady Award&lt;/strong&gt; details can be found &lt;a href="https://kit.pyladies.com/en/latest/global/award.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;PSF Distinguished Service Award&lt;/strong&gt; details can be found &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/community/awards/psf-distinguished-awards/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Need for Better Representation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the PSF has made significant strides in promoting diversity and inclusion, such as the creation of the &lt;a href="https://wiki.python.org/psf/DiversityandInclusionWG"&gt;D&amp;amp;I Workgroup&lt;/a&gt; and granting more grants to the African and Asian communities in 2023, there is still a need for better representation from different communities around the world in terms of acknowledging the work of individuals and groups. Many regions are underrepresented in PSF leadership and recognition programs. This lack of representation can create barriers to entry for new contributors and limit the diversity of ideas and perspectives within the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To address this, we need to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Promote Awareness&lt;/strong&gt;: Increase awareness about the nomination processes and opportunities for recognition among underrepresented groups.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Provide Support&lt;/strong&gt;: Offer resources and support to help individuals from diverse backgrounds navigate the nomination process and engage with the community.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Encourage Diverse Nominations&lt;/strong&gt;: Actively seek out and encourage nominations of individuals from underrepresented regions and backgrounds.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mentorship Programs&lt;/strong&gt;: Establish mentorship programs to guide and support new contributors from diverse communities in their journey within the Python ecosystem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By taking these steps, we can ensure that the PSF truly reflects the global and diverse nature of the Python community, fostering an inclusive environment in which all contributions are valued and recognized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;What Can I Do?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plenty!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, if you're not a PSF member yet, sign up &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/membership/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. If you've done work for the community that makes you eligible to be a &lt;a href="https://psfmember.org/civicrm/contribute/transact/?reset=1&amp;amp;id=32"&gt;Managing, Contributing or Supporting member&lt;/a&gt;, make sure you're recognized as such too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, you can nominate someone! If you've been in your community long enough, I'm sure by the time you're reading this, you'll have the person(s) in mind right now. No one? Are you sure? Well, one example I can give is when I get to a new city or community, I ask a few people who would be the best person to talk to for a newcomer to get involved, and if let's say 75% of them give me the same name, then that person would probably be PSF Fellow material. You can then start by getting to know that person and talking about the work they have done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Community Service Awards (CSA) have an easier criteria to understand, but still a high hurdle to be accepted. An example is the nomination that I made for the PyCon JP Association (read more &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/records/board/resolutions/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/community/awards/psf-awards/#december-2021"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, for the charity talks event that they did to raise money for the PSF on the wake of the pandemic, which had disastrous effects on the PSF financially. Another more recent example is the recognition by the board for &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/records/board/minutes/2024-03-13/#new-business"&gt;Leonard Richardson, Lais Cavalho and Raquel Dou to receive the CSA&lt;/a&gt; for the software or community that they have built and maintained, which benefited the community at large.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Distinguished Service Award (DSA) has a much higher hurdle to clear. Since given out in 2012, only 7 people have
received it. Sometimes a CSA nomination can lead to a DSA being awarded, but that is up to the PSF Board to decide. You
can read on the reasons for the DSA to be awarded &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/community/awards/psf-distinguished-awards/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and if you have someone that you think deserves to stand as
tall as these other recepients, that please make a nomination. Nominations can be sent confidentially by email to the
PSF Board as written &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/community/awards/psf-distinguished-awards/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can of course self-nominate, but I personally find this a very difficult thing to do and very boring, so I'm not interested in doing that. It's more fun to write about other people!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, you can help increase awareness of such opportunities to recognize, acknowledge, and elevate your fellow Pythonistas through these nominations: When I'm at PyCon or a Python meetup, I've started to include the amount of nominations I've made in my self-introduction, something like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hey, my name is Iqbal. I sometimes help around here, and have nominated xxx people to the PSF Fellow and xxx for the CSA. Would you like to know more about that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and sometimes I'll be pleasantly surprised that the person I'm talking to will know the person I nominated, and that becomes a great conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have someone in mind that should be recognized but you still don't know how to do it, you can just quickly drop
me a message through my &lt;a href="https://mtd.pythonasia.org/@iqbalabd"&gt;Mastodon&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://x.com/iqbalabd"&gt;X&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="linkedin.com/in/iqbalabd/"&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt; and I'll be happy to help whatever I can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;FAQ&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During my Open Space about PSF Nominations, these are some of the questions we had:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Can you self-nominate?&lt;/strong&gt; - Yes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What's the difference between the Community Service Award (CSA) and PSF Fellow?&lt;/strong&gt; - You can read the official description of what the CSA is for &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/community/awards/psf-awards/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and the PSF Fellow &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/fellows/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. In a nutshell, the CSA celebrates particular acts of service, while the PSF Fellow membership recognizes an individual's comprehensive and distinguished contribution to the Python ecosystems and community.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What's the requirement to nominate someone for the PSF Fellow?&lt;/strong&gt; - There are no hard requirements, but contributions that clearly go beyond your casual organizer or contributor. A good place to get examples are the nomination statements themselves, which are published &lt;a href="https://wiki.python.org/moin/PythonSoftwareFoundation/FellowNominations"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for the PSF Fellow nominations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How do these nominations get decided upon?&lt;/strong&gt; - Anyone can nominate someone, but the nominations are deliberated, accepted or rejected by different groups within the PSF. The PSF Fellow nominations are decided by the &lt;a href="https://wiki.python.org/psf/FellowWG/Charter"&gt;PSF Fellow Workgroup&lt;/a&gt;, the CSA by the &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/board/"&gt;PSF Board&lt;/a&gt; while the Outstanding PyLady Award by the &lt;a href="https://pyladies.com/blog/Announcing-the-Inaugural-PyLadies-Global-Council/inaugural-pyladies-council/"&gt;PyLadies Global Council&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thank you to &lt;a href="https://x.com/cheukting_ho"&gt;Cheuk&lt;/a&gt; for reviewing this post&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2024"></category><category term="pycon"></category><category term="psf"></category><category term="community"></category></entry><entry><title>Going To PyCon US 2024 - Heading To Pittsburgh (Part 1)</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/en/posts/2024/05/going-to-pycon-us-2024-in-pittsburgh-part-1/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-05-09T22:20:00+09:00</published><updated>2024-05-27T11:50:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabdullah.net,2024-05-09:/en/posts/2024/05/going-to-pycon-us-2024-in-pittsburgh-part-1/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The first part of my journey across the world in May/June 2024.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;First Stop: PyCon US 2024 via New York&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were two events which I needed to attend in May this year:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://us.pycon.org/2024/"&gt;PyCon US 2024 in Pittsburgh&lt;/a&gt; (From May 15th to May 19th)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://latitude59.ee"&gt;Latitude59 in Tallinn&lt;/a&gt; (From May 22nd to May 24th)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem with this is that both events are only a few days apart from each other, but at totally different places on the planet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Booking Travel and Accommodations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Flights&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of these two places that I needed to go, I decided to take the &lt;a href="https://roundtheworld.staralliance.com/staralliance/EN/round-the-world"&gt;Round The World ticket from Star Alliance&lt;/a&gt; (also known as RTW) because I am an ANA member. It's actually much better deal to take the RTW ticket compared to a multi-city ticket, unless you want to go down the route of building your own flight plan through low-cost airlines. Even then, if you travel often, you might lose out on the Miles benefits if you take the multi-low-cost airlines route.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tip: The RTW ticket allows you to change your flights (add, remove or change), but try not to do that. They will charge you USD 150 every person for each time&lt;/em&gt;. If you have to change though, it's pretty easy: Just send them an email and they will figure it out for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Hotels&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Afiza handles our accommodations when we travel. She has a membership with the Marriott group hotels and her membership level gives her useful perks when we stay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I can say is that prices of accommodation have at least doubled since a year ago, while the quality hasn't changed much and depends very much on the establishment you stay at.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Packing for the Trip&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been doing multi-month travels over multiple cities, countries, timezones, and climates since 2013. Over the years, the amount that I pack has gone way down. When I started out, I called it "&lt;em&gt;Defensive Packing&lt;/em&gt;" where you get as many things as possible to handle all possibilities when you're traveling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I have transitioned to "&lt;em&gt;Aggressive Packing&lt;/em&gt;" where you get only essentials for your comfort and try to get anything else that you'd need along the way. When you're away from home for months in different cities and countries the "what ifs" pile up. 
It takes years to get to know yourself and the people you travel with to get this part right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your mileage may vary, but here's what I've got:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Essentials: Clothes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I travel, the maximum amount of clothes I bring is six nights. This requires that I go to a laundry at least every five days. Hotel laundries are &lt;strong&gt;expensive&lt;/strong&gt; (unless you're in a particular hotel in Istanbul, maybe I'll write about that one day). &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At least two pairs of shoes: One for running, and another is a pair of Dr. Martens boots. Sneakers are too painful for my feet when I walk on European cobblestones. Black boots are also useful when I need to go to a posh restaurant or business meeting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uniqlo light down. Alongside a hoodie, this combination can get me through tempreatures of as low as 14C.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A nice dinner jacket that can be rolled up and doesn't crease.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Essentials: Travel Goods&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Portable bidet. Living in Japan and around South East Asia, we take our toilet time seriously.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Portable water pot to boil water. I have a habit of not drinking cold drinks. US hotels also don't have water pots for you to boil water. Because our world mostly works on two different voltages, certain trips require me to bring two types of water boilers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Essentials: Medication and Toiletries&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't forget your medication and prescriptions. I have been so far blessed with good health, so I usually only pack painkillers, stuff like skin cream for itches, bandages, and band-aids which will come in handy if you get blisters. Anything beyond this, I usually will go to the local clinic or hospital. Exercising while travelling is an important part of my routine and is part of my effort to keep things this way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I strongly suggest you obtain travel insurance&lt;/strong&gt;. Due to travel stress or being overzealous at experiencing the local delicacies, I have had the pleasure of experiencing the local medical facilities in Bangalore, Istanbul, Madrid, Marrakech, Kuala Lumpur, and Barcelona in the past. They cost money, and some facilities actually require proof of travel insurance from you before accepting you. You'll need to pay upfront, but with travel insurance, you can claim those expenses back when you get home. &lt;strong&gt;Remember to keep your receipts!&lt;/strong&gt;
If you have a credit card, chances are there's already travel insurance that comes with your contract. Mine do, and I print out the local phone numbers of the concierge that can help us if we need assistance while traveling. I've actually called them twice in my past travels to get help on which hospital to visit when I was sick, and they were really helpful.
Beware of CBD products: Now in Japan, CBD products are getting widespread, and some people find them useful. However, remember not to bring them on your trip because not all countries are acceptable with CBD. It could get you into a lot of trouble at customs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Essentials: Work Items&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're like me, you'll still be working while traveling. The work items that I bring with me are the things that I use daily when I'm at home, so I appreciate it that they also give me a reminder of home when I travel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Laptop (Dell XPS-13) and 65W Ravpower charger&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Two cables that can handle PD and USB-C/USB-A ports&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A dongle that plugs into my laptop's USB-C and gets me connected on HDMI if I need to do presentations, and also Ethernet when it's available&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Moleskin notebook and my Lamy pen. Writing things down on a piece of paper is still one of the most effective ways for me to gather my thoughts. It's also an effective way to pass someone information. I also love my Lamy pen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kindle&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.glocalme.com/product/numen-air/"&gt;Numen Air 5G router&lt;/a&gt; which works as a backup. The cheapest way to get data plans is usually through a local SIM. If you travel to many countries, though, buying local SIMs for each country might be costly. In this case, I usually use &lt;a href="https://www.celcomdigi.com/roaming"&gt;Celcom's Multi Country Pass&lt;/a&gt; where you pay a flat MYR98 fee for a whole month and gets you 2GB per day on 70 over countries.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Others&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Others stuff that I bring along for pleasure:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A few packets of one-cup drip coffee (or pour-over as they are known in the US). I like the coffee from the usual place that I buy when I'm home. They remind me of home and I also get to save some money by drinking coffee instead.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Skipping rope. This is a form of exercise I picked up a few years ago. A half-hour skipping rope session can give me a decent workout. The ropes don't take up much space, and I only need a small area to do my workout. I bought the ropes from &lt;a href="https://www.crossrope.com"&gt;Crossrope&lt;/a&gt;. I have a whole set of four types of rope of different weights, but when I travel I only bring the 1/4 and 1/2 pound ropes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!-- EDPART --&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Packing It All Up&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Packing is done over a period of around a week. I'll gather everything piece by piece into one place based on a list, and get them all into the suitcases while also taking into account the clothes I need to still wear at home before leaving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I started traveling, I used to stuff everything into those big backpacks that backpackers use, but it turns out I can fit more, get my stuff organized better &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; get my luggage weight down by using those &lt;a href="https://shop.samsonite.com/collections/lightweight/?prefn1=collection&amp;amp;prefv1=Cosmolite%203.0&amp;amp;srules=category-position"&gt;Samsonite Cosmolite&lt;/a&gt; suitcases. They're spacious, lightweight, and durable. For longer than a week's travel, I usually have two with me: the 125L and the carry-on smaller type. If we're taking connecting flights, I will have 2- days' worth of basic clothing and toiletries in my carry-on and everything else in the bigger bag. This is to take into account my checked-in bag gets lost in transit, which did happened to me once when I went to Munich many years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been using the Samsonites for nearly 10 years now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;And We're Set&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After all that, everything gets packed into one large and one small suitcase and my backpack. You can see how my luggage
looks like below. We're now ready to go!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="A picture of my luggage for one month" src="https://iqbalabdullah.net/en/images/one-month-luggage.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2024"></category><category term="pycon"></category><category term="pittsburgh"></category><category term="may-2024-trip"></category><category term="travel"></category></entry><entry><title>Weblog Update (Finally!)</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/en/posts/2024/05/weblog-latest-update-2024/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-05-01T13:22:00+09:00</published><updated>2024-05-01T13:22:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabdullah.net,2024-05-01:/en/posts/2024/05/weblog-latest-update-2024/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Updating this weblog for 2024 and my 5-year diary&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Weblog Update&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I finally sat down and got to updating this weblog. I write a lot, but most of my writing is work-related and will go to
their respective blogs such as &lt;a href="https://kafkai.com/en/blog/"&gt;Kafkai blog&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://otp.dev/en/blog/"&gt;GetOTP blog&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://lalokalabs.co/en/blog/"&gt;LaLoka Labs's blog&lt;/a&gt;
and after all of that there wasn't enough time for me to write things which are more personal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Started by a 5-Year Diary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="My 5-year diary" src="https://iqbalabdullah.net/en/images/5-year-diary.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Afiza gave me a "5-year diary" present for my 47th birthday. She enjoyed writing things on it and nearly finished her current diary.
She was recommended to it by a friend, and now she has also recommended it to me. I've started spending two or three minutes at the end of my
day every day to write random things that happened that day in it, and realized the urge to write longer thoughts without thinking about work too much.
That brought me around to updating this personal weblog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Some Fixes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, no point in updating something without fixing things along the way, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Categories&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I realized after all the time I've spent writing that my posts needed to be categorized in a particular way was actually restricting my writing.
I have always been a person who thinks from top to bottom. Categories help if I'm writing for work because we usually have an outcome we want to
achieve and it gives me structure, but when it comes to personal writing, this gets in the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I've decided to just file all my posts under the year they were written and use &lt;a href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/tags.html"&gt;tags&lt;/a&gt; instead as a loose form
of categorization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Non-Translatable Categories in Pelican&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another thing is that sometimes I translate my posts to different languages and I'm using Pelican for this weblog. Pelican does a great job at publishing the
different languages through the &lt;a href="https://qiita.com/agektrombala/items/bc0da1f2bdf9e1f35aeb"&gt;i8n_subsites plugin&lt;/a&gt;, but I haven't found a way to have the categories
(which are decided when you create directories) in Pelican translated. So, just having them as years doesn't require translation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;New Domain&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And finally, this weblog has a new domain. Just like the weblogs of people I read frequently, such as &lt;a href="https://ziade.org/"&gt;Tarek Ziade&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href="https://simonwillison.net/"&gt;Simon Willison&lt;/a&gt;, it just makes more sense to me to have a domain that reflects myself on the internet.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2024"></category><category term="daily stuff"></category><category term="writing"></category><category term="blogging"></category></entry></feed>