<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Iqbal's Weblog - 2025</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/en/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/feeds/2025.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://iqbalabdullah.net/en/</id><updated>2025-06-08T09:00:00+09:00</updated><entry><title>Receiving the 2024 Q4 PSF Community Service Award</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/en/posts/2025/06/psf-community-service-award/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-06-08T09:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2025-06-08T09:00:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabdullah.net,2025-06-08:/en/posts/2025/06/psf-community-service-award/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I received the PSF Community Service Award for contributions to Python communities across Asia, highlighting the importance of recognizing those who champion the language.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;On November 16, 2024, I received an email from &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/denicholson/"&gt;Deb Nicholson&lt;/a&gt;, the Executive Director of the Python Software Foundation (PSF), with the title: &lt;em&gt;"You're a Community Service Award Winner!"&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It appears that on November 13, 2024, the PSF board approved a resolution to award me the &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/community/awards/psf-awards/"&gt;PSF Community Service Award&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RESOLVED, that the Python Software Foundation award the 2024 Q4 Community Service Award to Iqbal Abdullah for contributions to the Python community in the Asia-Pacific region, including PyCon Malaysia, PyCon APAC, and PyCon Japan, as well as contributions to multiple PSF workgroups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a pleasant surprise on that cool fall morning. I feel happy and proud that my peers nominated me, and that the work we've done over the years was recognized. It was unfortunate that I could not be at PyCon US 2025 in Pittsburgh to personally receive the award.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The award was received on my behalf by Freilla Espinola during PyCon US, and Terada Manabu brought it back to Tokyo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Iqbal Receiving the PSF Community Service Award for Contributions to the Python Community" src="https://iqbalabdullah.net/en/images/psf-python-community-service-award.png"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Iqbal receiving the PSF Community Service Award from his friends of the PyCon JP Association&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it was unfortunate that I couldn’t meet my fellow recipients, friends, and receive the award in person during PyCon US this time, it was meaningful to receive the award from the people that I started my community and Python work with. The people pictured above are also past recipients of the award.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be honest, looking at the people who have received the award in the past, I don't think I deserve it. I don't think the things I have done in my community are as impactful or as difficult as theirs. I couldn't have done it alone either, and many people did it with me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, in the past, some friends have confided in me that they don't think they deserve this or that award or recognition because they think their work wasn't significant enough. I didn't quite understand them at that time because I thought they did good work and totally deserved it. So I usually just say something like this to them:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"The wonderful thing is, this isn't something for you to decide. We (the community) are the ones deciding, so don't sweat it. Please accept the gift."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I think I understand how they feel. So with a thank you, I will happily accept this gift and not sweat it. It is an
honour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Nominate Your Friends!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are approximately 10.1 million Python developers worldwide. Around 22% of them are in Europe, and another 16% are in the United States. China, India, and Japan combined account for 52%. Nearly 19% of all Python developers are women.&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
I’m extrapolating from the data, of course, but it’s something for us to ponder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the award was initiated in March 2008, a total of 127 people have received it.
I am the sixth person in Japan, the first Malaysian, and the tenth person within East, South East, and South Asia to receive it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In December 2021, five people representing the PyCon JP Association received the award for their fundraising efforts for the PSF. Before that, in December 2020, Georgi Kerr was awarded for her PyLadies, D&amp;amp;I, PyCon TH, and PyCon APAC work. In September 2018, Mariatta, who is based in Canada but originated from Indonesia, received the award for her contribution to CPython and diversity efforts within the community. Before Mariatta, the award was given to Kenneth Gonsalves of India in October 2012 posthumously for his community work in India, and the first recipient of the award within our region was Noufal Ibrahim (also India) in October 2009 for his work organizing the inaugural PyCon India.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of the ten people within our region receiving the award, two are women, and the rest are men.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are so many of us here that I’m pretty sure you know someone around you who has done or is doing great work but isn’t acknowledged or recognized. So just go ahead and &lt;a href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/posts/2024/05/nominating-pythonistas-at-the-psf/"&gt;nominate them for stuff!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://distantjob.com/blog/how-many-developers-are-in-the-world/"&gt;How Many Software Developers Are There in The World? - DistantJob&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="2025"></category><category term="python"></category><category term="asia"></category><category term="pycon"></category><category term="csa"></category><category term="award"></category></entry><entry><title>Goodbye PyCon APAC: A New Chapter Begins</title><link href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/en/posts/2025/03/the-final-pycon-apac/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-03-03T10:30:00+09:00</published><updated>2025-03-03T10:30:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabdullah.net,2025-03-03:/en/posts/2025/03/the-final-pycon-apac/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;PyCon APAC 2025 marks the end of an era and the beginning of a new journey for the Python communities and conferences in Asia.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://pycon-apac.python.ph"&gt;PyCon APAC 2025 in Manila&lt;/a&gt; will be more than just another PyCon: It marks a significant transition. After 15 years, the community has chosen to retire the name "PyCon APAC" and embark on a new journey for Python conferences in Asia. This change isn't just about rebranding; it's about creating a more sustainable and structured future for the Python community across the region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conference wrapped up on March 2, 2025. Traditionally, we announce the next hosts at the end of each event. The PH organizers graciously gave me a few minutes during the closing to address the audience and fill in the "who's next" portion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The End of "PyCon APAC"&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://pycon.blogspot.com/2010/04/pycon-apac-early-bird-and-tutorial.html"&gt;PyCon APAC began in 2010 in Singapore&lt;/a&gt;, thanks to the efforts of Beng Keat, Maurice Ling, and the dedicated Pythonistas in Singapore. Their goal was to unite Python enthusiasts across the region, bringing PyCon to Asia to make it more accessible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the years, the conference rotated among eight host countries, fostering friendships and proving that Python is more than just a programming language. It's a community. Brett Cannon's famous quote captures it best: "I came for the language, but I stayed for the community."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, as the event grew, so did the challenges. The term "APAC" often required explanation to global audiences. More critically, each year's host had to rebuild everything from scratch—securing sponsorships, navigating permissions, and handling logistics—leading to inefficiencies and the loss of institutional knowledge. Organizer burnout became an all-too-common reality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To address these issues, we made a pivotal decision: &lt;strong&gt;PyCon APAC needs to evolve.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Introducing Python Asia Organization (PAO)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The directors and members of the Python Asia Organization (PAO)" src="https://iqbalabdullah.net/en/images/pycons/pao-directors-pycon-apac-2025.jpg"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The members and directors of the Python Asia Organization posing on stage before their talk (L to R: Kwon Han Bae,
Freilla Espinola, Manabu Terada, Iqbal Abdullah)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To ensure sustainability and continuity, we established the &lt;a href="https://ariregister.rik.ee/eng/company/80644409/Python-Asia-Organization-MT%C3%9C"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Python Asia Organization (PAO)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. This new nonprofit will oversee regional Python conferences in Asia, holding intellectual property rights, managing trademarks, and most importantly, providing long-term structural support for future events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have considered something like PAO since &lt;a href="https://iqbalabdullah.net/posts/2020/06/diversification-is-the-future-for-the-psf/"&gt;running for a PSF board seat in 2020&lt;/a&gt;, noticing the lack of representation from our side of the world—often due to indifference or even not knowing the PSF exists. After discussing informally with my community members, I formally announced my idea for PAO at the end of my &lt;a href="https://tw.pycon.org/2022/en-us/conference/keynotes/"&gt;keynote during PyCon APAC 2022&lt;/a&gt; hosted by our TW friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But let me be clear: &lt;strong&gt;PAO is not an umbrella organization representing all Asian Python communities.&lt;/strong&gt; Each country and community remains independent. PAO serves as a hub to facilitate collaboration, empower community leaders, share resources, and ensure that future Python conferences in Asia no longer have to start from scratch each year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Path Forward&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;strong&gt;new name&lt;/strong&gt; for the conference will be chosen, with an official announcement by &lt;strong&gt;April 10, 2025&lt;/strong&gt;.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PAO will take over trademarks and intellectual property&lt;/strong&gt;, giving the community independent ownership over its conference brand. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Governance changes will be tested&lt;/strong&gt; with the 2026 conference.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The 2026 host selection will shift from proposals to a structured assignment process&lt;/strong&gt;, ensuring smoother transitions and better planning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The host country for 2026 is yet to be decided. One of the biggest shifts we are considering is moving away from the traditional call-for-proposals model and instead &lt;strong&gt;designating hosts&lt;/strong&gt; through a structured selection process. This change will allow PAO to work closely with the host country for 2026, to consolidate learnings from that process and ensuring a seamless transition from one conference to the next from 2027 where we hope to resume the call-for-proposals model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Acknowledging Our Challenges&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As exciting as this new phase is, it doesn't come without challenges. Every PyCon APAC host in the past has faced hurdles securing sponsorships, managing logistics, and navigating local regulations. Despite tremendous effort, much of that knowledge was lost when a new host took over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With PAO, we are determined to change that. &lt;strong&gt;Standardized processes, shared knowledge, and a more structured support&lt;/strong&gt; will ease the burden on future hosts. More importantly, we want to ensure that Python conferences in Asia &lt;strong&gt;continue to thrive, grow, and bring people together for years to come.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Looking Back, Looking Forward&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Iqbal making the annoucement about the 2026 regional conference" src="https://iqbalabdullah.net/en/images/pycons/iqbal-closing-pycon-apac-2025.jpg"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Iqbal making the annoucement about our regional conference for 2025 during the closing (Picture by Calvin Tsang)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a bittersweet moment as I stood on stage for the final PyCon APAC closing in Manila. This wasn't just a conference; it was the culmination of years of passion, dedication, and collaboration among people from many countries. Only a few in the audience had attended a PyCon APAC conference before, so I briefly recapped its history, explained what's changing, and shared our plans. I also mentioned that this might be the last time we use "PyCon APAC", and we do not yet know who the next hosts will be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this isn't the end. It's the beginning of something even greater.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I invite all of you to join this next chapter. We need your voices, your ideas, and your passion to build something that will last for the next generation of Pythonistas in Asia. I also want acknowledge and say thank you to other community partners such as &lt;a href="https://blackpythondevs.com"&gt;Black Python Devs&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href="https://www.europython-society.org/europython/"&gt;Euro Python Society of EuroPython&lt;/a&gt; for being such great examples we can follow that also pushes us forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We also need your sponsorships!&lt;/strong&gt; You can help by sponsoring us through &lt;a href="https://github.com/sponsors/PythonAsiaOrganization"&gt;GitHub Sponsors&lt;/a&gt;, or get your company or employer to sponsor us through our &lt;a href="https://github.com/PythonAsiaOrganization/public-docs/blob/main/sponsorship.md"&gt;Sponsorship Programs&lt;/a&gt;. You're our &lt;em&gt;haligi&lt;/em&gt; (pillar)!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Follow Us&lt;/strong&gt; on our social media channels too:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/python-asia-organization-mtu"&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/pythonasiaorg"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.instagram.com/pythonasiaorg/"&gt;Instagram&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://x.com/pythonasiaorg"&gt;X&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're part of a Python community in Asia and would like to connect with the rest of us, you can find us on Discord
&lt;a href="https://discord.gg/59e7W9yqmx"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The spirit of PyCon APAC isn't disappearing; it's evolving and growing into something better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's to the future of Python in Asia. 🚀&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P.S. I want to acknowledge and thank my comrade-in-arms, Manabu Terada, for his public gratitude about my role in managing PyCon APAC over the past ten-or-so years. All of us contributed just as much as the rest of us.
P.S.S Thank you to Freilla for reviewing this post.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2025"></category><category term="python"></category><category term="asia"></category><category term="pycon"></category><category term="ph"></category></entry></feed>